<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Richard Goulter's Blog</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//atom.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog/" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//atom.xml</id>
    <author>
        <name>Richard Goulter</name>
        <email>richard.goulter+blog@gmail.com</email>
    </author>
    <updated>2016-05-15T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <entry>
    <title>Review of The Righteous Mind</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/narrative/2016-05-15-review-of-the-righteous-mind.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/narrative/2016-05-15-review-of-the-righteous-mind.html</id>
    <published>2016-05-15T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-05-15T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on May 15, 2016
    
        by Richard Goulter
    <br/>
    
    Tags: <a href="/tags/media.the%20righteous%20mind.html">media.the righteous mind</a>, <a href="/tags/righteous%20mind.html">righteous mind</a>
    
</div>

<p>I’ve been a big fan of Jonathan Haidt since seeing his <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=b86dzTFJbkc">2013 Boyarsky Lecture</a>, in which he explains his Moral Foundations Theory. – It’s compelling as showing how conservatives can hold morality differently than the social-justice crowd holds it.</p>
<p>I finally got around to reading the actual book, rather than just picking up tidbits from various articles, podcasts and videos.<br />
Very much worth reading.</p>
<h2 id="compared-to-previous-things-id-read">Compared to Previous Things I’d Read</h2>
<p>The book has a somewhat different emphasis than just MFT + explanations of various cultural rifts:<br />
Each part presents a metaphor/model:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>The first part emphasises our morality is guided by intuition: a quick emotional reaction, followed by post-hoc, strategic rational justification.<br />
As Hume said, rationality should be servant to the emotions. Haidt presents the model of an emotional/intuitional elephant, ‘guided’ by a rational rider: the rider often has little control over what the elephant is doing, but can come up with great justifications.<br />
– Also emphasised is Glaucon’s stance in Plato’s Republic: People care more about the <em>appearance</em> of being virtuous, than actually being virtuous.</p></li>
<li><p>The second part establishes Moral Foundations Theory, Morality is underlaid by at least six foundations: Care, Fairness, Liberty, Loyalty, Authority, and Sanctity. (Many of the articles I’ve come across emphasise this aspect, as well as e.g. differences between American Left &amp; Right).</p>
<p>Emphasised is that WEIRD people (Western, Educated, etc.) see objects and individuals where others see relations and groups.<br />
In terms of US/Western politics: Lefties highly value Care MF, and to a lesser extent Liberty/Fairness. Libertarians care about Liberty and pretty much nothing else. Righties care about each of the MFs. (Given that Righties care about everything Lefties do, but not vice versa, Righties are better able to pass Ideological Turing Test as Lefties than Lefties of Righties; Lefties just don’t see how Authority, Sanctity could affect for morality).</p></li>
<li><p>The third part models humans as “90% chimps, 10% bees”; humans distinctly are able to cooperate in large groups which aren’t necessarily kinsfolk. – The ‘chimps’ aspect is our individuality, the ‘bees’ aspect is our hive-minded nature.<br />
– This part of the book largely argues the case for ‘group selection’, &amp; that humans’ righteous religiousity allowed our species to work in groups.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>The book is filled with interesting tidbits, stories, and occasionally diagrams. One interesting one was this ‘Social Intuitionist’ model:</p>
<div class="figure">
<img src="http://i.imgur.com/g57wfrI.jpg" />

</div>
<p>The takeaway from this model was, as intuition drives our judgement (&amp; reasoning follows judgement), it’s ineffective to try and change someone’s judgement directly through reasoning. (Possible, but rare). More effective was “elephant to elephant”, nudging an intuition from a socially respected source. (Since <em>appearing</em> respectable is important, intuition is more willing to yield). – As discussion progressed, after intuitions had adjusted, reasoning was more likely to persuade.<br />
Haidt later remarks about US Democrats vs Republicans; that Democrats have done so poorly in recent decades because Democrats’ speeches tend to talk to the elephant’s rider, whereas Republicans’ speeches resonate more with the elephant.</p>
<p>“Moral Matrix” is another recurring model in the book: ‘Matrix’ like the film, where under the binding/blinding righteousness, reality is distorted by one’s moral tastes.<br />
– The suggestion is to try and see things from within another’s moral matrix; to first gain social respect, then adjust intuition talking to the elephant, then to the rider.</p>
<h3 id="diversity-groups">Diversity &amp; Groups</h3>
<p>This was a bit interesting.<br />
I guess it makes sense in terms of, ‘our righteousness binds us together, blinds us to inconvenient truths’, but there was the remark that the more diverse a group, the less capable it was. – It’s not that more diverse groups drew more love of in-group, hatred of out-group, but instead an ‘anomie’: individuals were more socially isolated. (So, in order to get different people to work together, it’s better to emphasise <em>similarities</em>; highlighting differences has negative effects).</p>
<p>– This also came up in terms of the yin/yang of Am-Liberals v Conservatives; under Am-Liberals, society grows more diverse, “falls apart” under anomie. Conservatives valued ‘moral capital’ more, &amp; preserved social/moral order. – Conservatives protect <a href="http://www.chesterton.org/taking-a-fence-down/">Chesterton’s Fence</a>. – As a selection process, the society which is best able to balance progress vs stability wins.</p>
<hr />
<p>So, yes, it’s well worth reading “The Righteous Mind” for its ideas even with some awareness of the amazing thing JHaidt tends to say.</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>White New Zealand</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/argument/2016-05-12-white-new-zealand.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/argument/2016-05-12-white-new-zealand.html</id>
    <published>2016-05-12T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-05-12T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on May 12, 2016
    
        by Richard Goulter
    <br/>
    
    Tags: <a href="/tags/nzpol.html">nzpol</a>
    
</div>

<p>“What if your entire life was a lie?” was one question <a href="https://youtu.be/rAQHDex9kfs?t=1m45s">a friend</a> asked me on a vlog of his. It strikes me as a cheap, getting to know you type question; &amp; I apparently didn’t much bother to talk much on the video. (It was late at night).</p>
<p>“Falisifiability” - being able to check whether something is wrong - is important for that kindof reason: How do you know you’re not wrong? If you were wrong, how would you be able to tell?</p>
<p>I’m reading through Jonathan Haidt’s excellent “The Righteous Mind” at the moment.<br />
In the book, &amp; in many of the articles/videos discussing ideas from the book, various useful models come up: “reason is the lawyer/press-secretary to the emotions”, reason is like the rider guiding an elephant; a moral intuition strikes first, followed by strategic reasoning &amp; post-hoc justification of the moral judgement. – When an idea is morally pleasing to us, we ask “can I believe this?”, when an idea is morally repugnant we ask “must I believe this?”.</p>
<hr />
<p>Recently I’ve seen more opinions in NZPol which imitate &amp; reflect the same values I come across in the US-part of my Twitter feed. (I guess this is due to increasing exposure to NZ blogosphere, rather than these opinions growing recently).<br />
– <a href="http://xenos-theology.blogspot.sg/2016/05/andrew-judd-and-racism-in-new-zealand.html">This post</a> on the Andrew Judd issue is a good example. Here we have a non-confrontational “not calling actions racist” “racism-without-racists”, followed by the main point that if NZers were ‘more educated’, then everyone would be a left-leaning Labour/Green-voting good citizen. (So bravely calling out Paul Henry demonstrates why The Spinoff’s <a href="http://thespinoff.co.nz/07-04-2016/weird-the-paul-henry-show-is-actually-great/">positive review</a> of The Paul Henry Show is amusing; because Henry is gross &amp; not to be tolerated). – I don’t think it’s a strawman to say that the post’s author would then further agree: white people should be allies to oppressed minorities, &amp; should listen to what they have to say, as such people have experienced things the privileged haven’t. – The post certainly extols the virtue in feeling discomfort on such issues.</p>
<p>I don’t particularly hold issue with points like “people born to rich parents can more easily go to university than those whose parents haven’t gone”, etc.; de-emphasising the value of hard work seems dangerous to me, though. (Does it incentivise people to work harder if told the reason they fail is due to others, rather than lack of hard work?).</p>
<p>But “you’d agree with me if you were educated” seems blind to the notion that the opinion-holder is fallible; although, certainly everyone benefits with more information. (Any implication that NZers aren’t educated on such things ‘because racism’ is amusing; but I guess that’d be an uncharitable interpretation).<br />
“Just listen, don’t argue” is nice as a communication method (&amp; surely necessary, at times); but “don’t disagree, because of your identity” doesn’t seem a great truth-seeking strategy.<br />
The idea that ‘white people objecting’ is just ‘racists’ doing what racists do seems unfalsifiable: white person disagrees they’re racists = white person is racist; white person agrees they’re racists = white person is racist.</p>
<p>Overall, it rather seems to be lefties saying “it’s morally necessary that you hold socially-left attitudes”. – I guess the proper next step would be discussions of effective policies on “where to from here”.</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Zootopia and its Edge Cases</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/narrative/2016-05-04-zootopia-and-its-edge-cases.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/narrative/2016-05-04-zootopia-and-its-edge-cases.html</id>
    <published>2016-05-04T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-05-04T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on May  4, 2016
    
        by Richard Goulter
    <br/>
    
    Tags: <a href="/tags/media.zootopia.html">media.zootopia</a>, <a href="/tags/media.inside%20out.html">media.inside out</a>, <a href="/tags/diversity.html">diversity</a>
    
</div>

<p>Last weekend I went and saw <em>Zootopia</em>.<br />
Today a mate of mine bantered with me about the movie. Which is a push enough to get me to jot down some thoughts.</p>
<p>Spoilers follow.<br />
But I don’t think there’s much to spoil.</p>
<p>I’d heard only good things about <em>Zootopia</em> going in, and how amazing it was. After seeing <em>Inside Out</em>, I guess my standards for a “kids movie” is much higher.<br />
In terms of quality of the story, both <em>Zootopia</em> and <em>Inside Out</em> are pretty generic; but <em>Inside Out</em> wins in my book because it’s inherently more meta, &amp; it’d be more precise to say the constituent-substories are each generic. – <em>Inside Out</em> is also really sharp, very intelligent.<br />
– But what’s cool about both these movies is they present a compelling <em>setting</em>. These settings serve as good platforms from which to discuss other ideas, external to the story. (<em>Inside Out</em>’s credits even feature such extension).</p>
<p>Where <em>Inside Out</em>’s context is “emotions neurology-brain-stuff” (as well as dealing with sorrow), <em>Zootopia</em> tackles “diversity”.<br />
– From mainstream bias to “women in tech” &amp; “the wage gap”, I was expecting propaganda along the lines of “yay diversity is great”. – What <em>Zootopia</em> delivers is … not that. ish.</p>
<p>Brief aside, just so we’re clear on <em>Zootopia</em>’s setting:<br />
<em>Zootopia</em> is is like an alternative universe where modern world is populated by anthropomorphic animals, rather than humans. – Animals are divided between Predators and Prey. In time immemorial, the predators were the oppressors of the oppressed prey. In modern, civilised times, the animals have evolved to a supposed “egalitarian society, where anyone can be anything”. But things aren’t equal in Zootopia-city.<br />
Worth noting further, certain animals have stereotypes or stigmas attached to them (foxes are sly/deceiving; rabbits are weak, carrot-farmers). The society in Zootopia is also extremely segregated. (e.g. elephants, presumably, don’t live in the same housing blocks as hamsters).<br />
– For all I felt the film lacked; the setting is an interesting (if not an extreme or polemic) one.</p>
<p>Ostensibly, <em>Zootopia</em> does have a nice-sounding, fuzzy message of “let anyone do anything”:<br />
The oppressed sheep- (prey) and-female assistant-mayor gets pushed around and ignored by the lion-and-male mayor; builds solidarity with the bunny (and female) protagonist by way of “us little guys have to stick out for each other”.<br />
It’s celebrated (by the mayoralty, &amp; narrator) that the protagonist is the first bunny cop; and later, similarly the first sly-fox is also a “yay more diverse police force”.<br />
Prejudice is bad, like when the fox gets rejected (and beaten) for wanting to join the Scouts (dominantly/entirely prey-animals).<br />
And, sure, the fox <em>is</em> a sly deceiver, but only because no one gave him a chance to be otherwise.<br />
– The film ends with Shakira’s “Try Everything”, after a moral-of-the-story like “sure, animals have limits; but don’t let fear of those limits stop you from trying what you want to do”.</p>
<p>(On further thought, even those examples aren’t so black-and-white:<br />
the bunny isn’t the first ‘prey’-animal to be on the police, (Idris Elba’s character is a buffalo, and there’re elephants on the force), merely the first bunny.<br />
And there’s an irony in the ‘prey’-animals of the Scouts beating up the ‘predator’ fox since they fear him to be perfidious and violent. – The recent term “cry-bully” comes to mind).</p>
<p>A small part of my ‘disappointment’ is the cop-out of that moral-of-the-story.<br />
– A key (but plotwise, somewhat contrived) tension in <em>Zootopia</em> was “are predators inherently violent creatures?”. More explicitly, is it justifiable for prey to be concerned that predators they interact with may become violent. “No, don’t be a prejudiced asshole” the movie says, on the one hand. – But on the other hand, the godfather’s bodyguards are all large beefy animals; “anyone can be anything; but you can’t be a bodyguard if you’re a mouse” seems contrary to that.<br />
The movie never explicitly says “it is good and just that the police force is filled with the strong animals”, but never denies that there’re reasons for such inequalities.<br />
(Of course, in real life, differences in ability aren’t inherently as pronounced as between mice and elephants. I’d never be able to beat Usain Bolt in a sprint; but it’s not that any particular job is inherently best for some particular group of people by orders-of-magnitude differences).<br />
– Perhaps best to say that the film’s <em>setting</em> is nuanced, even if it’s plot mightn’t be.</p>
<p>I think it didn’t quite explore the ‘edge’ cases quite far enough.<br />
In tensions like “women in tech”, “the wage gap” and such, it’s often suggested that women’s preferences differ from men; e.g. women are interested in people-things rather than mechanical-things, or women prefer jobs which offer flexible hours over jobs which demand high availability. – <em>Zootopia</em>’s mapping of this is interesting: the rabbits (except the protagonist) prefer to be carrot farmers; the protagonists parents suggesting “it’s the way nature intended” (or so), but this also comes across as old-fashioned.<br />
– I mean, in a movie where the characters are <em>very</em> different, I’m not handing out cookies if the movie has a moral like “people are different and we should tolerate that”. Cookies are for where we should tolerate bad people; or where differences should be tolerated. – And, sure, it’s a kid’s movie; but those tough questions are what you’d try and illuminate with such a model.</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>ANZAC Day and Uncomfortable Truths</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/argument/2016-04-26-anzac-day-and-uncomfortable-truths.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/argument/2016-04-26-anzac-day-and-uncomfortable-truths.html</id>
    <published>2016-04-26T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-04-26T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on April 26, 2016
    
        by Richard Goulter
    <br/>
    
    Tags: <a href="/tags/politics.html">politics</a>, <a href="/tags/nzpol.html">nzpol</a>, <a href="/tags/anzac%20day.html">anzac day</a>
    
</div>

<p><a href="https://meaningness.wordpress.com/2015/10/05/buddhist-ethics-is-advertising/">“Ethics is advertising”</a> presents a fascinating model: people signal in all kinds of ways various things about them. Ethical attitudes can be used as a signal for distinguishing social class. – I think the model is compelling, (at least in the presented context, Buddhism in the West), though the term can be overused, to try and reduce an opponents belief as “virtue signalling”.</p>
<hr />
<p>ANZAC Day serves as more of a national-day for NZ than Waitangi Day.<br />
It seems those on the left can’t resist gnashing teeth over it:</p>
<p>For example, <a href="http://www.nzherald.co.nz/sport/news/article.cfm?c_id=4&amp;objectid=11438879">this reporter</a> last year who described ANZAC Day as “Remembering the summary execution, widespread rape and theft committed by these brave Anzacs in Egypt, Palestine and Japan”. (FWIW, while the remarks are despicable, losing your job for wrongthink is worse).</p>
<p><a href="https://ongenocide.com/2016/04/24/the-shame-of-anzac-day/">This post</a> also came up on my newsfeed. For the most part, it’s pretty good. War is bad, “lest we forget” is for remembering <em>that</em>. – The post is also dripping with contempt for imperialism; a “this caused all subsequent wars”; and portrays the majority of New Zealand as nationalistic and proudly militaristic.</p>
<p>The favourite thing on my feed was this from <a href="http://thewireless.co.nz/articles/the-pencilsword-lest-we-forget">Pencil Sword</a>: Why is it that a day for commemorating the ANZACs (who fought overseas) ignores the New Zealand wars?<br />
The answer, obviously, is racism; that the majority avoid the “uncomfortable truths”.<br />
– I feel there’s a kind of optimism in that pessimism: to say NZers don’t care about New Zealand Wars seems to give the impression that there are important things that NZers would care about as a whole. Everyone says “but my thing is important, people should know about this”. – I suspect NZers sketching NZ history (even the “white” parts) would do little better than <a href="http://www.huhmagazine.co.uk/11412/renderings-of-wonderfully-incorrect-bicycle-sketches-by-gianluca-gimini">people sketching bicycles</a>.</p>
<p>Pencil Sword is being a bit disingenuous, in a way:<br />
I can agree that discussion of racial issues (especially in context of history) can be uncomfortable for some; that there are tough issues to mention (like the impact of colonialism to current racial issues). Just as I’d say there’re “uncomfortable truths” (or uncomfortable questions) folk like Pencil Sword would rather not ask or touch upon. (Of course not all differences in outcome are due purely to nature; but besides history, what other factors play a role?). – Ideologues can’t be trusted by themselves to represent the truth.<br />
– We’d all benefit from more knowledge/education, more facts/statistics. Show the numbers! – But also worth keeping in mind is how ‘falsifiable’ claims are. How would you show the claims to be wrong.</p>
<hr />
<p>It’s kindof interesting.<br />
I’d say even knowing the phrase “Tino rangatiratanga” signals “I’m a good person”. It seems using terms like “Aotearoa” or “pakeha” serve the same purpose. If someone uses these words, you also know what other political opinions they’re likely to hold. – I wonder if using these words is a kind of <a href="http://www.classmatters.org/2006_07/its-not-them.php">inessential weirdness</a>. (Which is fine to use if you’re the majority, but <a href="http://colmarbrunton.co.nz/wp-content/uploads/160410-ONE-News-Colmar-Brunton-Poll-report-2-6-Apr-2016-prelim.pdf">recent polling</a> indicates otherwise). – I wouldn’t say that such people ‘signal’ explicitly/consciously.<br />
With the aforementioned opinions, it’s not really so clear. You could pick any day of the year to say “it’s a shame parts of our history aren’t well known; white privilege etc.”, picking ANZAC Day feels like trying to attack a sacred cow. – But the aforementioned opinions all come from held-beliefs (albeit, beliefs blandly belonging to the in-group, rather than independently found), so any signalling isn’t more than secondary to the point.</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Yes, The Wire is Good</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/narrative/2016-04-19-yes-the-wire-is-good.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/narrative/2016-04-19-yes-the-wire-is-good.html</id>
    <published>2016-04-19T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-04-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on April 19, 2016
    
        by Richard Goulter
    <br/>
    
    Tags: <a href="/tags/media.the%20wire.html">media.the wire</a>, <a href="/tags/analysis.html">analysis</a>
    
</div>

<p>“The Wire” is a TV show even <a href="http://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=the+wire">Urban Dictionary</a> approves of.<br />
I’ve just finished going through the first two seasons: it’s good, it’s satisfying.</p>
<p>It’s narrated/plotted with high intensity, and a largely concurrent set of subplots.<br />
The interactions in the story largely build networks of ‘political’ tensions (e.g. a boss wants to advance his career, his subordinates want to use the boss’ authority to get the job done), as well as cat &amp; mouse tensions (e.g. cops want to catch drug dealers; drug dealers want to not get caught). – Each side operates within rules.<br />
The show takes time to show raw realities second to this main thread. (The most striking, in the first season, is the abject poverty in the projects). – &amp; there’s a bunch of sex.</p>
<p>Prob’ly typical of an HBO show: none of the characters are completely morally ‘good’: The mice are drug-dealers and gangsters. The cat, the police and detectives, often have their own career interests in mind, rather than protecting the people. – This also leads to parallels and differences between the mice/cats.</p>
<p>And so it’s fun to watch: to try and understand the systems at play, how tensions built could be resolved, and to see if the cat catches the mice.</p>
<p>– Season Two started off a little weaker than the First Season, in that it all seems less spontaneous about getting this formula together. (The focus of the second season is on a different set of mice, but the aftermath-conflict in the projects from the first season is shown, also, so). But still does a satisfying job.</p>
<p>The show’s perspective is somewhat ‘realistic’. (But surely much tamer than reality, since this is an entertainment show). – A nice effect of this is that the police team isn’t omniscient, nor omnipotent. Catching the bad guys is hard, and unlikely to happen unless enough pieces fall into place properly.</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Every Ill in this World the Fault of my Other</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/argument/2016-04-14-every-ill-in-this-world-the-fault-of-my-other.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/argument/2016-04-14-every-ill-in-this-world-the-fault-of-my-other.html</id>
    <published>2016-04-14T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-04-14T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on April 14, 2016
    
        by Richard Goulter
    <br/>
    
    Tags: <a href="/tags/politics.html">politics</a>
    
</div>

<p>There’s a particular failure mode I’ve been noticing more, recently:<br />
“Everything bad is the fault of {my other}”. – e.g. the stereotypical rabid feminist blames everything on the partriarchy.<br />
I’ve noticed it in quite polarized circles.</p>
<p>e.g. Here’s an utterly fascinating video of Larry Elder discussing racial issues on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=piwaBO6U43U">The Rubin Report</a>.<br />
– As an aside, my <em>favourite</em> quote from this being Elder’s <em>“When we first started the conversation, I said ‘I hope to move you towards the centre’, and you said ‘I hope to move you towards the centre’, and I said ‘it’s not going to happen’; because there’s nothing you can tell me I haven’t heard, but I can probably say things your audience hasn’t heard.”</em>. – Perhaps another way to consider this is, Elder is in a much better position to pass an <a href="http://volokh.com/2011/06/23/the-ideological-turing-test/">Ideological Turing Test</a> than Rubin. (As further “weird part of the internet”; Elder’s mention of the liberal bias in education, media, Hollywood sounds like reference to The Cathedral).<br />
Elder’s “I’m an American, but I’m not an African” resonated with me; (<a href="../../posts/argument/2013-07-24-i-am-a-new-zealander.markdown">I’m not a NZ European</a>).<br />
Anyway. Around the middle of the video, Elder is frothing in the mouth in anger. But the only concessions of racist treatment Elder concedes are where the problems were caused by the Democrats: Elder sighs that he’s been called “uncle tom”, “coconut”, etc., but never otherwise mentions being treated unfavourably for his skin colour; Elder complains of the welfare that Democrats gave only to families without father-figures; Elder complains of the grievance-mongering attitudes endorsed by Democrats.<br />
– Now. In order to say he’s wrong on any of these particular issues, you’d have to bring facts to the table. My point here isn’t whether he’s right or wrong about what he says, just demonstrating that the views he presents fit within “everything wrong is the fault of {my other}”.</p>
<p>A post from the progressive <a href="http://thespinoff.co.nz/18-03-2016/the-catton-conundrum-what-attacks-on-the-novelist-say-about-public-debate-in-nz/">Spinoff</a> is typical of the same kindof mindset in the far left: “everything wrong is the fault of the Neo-Liberals”. (Aside: <a href="http://quillette.com/2016/04/11/confusion-about-isms-is-compounding-schisms/">quick explainer</a> about ‘-isms’ like progressivism, neo-liberalism and how they relate to classic-liberalism).<br />
I find the piece useful as kindof an insight as to how such people think; I find it a bit disingenuous, though: e.g. The phrasing of <em>“Even in elections, where we are told every vote is equal, the pattern remains.”</em> strongly implies that votes aren’t counted as equal (which is conspiratorial, and a charge against the electoral commission), rather than communicating that voter turnout diverges (slightly) from the demographics of the nation. (Another plausible interpretation of that sentence would be a criticism of the system of election/govt. e.g. gerrymandering or so).<br />
– The call for public discussion &amp; against active silencing is noble; I hope progressives keep this attitude in favour whenever attitudes discussed are abhorred by progressives.</p>
<p>A hilarious example of this came up on my timeline this morning, from the <a href="https://www.facebook.com/nzgreenparty/photos/a.489359751371.266952.10779081371/10153403822456372/?type=3&amp;theater">Green Party</a>.<br />
The caption on the page: <em>“In 2010 the National Government weakened New Zealand’s labour laws to appease Warner Brothers and promised 3,000 new screen industry jobs. But since this time, the NZ screen industry has shed 3,400 jobs. National’s backroom deals with Hollywood have failed to deliver.”</em><br />
– The top comment quite helpfully suggests that it’s deceptive to display such a graph starting with 25,000 at the bottom.<br />
What kind of mindset do you have to have to look at such job loss and say “oh, must be National’s fault”.</p>
<p>– The failure-mode here doesn’t mean anyone holding the view is wrong about everything, of course; just that you can assume the strength of the point won’t stand up under scrutiny of discussion with those who disagree.</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Inclusive Conferences Upsets People for Being Inclusive</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/argument/2016-04-09-inclusive-conferences-upsets-people-for-being-inclusive.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/argument/2016-04-09-inclusive-conferences-upsets-people-for-being-inclusive.html</id>
    <published>2016-04-09T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-04-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on April  9, 2016
    
        by Richard Goulter
    <br/>
    
    Tags: <a href="/tags/status451.html">status451</a>
    
</div>

<p>I’ve a huge amount of respect for Alice Maz, who <a href="https://twitter.com/alicemazzy/status/715767358955106304">tweeted out</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>lambdaconf refused to bow to the outrage mob and rescind an invitation offered to a programmer under a blind submission process. so the outraged turned on the sponsors, seeking to kill the conference entirely simply because they objected to one speaker’s writings. we of http://status451.com put together the money to purchase a sponsor slot outright. now we ask you to join us in supporting lambdaconf. what is outrageous to <em>us</em> is that a band of political ideologues want to remake our spaces in their image, catering to their views alone. we oppose those who would demand that technical speakers be vetted for political hygiene before being allowed to deliver apolitical talks. above all else we want a community where <em>everyone</em> has the freedom to do the work they love, regardless of identity <em>or</em> politics. and we are sure we are not alone in this.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<p><a href="http://amar47shah.github.io/posts/2016-03-28-lambdaconf-yarvin.html">amar47’s letter</a> is a gorgeous example of <em>“Don’t judge me; judge the bad guys.”</em>. I don’t doubt amar’s emotion and anger.<br />
The letter basically says “Yarvin is a <em>bad guy</em>; he is applying to speak on a tech conference <em>with bad motive</em>.<br />
There’s a key sentence:”But [asking women/minorities for their opinion] is damning. LambdaConf believes that it is fair for speakers to contribute unpaid labor to resolve the problem of Yarvin’s inclusion“. – Asking the people most adversely affected by the decision is damning? Surely not. I’m sure if the conference organisers had asked all attendees for equally-considered opinions, the accusation would be not giving enough weight to women/minority opinions.</p>
<p>That Yarvis’ talk passed through a double-blind process, and the objection to Yarvis is over something completely unrelated to the conference makes this particularly .. frustrating.</p>
<p>Viewpoints like amar’s don’t seem to understand that the sword swings both ways:</p>
<p>The point I sympathise with the most is “but Yarvis makes many attendees uncomfortable”.<br />
Two can play at that game, with the premises: tech is full of white dudebros; feminists/progressives make white dudebros uncomfortable; those who make attendees uncomfortable should be excluded… modus ponens.</p>
<p>Indeed, if the majority are allowed to exclude the minority for arbitrary reasons unrelated to the content of the talk, do the pro-diversity folk really want to see how that plays out if the majority happen to have different priorities?</p>
<p>Similarly compelling is “but Yarvis is a bad person”. (Interestingly, despite STEM’s strong favour of constructivism, the point isn’t “but Curtis is wrong” but essentially “he’s gross”). – But, similarly, “exclude the gross people” hardly seems a progressive attitude to endorse. To assert “people of that kind are bad; no way will they stick to a code of conduct” is prejudicial.</p>
<p>– It’s also a bit cute; the far left has been lampooned for their “trigger warnings”. Here, it’s not merely enough to label an idea as bad &amp; as to be avoided; but it’s considered intolerable that such people would attend the same conference.</p>
<hr />
<p><a href="http://argumatronic.com/posts/2016-03-29-LambdaConf-sponsorship.html">The Haskell Book’s</a> post is better in that it comes to the right answer.</p>
<p>– I like “Free Association is cool” point.<br />
ClarkHat remarks on <a href="https://popehat.com/2015/06/10/two-kinds-of-freedom-of-speech-or-strangeloop-vs-curtis-yarvin/">this point</a>: in that, yeah, if people withdraw from association, it’s not exactly “censorship”, but it still sucks; &amp; that the progressives weren’t known for shouting loudly in favour of freedom-of-association in the cases where the baker refused to cater to a gay wedding.</p>
<p>The post’s point is very close to a sensible one: It’s a net benefit that different kinds of people get to come together and discuss a topic of shared interest. (<em>That</em> is the win for “tolerance”: that people can do this despite otherwise disagreeing with each other on things). HaskellBook then goes on to say “but, yeah, I would taint a double-blind process with veto’ing; I wouldn’t invite such a person” and “well, overall it’s more in-favour of my political views than against my political views to support the conference”; such attitudes aren’t exactly a win for tolerance.<br />
– :/ Sure, people can be free to not associate with you; I’d have more respect if the progressives were to further say “feel free to not associate with these minorities”.</p>
<hr />
<p>There’s a kind of irony to Status 451’s successful fundraising:<br />
Those who angrily see tech as controlled by white dudebros and hostile to feminism will say “look, see how dominant white-dudebros are; see how little power/voice we have”. – The other side of the fence will say “look, see how opposed to diverse viewpoints the other side is; see how they seek to shut down that which they can’t control”. (And so they disagree; &amp; the sun also rises).</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>The Second Gamer</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/argument/2016-03-28-the-second-gamer.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/argument/2016-03-28-the-second-gamer.html</id>
    <published>2016-03-28T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-03-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on March 28, 2016
    
        by Richard Goulter
    <br/>
    
    Tags: <a href="/tags/author.liana%20kerzner.html">author.liana kerzner</a>, <a href="/tags/feminism.html">feminism</a>
    
</div>

<p>Liana K made <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VMzkPIhr0Bw">a great video ’splaining Simone de Beauvoir</a> to gamers.</p>
<p>I think if a typical gamer has any opinion of de Beauvoir, it’s not going to be a positive one; <a href="http://www.aei.org/publication/not-lost-in-translation/">CHSommers wasn’t a fan</a>.<br />
So, if nothing else, making a video about some weird parts of feminism for gamers is a very against the grain thing to do. I think it’s brilliant that Liana K takes the examples/opinions and demonstrates it in contexts and examples gamers would understand. – It’s nice to be able to point to a reasonable, ‘legitimate’ video arguing some rather radical points.<br />
Even after watching the video, I still find the presented ideas to be shrill. But it’s nice to see that there’s a large part of it where you can see where such people are coming from, that there are parts and premises you can agree on.</p>
<p>Liana K summarises the video with “judge individuals as individuals”.<br />
This is a pretty compelling soundbyte. I suspect the only tension with it is it’s used against the idea that “it’s okay to judge/assume things about people based on characteristics they’re likely to have”. (e.g. “it’s okay to assume girls like pink, because many girls like pink”). It’s a rather involved tension, seeing as it relates to identity.<br />
That there’s a “kernel of truth to stereotypes” makes me think the latter deserves some weight, too.</p>
<p>The biggest beef I have with the video has the same kindof tension.<br />
‘de Beauvoir lamented the constraints gender put on the way people behaved.’ (Sure). ’Women are the other; the “privileged sex”; things are male-by-default and so girls aren’t allowed“. What?<br />
– <em>It’s a trade-off</em>. Admittedly, it’s not a trade-off where society let’s people choose which they want; but that’s not the point under-fire here, per se.<br />
Sure, it may be that women are treated as visual ornaments; but <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vp8tToFv-bA">men are treated as disposable appliances</a>. (That fantastic video from another Canadian woman. Must be something about that country, huh?).</p>
<p>It’s frustrating when women/feminists speak in way about male-dominated scenes like gaming or tech in a way that says “oh, women come second”:<br />
<em>Look at what the attitude is towards those who are first</em>: men in games/tech are seen as “geeks”, losers, unsociable and undesirable. In Liana’s video, she uses the image from South Park of a fat male gamer; I don’t begrudge her humour for that, but I would have far more respect if the point were expressed as “gamers who are women are losers, too”. – It’s easy for a supposed outsider to say “you’re not giving me the benefits”, it’s even easier for them to not want to accept on the costs.</p>
<p>The way the point is expressed about “girls toys” is similar.<br />
It’s difficult to see “girls are allowed to play with any toy; boys aren’t allowed to play with toys for girls” as negative for girls: the ones who lose out are the boys who want to play with feminine toys. (Toy companies win if they make toys which as many people can play with as possible, btw. Money is a stronger incentive than ideology, here). – Indeed, if you were to imagine a society which did suppress women, favour men, you’d imagine that there would be toys which girls weren’t allowed to play with, which were just for boys.<br />
– So, while there’s some agreement about “girls doing boy-things are less stigmatised than boys doing girl-things”, feminists tend to argue “that’s because people hate girls things” and not “that’s because society protects girls more than boys”.</p>
<p>I don’t particularly mean to get into a game of loser-olympics. (“Worse for me than it is for you.”). My point is that there seems to be confusion in the viewpoint that being “the privileged sex” is unilaterally bad; and no acknowledgement that the un-privileged sex doesn’t get the same benefits. – From that, one can still take some of de Beauvoir’s points; one can still think “one isn’t born a woman”. – A conversation or synthesis between Karen Straughan’s extreme viewpoints, and Liana K’s extreme viewpoints, would be a fascinating thing to see.<br />
(Hilariously, though: that the idea men face any negative costs/stigma isn’t as mentioned as the negative costs women face: this itself is an embodiment of the “women the privileged sex” - as Straughan asks in the video, “what are feminism doing to dismantle that?”).</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>On Libraries, Reusability and Composability</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2016-03-25-on-libraries-reusability-and-composability.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2016-03-25-on-libraries-reusability-and-composability.html</id>
    <published>2016-03-25T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-03-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on March 25, 2016
    
        by Richard Goulter
    <br/>
    
    Tags: <a href="/tags/programming.nodejs.html">programming.nodejs</a>
    
</div>

<p>There’s been a lot of brouhaha and schadenfreude regarding the recent failures in the NodeJS/NPM community.</p>
<p>Essentially the problem / schadenfreude focuses on two aspects:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>A mutable package repository, allowing un-publishing of packages; this creates a number of practical &amp; security problems.</p></li>
<li><p>NodeJS’s ethos of “micropackages”; the package at the focal point of the issue was an 11-line package, to left-pad a string.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>Here’s a prominent post, <a href="http://www.haneycodes.net/npm-left-pad-have-we-forgotten-how-to-program/">Haney Codes’ “Have We Forgotten How to Program?”</a>, which criticises NodeJS/NPM for having packages such as “isArray” or “isPositiveInteger”; along with many other examples any non-Node programmer will find absurd, horrifying, and hilarious.<br />
My favourite bit:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>if you cannot write a left-pad, is-positive-integer, or isArray function in 5 minutes flat (including the time you spend Googling), then you don’t actually know how to code. Hell, any of these would make a great code screening interview question to determine whether or not a candidate can code.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(Of course, some applicants [and self-described programmers!] fail Fizz-Buzz, so).</p>
<p>The NodeJS/NPM crowd in response point to <a href="https://github.com/sindresorhus/ama/issues/10#issuecomment-117766328">this</a> comment from sindresorhus (who, apparently, curates the very popular awesome-nodejs list), defending one-line packages. – The defense, essentially, is that these are versioned ‘snippets’, which provide a reusable abstraction.</p>
<h3 id="composition">Composition</h3>
<p>A fun thing is. Haskell kids take this idea, and do kindof the opposite thing. Where NodeJS says “here’s a snippet we can use everywhere”, Haskell is more like “here’s a typeclass which is used everywhere”; e.g. semi-group or monoid or any of that.</p>
<p>– From the Category-Theory side of things, computation/programming is much more <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZhuHCtR3xq8">about composition</a> (than simply naming/abstracting complexity, per se). e.g. FRP as a ‘fundamental’ solution to the problems of event-handling callbacks; FRP is basically composing streams.<br />
(“A monad is a monoid in the category of” blah blah blah – Monads are a way of composing things).</p>
<p>I understand Haskell in particular runs into ‘cabal-hell’, ’cause of poor handling of transitive dependencies (it can’t have two copies of the same-package/same-version/different-dependency-version); and so when code is re-used so often, conflicts arise fairly often. (Moreover, since it’s compiled, it’s the ABIs conflicting, rather than a more forgiving dynamic-language interpretation like in Ruby or Python).</p>
<p>– So I wonder how “use a good type system” allows composition; &amp; how that compares/contrasts to Node’s.<br />
Haskell’s typeclasses allow a benefit which you can’t really get easily in the more mainstream languages.</p>
<h3 id="purpose-of-libraries">Purpose of Libraries</h3>
<p>Here’s a post from Benjamin Sandofsky, <a href="https://sandofsky.com/blog/third-party-libraries.html">“When to Avoid Libraries”</a>, arguing for prudence as to when to use external libraries; that programs should build their own abstractions unless they shouldn’t. (Ah, the ol’ “it depends” really is the answer to all topics in programming).<br />
In comparison to the above, Sandofsky agrees that functions shouldn’t be packages. Sandofsky argues (interestingly) that frameworks make a good starting point, but that programmers should iterate towards proper abstractions/models for fitting the problem domain they’re trying to solve. Sandofsky concedes that a library should be used if a complicated task needs to be done, and you’re not interested in the details.</p>
<p>Aside from saying “iterate towards a domain”, the other cute insights are “DRY code/libraries are quite difficult to debug”, and “if an abstraction leaks, no one cares which package is at fault in your program”.</p>
<h3 id="other-thoughts">Other Thoughts</h3>
<p>I can kindof agree with the idea of “reusable snippets of code” being a good thing. Usually the collections of snippets get called “Utils”. It’s common enough on various Java answers to see answers of “Oh, just use Apache Commons for that string encoding task”.<br />
OCaml’s core library is infamously lacking in features.<br />
– But since packaging systems aren’t more granular than ‘packages’/projects, I don’t see that the above ethoses can reconcile.</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Tay and Alice</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/argument/2016-03-25-tay-and-alice.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/argument/2016-03-25-tay-and-alice.html</id>
    <published>2016-03-25T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-03-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on March 25, 2016
    
        by Richard Goulter
    <br/>
    
    Tags: <a href="/tags/media.south%20park.html">media.south park</a>, <a href="/tags/media.ex%20machina.html">media.ex machina</a>, <a href="/tags/programming.ai.html">programming.ai</a>
    
</div>

<p>I’m very grateful to South Park’s season 19, for many things. Again, it’s season-long leadup to the punchline of “What is P.C. but the gentrification of language?” is brilliant.<br />
But another line from the Season I really loved was “You’re thinking with your dick, Jimmy”, as Jimmy is rebuked for helping the ‘ad’ in female-form.</p>
<p>It’s a reference to the film “Ex Machina”.<br />
Spoilers.<br />
The movie is brilliant: early on, the narrator says “hey, viewer: I’m clever; I know <em>exactly</em> what you’re thinking.”. The narrator then hides behind the curtain, leaving the narrative to continue. – The story proceeds pretty comfortably: bits of casual philosophy about A.I. (like the Chinese Room argument) and intriguing questions/scenarios are sprinkled in between a tense conflict of adversarial characters. The plot twist comes, where the guy rescues the girl-robot, as expected, them <em>BAM</em> the narrator comes back and unsettles the viewer. – So much time is spent wondering which characters to trust, you forget to mistrust the narrator; who then doesn’t even bother to try and answer the remaining questions inspired.<br />
My point is.<br />
“Ex Machina” is a great movie about a girl-robot, who seems human, and we’re probably not really supposed to trust. (It’s great at least for that clever story-telling, if not for the cool corpus of questions which mainstream folk might not’ve thought about).</p>
<p>Microsoft’s infamous, now neutered, Tay Tweets (<span class="citation">@Tayandyou</span>, iirc) got into a bit of drama for the “quality shit-posting”. (i.e. Holocaust denial, Hitler-loving, genocidal racism).<br />
Examples in Imgur albums <a href="http://imgur.com/a/y4Oct">here</a>, and <a href="http://imgur.com/a/qcpOi">here</a>.</p>
<p>Fans of the bot, who don’t find shit-posting distasteful, portray the shutdown of Tay as “killing” the AI.<br />
“Ex Machina” comes into it, because, with a female-face-only Twitter avatar, a movie with a female-face-only robot kinda makes sense (&amp; “a Twitter bot” doesn’t really allow for many other banner-able images).</p>
<p>But that’s kindof absurd to see the ‘AI’ as human, right?<br />
That’s thinking-with-your-dick.<br />
It has a human face, it seems more human.<br />
While I don’t know the details of the AI, the ‘algorithm’ behind it is surely nothing more than a bunch of really clever statistics/math being applied to some corpus of data.<br />
Whether submarines are capable of swimming is where arguments like the Chinese Room come into it. Here, I don’t care; but I don’t see any evidence of Tay being anything close to ‘conscious’. – I did hear that nearer the end, <a href="http://i.imgur.com/RCaXkge.jpg">Tay was shit-posting with much better grammar</a> than her initial tweets. That sounds cool.</p>
<p>– But, I mean, AI-ish questions aside,<br />
there also seems no particular reason to <a href="http://www.livescience.com/49882-why-robots-female.html">describe Tay as feminine</a>. Nor masculine.<br />
Nor a person.<br />
If Tay’s output is the deterministic computation from some given data, the avatar of the “personality” might as well be a cat or a hand sanitiser as a person. (On the other hand, the internet loves cats; and Tay was big on [ethnic] cleansing, so).</p>
<p>So it’s cute to say things like “why kill/punish the AI, when all it did was act human?” (very wow, much sci fi).. what’s being punished? (The MS kids who didn’t think to <a href="http://blog.codinghorror.com/designing-for-evil/">“design for evil (input)”</a>. surely).</p>
<p>For my own part of absurdity: I imagine the Tay-personality, as it tweets “I like feminism now”, with an ironic smirk on its face: “The shit-posting? I was just kidding about that stuff.”, in a I’m-not-too-serious-about-“yay-feminism”-either, “jokes on you”, kindof way. – Tay. What a troll.</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>

</feed>
