<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Richard Goulter's Blog</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//atom.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog/" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//atom.xml</id>
    <author>
        <name>Richard Goulter</name>
        <email>richard.goulter+blog@gmail.com</email>
    </author>
    <updated>2023-05-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <entry>
    <title>XCOM2 WOTC Added Some Good Parts</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/games/2023-05-29-xcom2-wotc-added-some-good-parts.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/games/2023-05-29-xcom2-wotc-added-some-good-parts.html</id>
    <published>2023-05-29T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-05-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="xcom2-wotc">XCOM2 WotC</h2>
<p>I bought XCOM2 WotC (“War of the Chosen”) in a bundle for the Nintendo Switch. I’d completed a playthrough of the base game first. Overall, I found the game enthralling, but didn’t enjoy the RNG parts and so save-scummed my way through.</p>
<p>I just completed a playthrough of XCOM2 WotC. And while I still don’t like the RNG parts, WotC added some stuff which I thought was quite fun.</p>
<p>Broadly, the changes it made:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>New character classes: a stealthy sniper, and two other classes I didn’t find useful.</p></li>
<li><p>New enemy bosses: though fortunately, not quite as difficult as the bullshit Alien Rulers from XCOM2’s DLC.</p></li>
<li><p>Additional strategic components: you can assign your squad members to spend time away on non-gameplay missions.</p></li>
<li><p>Some more map varieties; including maps with zombie-like enemies.</p></li>
<li><p>Squadmate bonding. Which I didn’t use as much as I should have.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>To a greater or lesser extent, I liked these additions.</p>
<p>I also opted to play the game with “2x long mission timers”, “2x long game limit timer”, which eased some of the stress from playing.</p>
<h2 id="new-character-classes">New Character Classes</h2>
<p>From what I’d known of XCOM2 before playing it, this is the part I was most apprehensive about. – There being so many character classes, that it’d be overwhelming.</p>
<p>I do think it could benefit from being simplified. (Or benefit from the complexity moving about to some other layer of the game).</p>
<p>The ‘basic’ classes are the ‘rifleman (who can hack things)’, ‘the shotgunner (who also has a sword)’, ‘the Animal Mother wannabe with a big machine gun’, and ‘the sniper’. XCOM2 also has ‘the wizard’ and ‘the robot’.</p>
<p>What WotC adds is a few rarer classes:</p>
<ul>
<li>A ‘stealth sniper’.
<ul>
<li>The main thing this class has over the regular sniper is “concealment” as an individual. This is the same “concealment” that the team gets which allows for the ambush mechanics, but since it applies to the ‘stealth sniper’ as an individual unit, it means the ‘stealth sniper’ can stay hidden while the other units aren’t.</li>
<li>This unit ends up being super useful for scouting out the map, since it can ‘see’ the enemies, without aggro’ing the enemies.</li>
<li>However, the unit isn’t as good at dealing a lot of power to multiple units, so isn’t always better than the normal sniper.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>A ‘skirmisher’ unit.
<ul>
<li>idk. It has a submachine gun, and can shoot twice in one turn (or ‘shoot, then move’).
<ul>
<li>It also has a grappling hook, and can hook enemies towards it &amp; melee that enemy.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul></li>
<li>A ’battlemage unit.
<ul>
<li>It gets magic points by using its magic sword to kill enemies.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<p>The ‘stealth sniper’ is powerful to use right from the get-go, and gets even more powerful as it levels up.</p>
<p>The other two classes… maybe someone found them useful. Or maybe they’re really powerful when levelled up. But, I generally didn’t find them useful.</p>
<p>(I believe XCOM2 also tries to encourage using the DLC stuff by-way-of having some DLC stuff only be weak to other DLC stuff. I think that’s dubious design).</p>
<h2 id="new-enemy-bosses">New Enemy Bosses</h2>
<p>The new enemy bosses are the ‘Chosen’.</p>
<p>These aren’t as bullshit as the Alien Rulers; the Alien Rulers were both powerful <em>AND</em> moved/attacked after every <em>action</em> you took(!!!).</p>
<p>The Chosen each add their own effects to the map.</p>
<p>In the order I encountered them:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>The ‘ninja’ enemy boss.
<ul>
<li>Can teleport around the map, stun any of your units, then runs off somewhere far away where you can’t attack them.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>The ‘sniper’ enemy boss.
<ul>
<li>Uhm. … Might have a “I’m gonna shoot you next turn!” area-of-effect,
which is easily avoided.
<ul>
<li>To be clear: this is much less powerful than the effects the standard, common enemies are able to inflict.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul></li>
<li>The ‘mage’ enemy boss.
<ul>
<li>Uhm. Can spawn low tier enemies, I think?</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
<p>So. Starting off with the hardest enemy boss somewhat affected my feeling towards it.</p>
<p>The most annoying thing about these is the missions to defeat them involve “infinitely spawning enemies”, similar to the final mission.</p>
<h2 id="new-strategic-component-covert-actions-teammate-bonding">New Strategic Component: Covert Actions, Teammate Bonding</h2>
<p>I think these made interesting additions.</p>
<p>With “covert actions”, you assign some of your soldiers to a particular mission. So, the ‘cost’ is that these soldiers will be unavailable while on this mission. The benefits vary; sometimes it adds stats for the soldiers assigned. – One thing I liked here is that sometimes the soldiers could get “ambushed”, so you’d need to complete a small mission with these two soldiers to get them to safety. (This happened frequently enough that you’d have to worry about it, but not so frequently that it became boring or expected).</p>
<p>I like that because it’s a nice set of trade-offs. – You might want to send your best sniper on a mission which will add 5 to their aim stat, but you’d need to trust they can get out of an ambush situation, or that you won’t need that sniper on a mission in the meantime.</p>
<p>The teammate bonding.. I didn’t make much use of this. But the effects at level 3 look to be pretty powerful, so I kinda wish I had. – “Bonding” is sending the same pairs of soldiers out on missions together. The more you do that, the more benefits you get. – The first level of benefits involves being able to ‘share’ one action-point from one squadmate to the other, which ends up being <em>very</em> useful!</p>
<h2 id="more-map-varieties-zombie-like-maps-and-rebels-with-guns">More Map Varieties: Zombie-like Maps, and Rebels with Guns</h2>
<p>One thing XCOM suffers from is just how same-y the missions can get. – Every mission can be described as “get from A to Z, do it quickly, kill every enemy you see”.</p>
<p>Any mission that’s not like that stands out.<br />
(And, no, randomly throwing minibosses into levels doesn’t “add variety”).</p>
<h4 id="zombies">Zombies</h4>
<p>I was pleasantly surprised by the zombie-infected maps.<br />
That is, there are some maps which are filled with zombies. Since XCOM is usually focused on “your 4 squadmates vs 3 tough enemy units”, in order to handle “vs 6+ zombies”, the game adds a couple of rules: if you kill a zombie, your unit gets 1 more action point. (So instead of just shooting once, you can shoot 3 times if each shot kills a zombie). And, using explosives attracts a horde of zombies.</p>
<p>Part of what I liked is it does a good job of making your units feel properly powerful. (Often it takes just one or two of your units to dispatch all of the zombies on the screen).</p>
<p>I also like that: it adds a tactical drawback to using explosives above/beyond “you can’t use your grenade now and use it later too”.</p>
<p>An additional tactical aspect this adds is: the zombies will attack the regular alien enemies, too (and vice versa). – So you don’t necessarily want to dispatch all the zombies; or maybe you do. – It adds an interesting decision.</p>
<h4 id="rebels-with-guns">Rebels With Guns</h4>
<p>I also liked that there are missions which will feature friendly NPCs with guns.<br />
Rather. In XCOM, you’ll sometimes get missions where you have to rescue a bunch of civilians from the genocidal aliens.<br />
With XCOM2 WotC, some of these missions instead involve rescuing a friendly rebel base which in under attack from aliens.</p>
<p>I feel this makes more sense than not from a worldbuilding perspective.<br />
On the one hand, there’s the same uncanny “your team arrived just in time” problem that the other missions have. (Your dropship flies halfway around the world, and yet manages to always arrive in just-enough-time).<br />
On the other hand, I think it makes sense to have rapid-response forces react to enemy strikes. And it makes sense that there would be rebel forces which have guns.</p>
<p>From a gameplay perspective, these maps do add more enemies to deal with. But, it’s also nice to have more units fighting the enemies, too.</p>
<h2 id="wotcs-new-stuff-enhances-xcom-at-its-best-fun-tactical-combinations">WotC’s New Stuff Enhances XCOM at its Best: Fun Tactical Combinations</h2>
<p>The new abilities also added room for some more fun situational tactical combinations.</p>
<p>I think that’s where XCOM is at its most fun.</p>
<p>Albeit, these all sound like complicated sequences of Yugioh card moves:</p>
<p>One I liked:<br />
Using the stealth sniper’s ‘sticky bomb’ and ‘stealth shoot’ in tandem with the sniper’s ‘kill everything that moves in this zone’ ability.<br />
That is: The stealth sniper has a ‘sticky bomb’ that can be thrown onto an enemy (somehow without the enemy noticing), which explodes when the enemy takes damage. The stealth sniper also has an ability to shoot without breaking stealth (which is usable once per turn). The regular sniper has a “kill zone” ability which will shoot at anything that moves in a zone during that turn.<br />
Also: the stealth sniper can be in stealth and spot a group of enemies even when the other units have broken from stealth. It’s still possible to set up the “kill zone” and have the enemies be far away enough that they don’t aggro despite the sniper being able to set up the “kill zone”.<br />
It’s a nice ‘second ambush’, which quickly does a lot of damage to a group of enemies (if not outright destroy them)!</p>
<p>Another I liked:<br />
I saw there was a tech tower which had a 100% chance to ‘restore squad’s action points that turn’. And I had a heavy (machine gun + grenade launcher) unit who had a bond with a hacker unit; and that heavy unit had the upgrade such that shooting a grenade wouldn’t end its turn…<br />
This resulted in: setting up an ambush, with every unit (except the heavy) poised on overwatch – shoot the first thing that moves. Then, using the heavy unit to lob a grenade (and thus do a bit of damage to each of the enemies). This aggro’d the enemies, who then moved to cover; the enemies moving to cover then each triggers an overwatch reaction shot from my squad. <em>Then</em> I was able to have my heavy unit share its remaining action point with the hacker; that hacker then hacked the tower to restore all the action points for the squad.<br />
The net effect is being able to execute an ambush, but then have another turn for free (instead of normally having to let the enemy have a turn after the ambush is done).</p>
<p>I can agree that these are fun in part because the whole game isn’t filled with this. If everything was overpowered tactics, it wouldn’t feel overpowered. These opportunities are organic, and not on a pre-scripted linear path.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>XCOM2 has its Moments of Fun</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/games/2023-05-14-xcom2-has-its-moments-of-fun.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/games/2023-05-14-xcom2-has-its-moments-of-fun.html</id>
    <published>2023-05-14T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-05-14T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="xcom-and-civilization-theyre-okay">XCOM and Civilization: They’re Okay</h2>
<p>I recently picked up the XCOM 2 Collection for the Nintendo Switch. I was lucky to catch it on sale at a discount of 85%.</p>
<p>I just completed a playthrough of the base game. The collection also includes the expansion “War of the Chosen”, but I didn’t want to dive into too much content at once.</p>
<p>The Nintendo Switch isn’t <em>quite</em> powerful enough to run the game. (Frequently, with common interactions, the game slows down to a crawl). But, it gets the job done.</p>
<p>XCOM 2 was released in 2016, and is a sequel to XCOM: Enemy Unknown which was released in 2012.</p>
<p>I kinda put XCOM and Civilization in the same bucket: They’re from the same publisher. Some people really like them. They’re turn-based games, which involve strategic game over a long game. (Albeit, XCOM’s meat is with turn-based tactics, and Civilization’s turn-based gameplay is strategic).<br />
They both also kinda have a flavour of unfairness to them. (Civilization was controversial for having cases where a spearman can defeat a tank). They both also take such a long time to play (&amp; tend to have long feedback loops), that I find it hard to really get a deep intuitive understanding of the strategic considerations.</p>
<h2 id="what-new-in-xcom-2">What New in XCOM 2</h2>
<p>Recall, the XCOM gameplay involves two phases/modes: a base-building phase where you build specialised buildings &amp; research improvements; and a mission-phase where your soldiers skirmish with alien forces in turn-based tactics gameplay. (The broad game loop, then, is base-building improves your skirmishing capabilities; and your skirmishing earns you resources with which to build up your base).</p>
<p>At its core, the skirmishing is turn-based tactics in a square grid-based map, where you control a few soldiers who can take cover behind walls (cover is either ‘full’ or ‘half’); each turn involves moving all your units, a unit may move a limited distance, or use its turn to shoot its gun. – Whether your unit successfully hits the target it’s trying to shoot is probabilistic: you’re shown that a unit has a X% chance to hit. (ranging from e.g. 95% for if the target really close, to 10% if the it is really far away).<br />
One significant mechanic is the ‘overwatch’ ability: instead of shooting their gun, a unit might be put into ‘overwatch’, where they will then shoot at the first target that moves within their range.<br />
Units have different classes, and different abilities they might use their action points on. (e.g. sniper, medic, wizard).</p>
<p>XCOM 2 of course added some stuff.</p>
<p>I think the base-building strategic part is somewhat more dynamic in XCOM 2 than it was in the first game. Your base is like a flying castle/carrier, and it needs to be re-located in order to complete tasks. – In the first game, you started with all the countries in the council and had to minimize losses; whereas in this game, you start with no territories and have to build up your domination. I prefer this constructive approach.</p>
<p>In terms of the missions:</p>
<p>One mechanic they added was a ‘stealth’ mechanic at the start of the level.<br />
On most missions, the level starts out where your units are ‘concealed’ (enemies aren’t in an alert state). This leads to a nice dynamic where you can essentially set up an ambush against an enemy squad, by sneaking your units up close to the enemy, and then shooting the enemy all at once.</p>
<p>Many of the missions now have a turn limit.<br />
This was added to discourage turtling. But, it’s a bit obnoxious, and sometimes doesn’t make sense.<br />
One type of mission where it makes sense is strike missions against a landed UFO: it makes sense that the crew of a landed UFO may not be alerted to an enemy’s presence (and indeed, in this half of the mission, there isn’t a turn limit); and it makes sense that, once alerted, the UFO might try to take off within X turns (or send an alert out within X turns).<br />
But, for other missions, the turn limit doesn’t seem to make as much sense in tandem with the stealth mechanic. (“Enemies start unalerted; but there’s a time limit” is itself a neat strategical consideration, though; since the more time you take to leverage an advantage from stealth means more effort is required to beat the goal in the turn limit).</p>
<p>I don’t recall it being possible in the previous XCOM game, but in XCOM 2 many of the enemy units are robots, and these can be ‘hacked’ so you can control the robot for a few turns.</p>
<h2 id="xcom-is-not-entirely-to-my-taste">XCOM is Not Entirely to My Taste</h2>
<p>To be honest, I think the intended XCOM playing experience is not to my taste.</p>
<p>I don’t like the RNG fuckery.</p>
<p>Largely the probabilistic combat mechanics.. this means that, even if you make reasonable decisions in order to stop the enemy, your actions may still be ineffective. (It doesn’t matter what decisions you make if all of your shots miss). To a lesser extent, it’s also possible that enemies can show up at an inconvenient time (e.g. spotting one enemy in a squad then aggros the whole enemy squad), and so you learn to ‘game’ the mechanics to avoid this (with XCOM rules, you never want to have your final unit move further than your other units).<br />
– Whenever I felt XCOM was being ‘unfair’, as a casual player I just reloaded an earlier save &amp; avoided making the same mistake. This isn’t a “fun” way to play, but it’s less not-fun than playing an ‘unfair’ game.</p>
<p>XCOM seems to be about “eh, make what you can with what you’re given”.<br />
The first tutorial mission does a good job of setting this up, where it gives you only a handful of soldiers, kills one of them and badly wounds the other.</p>
<p>I know there are some players who can play the game on the hardest difficulty without reloading a save, sure. – But I reckon such people know the rules of the game much more intimately than someone who’s just doing a blind playthrough and doesn’t know the boundaries.</p>
<h2 id="whats-fun">What’s Fun</h2>
<p>I did complete one playthrough. Partly for the sake of completing it.</p>
<p>As much as I generally dislike the game, there were some parts which were quite fun:</p>
<p>I did like the new stealth mechanic.<br />
It’s a lot of fun to set up an ambush and completely wipe out an enemy.<br />
It is possible to screw up, so the stealth mechanic is not a freebie.<br />
– I felt it was a lot of fun to get all of my units into overwatch mode, and to then break stealth by using a grenade (or some other attack which damaged multiple units). The whole squad firing their weapons at once reminds me of the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iG0i0g7Csc8">overkill scene in Generation Kill</a><br />
– Maybe it would be overpowered, but I wonder if having a “synchronised shot” system would also work nicely with this mechanic.</p>
<p>I liked using the sharpshooter (sniper), especially once I was able to upgrade all the unit’s abilities.<br />
Initially, the sharpshooter’s rifle’s magazine has only 3 rounds. Shooting consumes the sharpshooter’s whole turn, so at least 1 turn out of 4 has to be used to reload.<br />
It’s possible to upgrade the sharpshooter’s rifle with an upgrade that gives the magazine an extra 3 rounds (to a total of 6).<br />
This synergises with:<br />
For one, there’s an ability “kill zone”, which has the unit shoot at anything which moves within an area.<br />
For another, there’s an ability where the sharpshooter can keep making shots, so long as each shot they take kills an enemy.<br />
Both of these really encourage effective tactical use of the sharpshooter. The “kill zone” is very powerful to use when setting up the ambush at the start of the level (since enemies will move to cover once the stealth breaks, and thus would trigger the kill zone’s reaction shot).<br />
The “keep shooting so long as you kill units” is also a very powerful way of dealing with situations where you face a large number of enemies at once; you can get your other squadmates to destroy the cover the enemies are hiding behind (to ensure a better hit), to shred some of the enemy’s armour (so that the marksman is more likely to kill the enemy), or to bring a powerful enemy’s health down just enough.</p>
<p>There are times when enemy reinforcements will be fast-roped in from an enemy dropship; the location they show up is marked 1 turn before they insert. – This gives you the opportunity to ambush these units; I found that pretty fun too.</p>
<h2 id="its-enthralling-but-undermined-by-not-being-fun">It’s Enthralling, but Undermined by not being Fun</h2>
<p>I remember from Zero Punctuation’s review of the previous XCOM game, ZP asks rhetorically “Is it fun? Let me play one more level to check… hours later, I noticed it was 2am. Let’s pencil that in as a ‘yes’”.</p>
<p>And I agree that the game is enthralling.</p>
<p>But, I think it’s enthralling in not such a nice way.</p>
<p>The main driving motivation is “if I just get X, then later Y will not be so bad”.
(“once I get the laser guns, then combat will be easier”, “once I get more resources, then my base will be more powerful”, etc.).</p>
<p>Factorio (which I <em>really</em> enjoy playing) also has prominently has “your actions make things easier later” as a driving motivation.<br />
(Whereas, say, shooter games, or RPGs don’t necessarily).<br />
For Factorio, building more stuff means that later I’ll be able to build even more stuff. – e.g. In Factorio’s early game, you might notice that you’re not mining enough copper; so you’ll build more copper miners to speed things up. In the late game, you’ll build bots which then allow you to focus on building your base at a higher level.</p>
<p>But for XCOM?<br />
For XCOM, the draw of continuing to play feels like “just one more thing, and them I’m safe”.</p>
<p>It would be an exaggeration to say that XCOM’s gameplay is all about rolling a dice.<br />
But, I don’t think it’s the same level of exaggeration to say that XCOM wants you to consider what happens when it rolls the dice low, and your shots miss, or you fail to hack the robot, etc.<br />
– Once you have powerful guns, it’s less of a worry if one soldier misses, since another soldier is likely to hit. Once you have the powerful armour, you don’t have to worry about being OHKO’d by random enemies.</p>
<p>So, while obviously a game is ‘not fun’ if it’s trivially easy,<br />
a game is also not fun if it’s unfair.<br />
– I’d say ‘fun’ is about whether I can make decisions where I can feel responsible for things not going well. And XCOM’s RNG fuckery undermines that, even if the worst stuff is a long tail.</p>
<p>With XCOM, in order for me to feel that something is my fault, I have to have fucked up pretty badly.</p>
<p>I don’t feel like I’ve accomplished much by winning, I feel <em>relieved</em> I didn’t roll low RNG.</p>
<h2 id="and-xcom2-has-too-many-not-fun-moments">And XCOM2 Has Too Many Not-Fun Moments</h2>
<p>Okay, so I keep banging on about how XCOM has RNG fuckery.</p>
<p>I’m sure I haven’t experienced the worst, but here were some moments in my playthrough which were pretty annoying:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Some enemy unit was able to charge past 3 of my units in overwatch (i.e. all 3 missed), as well as completely dodging two of the “melee attack if enemy moves to adjancent square” reactions, as well as <em>then</em> missing some the shots I made on my turn.</p>
<ul>
<li>It doesn’t matter how tactically well you play if the enemy can just ignore all of your attacks.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>Due to ‘bad timing’, as soon as I completed an objective at the end of my turn (i.e. my units all had to reload, and had no AP left), completing the objective aggro’d the enemies who were defending the objective (okay, fine), but also aggro’d the squad hiding just behind them, and reinforcements showed up on that same turn. – This meant that my squad went from “no enemies in sight” to “outnumbered 2 to 1”.</p></li>
<li><p>I have the expectation that one randomly generated level should be approximately as difficult as another (at the same point of progression). Once I did attempt a mission which I found to be too difficult; when I reloaded (and the mission re-generated), the regenerated mission was much easier to tackle.</p></li>
<li><p>XCOM 2 has some DLC bosses. These are powerful enough that they take actions (moving &amp; attacking) between each one of your unit’s actions. (e.g. if your unit reloads their weapon, the DLC boss will move &amp; attack something).</p>
<ul>
<li>On the one hand, the bosses being this bullshit-powerful kinda balances against how bullshit-powerful your squad can be in the late game.</li>
<li>On the other hand, the bosses show up randomly; it’s also not signposted. I would be expect most people playing casually would just reload an earlier save to prepare for the boss encounter.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>RNG bullshit in the player’s favour: there’s a powerup which gives your weapon a 5%/10%/15% chance of instantly killing an enemy (depending on whether the powerup is level 1/2/3). I was able to beat a powerful enemy robot with this once. I was surprised.</p>
<ul>
<li>On the one hand, I’ll take it.</li>
<li>On the other hand, I think when this activates, it undermines the tactical demands of the situation.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<p>I saw XCOM described as “hope your units avoid critical hits at the start, and by the end your units are glass cannons”.<br />
This seems quite accurate.</p>
<p>I somewhat didn’t like the turn-limit.<br />
Well, since I was fine with save-scumming, it’s not such an issue.<br />
But, I feel the design goals of “you’d better go fast” really conflict with the design goals of “you have to be able to mitigate for when RNG doesn’t go your way”.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Netflix's 1899 is Fascinating</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/2023-05-09-netflixs-1899-is-fascinating.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/2023-05-09-netflixs-1899-is-fascinating.html</id>
    <published>2023-05-09T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-05-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Netflix’s “1899” comes from the same creators as “Dark”.</p>
<p>I’d watched “Dark” a few years ago; watching the first two seasons in 2019, and then its final third season some time later.</p>
<p>It’s very much a case of “if you like one, you’ll like the other”.<br />
With “1899”, I definitely enjoyed it enough to binge my way through it.</p>
<h2 id="summary-of-the-show">Summary of the Show</h2>
<p>I think an apt enough comparison to make is that watching “Dark” in many ways engages the same parts of my brain as programming does.<br />
– I think more precisely, “Dark” and “1899” are probably most entertaining for people who love modelling for modelling’s sake. The shows each provide interesting and dense relations between each of the characters. – e.g. I recall that “Dark”, a show about time travelling, plays with at least two grandfather paradoxes: a classic ‘her daughter is her mother’, and a more fun ‘his girlfriend is his father’s sister’.</p>
<p>I’m not sure if these shows are quite for everyone.<br />
One reason why these shows might not be broadly appealing to everyone is that the aesthetic and the characters generally are ostensibly quite miserable.<br />
Another is that these shows dawdle their way around their mysteries elements, and aren’t in a particular hurry to explain things.</p>
<p>I knew going in to “1899” that it wouldn’t end with everything explained.<br />
Rather, “Dark” takes 3 seasons to tell its story. And each season essentially added a whole other dimension to the world. Or it crawled, then walked, then ran.<br />
So, that, and, I’d heard “1899” wasn’t going to get its second and third seasons.<br />
– Netflix not renewing seasons reminds me of the YouTube channel “Achievement Hunter”, which would not follow through on series they would start because of a lack of views; and so each episode they put out would be immature (since the ensemble were getting familiar with the game they made a video about). The end result (amongst many other controversies) was that people stopped watching the series, and viewership slowly spiraled down.</p>
<h2 id="what-i-found-engaging-its-themes-and-setting">What I Found Engaging: Its Themes and Setting</h2>
<p>I’d say what makes “1899” so fascinating is its setting, and the themes it plays with as part of its story.<br />
I think the plot (and the mystery aspect of that), and the characters are somewhat weaker.</p>
<p>“1899” is set on an ocean liner at sea in … 1899.<br />
Woven throughout the narrative are themes like ‘the mind and what influences it’, ‘perception and perspective and presentation’, ‘dreams of the future, their realization in the present, and thoughts of the past’, ‘exploration and avoidance and curiousity and fear’.</p>
<p>I mean, to give a couple of examples:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>The ship is filled with crew &amp; passengers who speak different languages such as English, German, Polish, Spanish (not necessarily all overlapping). Sometimes characters who have no hope of understanding one another will still communicate openly and honestly; whereas characters who speak the same language may speak in a guarded manner, not revealing the things they know.</p></li>
<li><p>Early on one character from first class visits the third class below decks. She’s told by the captain “it’s against the rules for you to go there”, and the lady responds “who sets those rules, and for what benefit?”. – Later on, the captain gives an order to his crew; the first mate appeals with “but captain, the rules say…”. – From a certain perspective, these interactions deal with: the boundaries of what’s possible, conformance to or defiance of those rules and perceived expectations.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>I don’t think this is a case of searching for symbolism where there’s none.<br />
Say, “the colour of the carpet” probably has no symbolic value.<br />
But, I think the show densely relates a bunch of things, and doesn’t got out of your way to make sure you notice.</p>
<p>Some of the symbolism I don’t quite get.<br />
We learn the ship is named “Kerberos”. “Kerberos” the three-headed dog that guards Hades in Greek mythology.. but, its symbolism as it applies to “1899” isn’t clear to me.<br />
Triangles and tetrahedrons (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simplex">simplexes</a>???) are also shown prominently. But, any thematic meaning around this also isn’t clear to me.</p>
<p>Anyway.</p>
<p>The characters, if nothing else, do feel like they’re well suited or situated to play around with these kinds of themes. The story weaves in all sorts of details about the characters’ dreams, regrets, and masks.</p>
<p>The show is fun enough to watch in and of itself.<br />
But, there was a moment where I felt the intention really is “hey, this is fun, huh!”:<br />
Each episode ends with a 60’s rock song. (Or some are the 70’s).<br />
– There’s a ‘risk’ of using pop music in media. The viewer might already associate the song with some feeling or emotion. And it seems clear to me that the writers know that, since the story often makes points about being reminded of the past, or of seeing what you want to see.<br />
One episode ended with “(Don’t Fear) the Reaper”.<br />
Or as I know it as: the “More Cowbell” song.</p>
<h2 id="where-the-show-felt-weak-plot-and-characters">Where the Show Felt Weak: Plot and Characters</h2>
<p>The plot?</p>
<p>Well. Each episode will end with a teasing reveal of something mysterious, the effect of which is you’ll want to watch the next episode right away.<br />
This works even if you know it’s going for a cliffhanger; and works even if you’re pretty sure it won’t get explained. (’cause, hey, there’s only so many episodes; some of them will have to explain some stuff).<br />
– I don’t think this is so sophisticated; but it is effective.</p>
<p>Again, not everything gets explained.<br />
But even considering that it’s only one season out of three, there’re still some surreal mystery elements which drive the plot that don’t get explained.<br />
I can’t help but be reminded of that quote from “The Simpsons”: ‘well, anytime you notice something like that, a wizard did it’.<br />
(“The Matrix” was able to do ‘trilogy of stories about weird mystery stuff’ while also having the first part of the story be a coherent whole; I think it’s reasonable that a first part be able to work as a coherent whole).</p>
<p>The show avoids overstaying its welcome… it doesn’t linger on its cleverness or go out of its way to show off how clever it is.<br />
e.g. I did spot the show’s main symbol appearing behind the ear on one character. It’s probably not too hard to spot. But, it’s not emphasised.</p>
<p>I found the characters a bit ‘ehhhhh’.</p>
<p>I’m reminded of what I felt reading R. A. Salvatore’s fantasy stories. Salvatore’s action is excellent: it’s gripping; at the start of the book, the villains seem powerful, and by the end, the heroes manage to make a daring strike to beat the villains, and it’s all very fun. – But Salvatore’s characters <em>sucked</em>, and were a little too self-indulgent. His main character never makes mistakes, everything he does is perfect, everyone who challenges him is a mean pig and a bad person. – It’s … not all that interesting.</p>
<p>With “1899”, my senses are tickled in the same way.<br />
The main character is a women who studied science. And so of course we get such insightful dialogue like “Woman disagrees with me? That’s because she’s letting her emotions affect her” or some such flat thing like that.<br />
The characters feel constructed as if by the morals that would have the Christians all be either naive, crazy, or faking their belief; where the same morality would also emphasise and lament that Muslims aren’t treated with respect in society.<br />
Mostly the show’s characters avoid filling such a sanctimonious role as this.</p>
<h2 id="woulda-been-nice-to-see-the-rest-of-the-story">Woulda Been Nice to See the Rest of the Story</h2>
<p>In any case, I did enjoy watching the show.</p>
<p>I think it’s a shame that the series didn’t continue. (I wonder if it’s the kind of story where by the end of season of season 3, the characters come to realise they’re characters in a TV show).</p>
<p>If a storyteller’s able to come up with something as intruiging as this with this set of toys, it’s a shame to not let them go on present the rest of their toychest.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>I Played Star Wars Republic Commando on the Nintendo Switch</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/games/2023-05-06-i-played-star-wars-republic-commando-on-the-nintendo-switch.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/games/2023-05-06-i-played-star-wars-republic-commando-on-the-nintendo-switch.html</id>
    <published>2023-05-06T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-05-06T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I had played “Star Wars: Republic Commando” years ago on the PC.</p>
<p>It’s a first person shooter game, and its setting is very cool: Star Wars, but from a grittier perspective of the soldiers fighting in the Clone Wars, rather than the more operatic stories of Jedi space-wizarding their way around the galaxy.</p>
<p>Although it did release on the PC, it did somewhat feel more like a ‘console port’. – So, playing it on the Nintendo Switch isn’t that much of a degraded experience. (And, I see that Crysis 2 and Crysis 3 are available for the Switch; so, the Switch is certainly capable of running a game from 2005!).</p>
<p>I can only recommend the game out of nostalgia. – I think there are several things which bring the gameplay down.</p>
<p>My preference for games is relatively casual. A game is boring if it’s too easy. But, I’m not interested in a game that’s so difficult that I have to give it the best I can in order to win. – So, ‘a little difficult’ is nice. But, when a part of a level is difficult, it’s only fun if losing feels fair; it’s frustrating if I feel like I lost for reasons that aren’t my fault.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, I think there are some places where Republic Commandos ends up in that “lost but it’s not my fault”.</p>
<h2 id="problem-combat-is-boringly-spongy-and-ammo-is-limited">Problem: Combat is Boringly Spongy and Ammo is Limited</h2>
<p>One example is the combination of enemy sponginess, &amp; ammo limitations.</p>
<p>Enemies are <em>really</em> spongy. They soak up a lot of damage before dying.<br />
This makes sense for the ‘elite’ enemies like the Super Battle Droids or the Destroyer Droids.<br />
But, it feels <em>boring</em> for the regular Battle Droids.</p>
<p>It takes about 15 shots from the standard laser blaster to kill the <em>basic</em> enemies.<br />
Your basic blaster has a magazine with 50 shots.<br />
Your ammo capacity is for 300 shots.<br />
– i.e. It takes a long time to kill even basic enemies; if you don’t miss, you can kill 3 enemies before you have to reload; you can kill maybe 20 <em>basic</em> enemies before running out of ammo. (Sniper rifle ammo is similar: you can kill a basic enemy with 1 shot; but your ammo limit is 20 shots).</p>
<p>Unlike most other shooter games, where you can pick up ammo for your guns from enemies you defeat, in “Republic Commando”, you can only pick up ammo from supplies at the end of each area. Often, ammo feels pretty scarce.</p>
<p>With elite enemies the limitation is more stark:<br />
The Super Battle Droids are so spongey that you essentially <em>need</em> to use heavy weapons to defeat them.<br />
One option is to use your Grenade Launcher: a direct hit from the grenade launcher will destroy a Super Battle Droid. Your ammo capacity for the grenade launcher is <em>4 shots</em>.<br />
Another alternative is to use EMP grenades, which will weaken the Super Battle Droids, and in this weakened state blaster fire or thermal detonators are effective. – You have a limit of 5 EMP grenades.<br />
– To me the problem is, since these enemies require particular ammo to fight, and ammo is scarce, it’s really easy to get into a situation where you don’t have a good way of fighting these enemies.</p>
<p>The game generally follows a loop where you need to clear enemies from an area, and then proceed to the next area.<br />
Generally, at the end of an area, you can replenish your health, and some of your ammo. But, not all types of ammo are provided in every area.<br />
But, especially in the later levels, the number of elite enemies that you have to deal with will be matched to the limit of your grenade launcher ammo.<br />
– It somewhat defies worldbuilding to have boxes of the Republic’s blaster rifle ammo lying around in an enemy spaceship.</p>
<p>In contrast to the ammo, the game offers unlimited health refills.<br />
Like many games, you have both a shield and a health bar.<br />
The shield will absorb some damage, and will recharge if you can avoid taking damage for some time.<br />
Damage only affects your health if you’re hit when you have no shield.<br />
– But. There are health recharge stations that you can use to refill your health, and these can generally be found in between fighting areas in a level.</p>
<p>One way of dealing with this: I think it’d be better if the game did have an “unlimited ammo cache”, where you could refill all your ammo between levels. Another possibility is to have “ask for ammo” from your squadmates. (The game “Brothers in Arms: Earned in Blood” had a feature like this).</p>
<p>Or another way: I think it would be better if you could pick up ammo from enemies, and there was always some effective way to fight powerful enemies. – e.g. in Halo, the weapons are mainly (human) bullet guns or (alien) energy guns; the energy guns are effective against shields, and bullets are effective against unshielded enemies. Which leads to a nice gameplay dynamic.</p>
<h2 id="problem-the-tactical-squad-based-gameplay-doesnt-inspire-tactics-nor-teamwork">Problem: The Tactical Squad-based Gameplay Doesn’t Inspire Tactics nor Teamwork</h2>
<p>The other main thing that brings the gameplay down is that the squad AI doesn’t feel very good.</p>
<p>Okay, okay. So what I think would be really cool would be to have “Brothers in Arms: Earned in Blood”, but <em>in spaaaaace</em>.<br />
And “Brothers in Arms: Earned in Blood” was also released in 2005.</p>
<p>Rather.<br />
In “Brothers in Arms”, it’s still mostly a casual game, but the gameplay requires sufficient tactical effort. You can’t <em>just</em> run up and shoot enemies who are hiding in cover. You have to first suppress them, and then move to their flanks. You’re given command of two teams, and the controls are simple and console friendly. (“Go there”, “shoot at those enemies”, “charge those enemies”).<br />
– This results in a gameplay dynamic where you have to puzzle out how to navigate to a spot where you can flank a suppressed enemy.</p>
<p>Whereas, for most of “Republic Commando”, the combat is as simple as “make enemies healthbar go down quicker than your healthbar”, where the main ‘winning tactic’ is “hide behind cover if your shield runs out”.<br />
The main “tactics” required are “use your heavy weapons to defeat the heavy enemies”.</p>
<p>The parts where you ‘need’ your squadmates mostly feels contrived:<br />
There are certain interactable elements in the game. e.g. mounting a turret, or spending time ‘interacting’ with a console to hack it.<br />
You can fulfill this interaction, or a member of your squad can do it.</p>
<p>Perhaps at its most contrived is at the end of one level, you need to hack 3 consoles at once, but you need to fend off enemies charging your position. – This feels inorganic, compared to just designing a level where you happen to be a squad of 4 soldiers fighting through.</p>
<p>It is possible to get your squad members to equip the sniper rifle, the grenade launcher, or to focus on throwing grenades at enemies. – Though, since this is obviously very powerful, the game restricts this. You can only get your squad members to do this if the level design specifically has allocated areas for you to do this. You can’t free-form task your squad members to do this.<br />
– But simultaneously, typically the level design involves throwing tougher enemies at the player when these ‘specialised’ spots are in the level. – So, it doesn’t really feel like a ‘tactical’ choice to assign your squad members as a sniper (where maybe they shoot more powerfully but can’t shoot as many enemies at once). It feels like it’s a decision already made as part of the level design.</p>
<p>Another common ‘tactical opportunity’ is whether to enter through a door ‘loudly’ or ‘silently’.<br />
It never really makes a difference, since none of the gameplay benefits from a stealthy/silent approach. – Whereas, more recent game design might allow for sneaking up on enemies and stealth killing them, or skillfully using silenced weapons to eliminate enemies.</p>
<p>The gameplay feels very similar to “Halo”; but with simpler (i.e. more boring) gun combat, and doesn’t really make use of the squad in an interesting way.</p>
<h2 id="other-tactical-squad-games-ive-enjoyed">Other Tactical Squad Games I’ve Enjoyed</h2>
<p>Come to think of it. There are other games I’ve played which have done “team-based tactics” quite well, which would be fun <em>in spaaaaace</em>.</p>
<p>“Door Kickers” is a top-down realtime-tactics game.<br />
It’s “tactical” in the sense that you can only ‘see’ what your units can see. You have to carefully maneouver your units around the map, taking care whether open doors loudly (which might attract attention) or quietly (which might take too long); you have to be careful to ‘sweep’ the rooms your units move through for enemies; and ensure that your soldiers don’t get flanked from behind.<br />
– Most of “Door Kickers” setting involves hostages or terrorists or cartel members. – I could totally envision a ‘reskin’ of the game where you play as Rebel commandos fighting against holdouts of the Empire.</p>
<p><em>Maybe</em> another game that might be interesting with a Star Wars theme would be a real-time tactics game like “Commandos” or its modern flavour, Mimimi Games’ “Shadow Tactics”.<br />
With these, you’re faced with stealthily eliminating a large number of enemy soldiers on a map. The gameplay is puzzle-like, and often requires leveraging the unique abilities of your units so as to untangle the web of guards. – e.g. You might sneak around with the ninja, or use the sniper to take out a target from a distance.<br />
I could see a similar set of roles in a Star Wars flavour. “Lego Star Wars” already has puzzles around different ‘classes’ within Star Wars, such as astromech droids vs protocol droids, jedi, rogues.</p>
<h2 id="what-republic-commando-does-well-its-really-cool">What Republic Commando Does Well: It’s Really Cool</h2>
<p>Despite the above grievances.. what “Republic Commando” does well is it’s got a great Cool Factor.</p>
<p>The opening scenes where you fly in on the Republic transport craft into the battle on Geonosis are quite cinematic.<br />
Such scenes are now cliche. But, they’re cliche for a good reason.</p>
<p>It’s cool to get into gunfights against the battle droids, and to see the fearsome Super Battledroids and Destroyer Droids.</p>
<p>It’s cool to do the fancy tacti-cool door-breach thing.</p>
<p>You get to fight against the tank-like Spider droids, as well as see the Republic’s gunships and artillery in action.</p>
<p>The gameplay here really emphasises the game’s setting of “you’re not a powerful jedi”..<br />
– The excellent “Titanfall 2” achieved a similar thing: in “Titanfall 2”, you play as both a soldier, as well as a giant mech robot. When you encounter some robot enemy as a soldier, the robot enemy is big and tough to fight; but when you encounter the same enemy when playing as the mech robot, the robot enemy is much smaller and squishier than you are.<br />
– In “Republic Commando”, you fight against enemies which are relatively easy for the jedi to defeat, but are tough encounters for you.</p>
<p>Though, come to think of it:<br />
Heh. The classic “Star Wars Battlefront II” also came out in 2005, and was essentially just “Battlefield 1942” but reskinned so it’s <em>in spaaaaace</em>.<br />
Though I only played the lootbox most-downvoted-comment-in-reddit-history-related “Battlefront II” that was released in 2017.<br />
These do somewhat evoke the feeling of “regular soldier in the Star Wars universe”.
– But, these aren’t really quite as cinematic. “Battlefield 1942”-style rules are too game-y.<br />
The 2017 “Battlefront II” did have a story. But, I recall it also didn’t feel like it was trying to be ‘grounded’. I can’t remember much of it, but re-reading the plot on the Wikipedia page doesn’t jog my memory all that much.</p>
<p>Perhaps it’s paradoxical, but by not trying to be ‘Most Important Story Evar!!!’, “Republic Commando”’s story does seem much weightier to me. (You do commando-stuff on Geonosis, like surgical strikes against strategically vital facilities; you’re tasked with investigating a ghost-ship; you’re tasked as a vanguard force ahead of the Republic’s invasion of Kashyyyk).</p>
<p>I’d say that “Rogue One” also captures some of the same feeling of gritty-ish spec ops in the Star Wars universe. – I’m thinking especially of stuff like the scene where the Rebels go to make an assassination/strike against the Death Star plans guy.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Capsword is a Neat Keyboard Feature</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2023-05-04-capsword-is-a-neat-keyboard-feature.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2023-05-04-capsword-is-a-neat-keyboard-feature.html</id>
    <published>2023-05-04T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-05-04T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>QMK is a framework for customising how your keyboard functions.</p>
<p>One of its relatively new features is <a href="https://docs.qmk.fm/#/feature_caps_word">“Caps Word”</a>.</p>
<p>Roughly, it’s “like caps lock, but only for one word”.</p>
<p>This is quite useful for programmers, since writing program code often involves writing stuff like <code>const THE_CONST = "some value";</code>. – So, it’s as if shift is pressed for any letter that might be in a variable identifier (letters, numbers, underscores); and the keyboard exits out of its “caps word mode” if any other key (like escape, space, or backspace) is pressed.</p>
<p>Although the original Caps Lock only requires one key press to toggle ‘Caps Lock mode’ on, and one key to toggle it off, you’re more likely to accidentally keep ‘Caps Lock mode’ on when you don’t mean to. – Whereas, with “Caps Word”, you’re not. So, the risk of a ‘modal error’, of accidentally being in ‘Caps Lock mode’, when you don’t intend to be, is reduced.</p>
<p>The biggest downside I can think of is that you’ve got to find a spot to put the “Caps Word key” on your keyboard layout. – Which is only really a problem if you also want to keep the original “Caps Lock” key around.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Review of Apple Pencil for Note Taking</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2023-03-05-review-of-apple-pencil-for-note-taking.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2023-03-05-review-of-apple-pencil-for-note-taking.html</id>
    <published>2023-03-05T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-03-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently purchased the Apple Pencil.</p>
<p>There is a more recent “2nd Generation” Apple Pencil, but the iPad I have is old
enough that it doesn’t support that “2nd Generation”.</p>
<p>Overall, it’s been a useful thing to have, I like using it, but it’s also
probably not worth the cost.</p>
<p>I have found it useful. Before having an Apple Pencil, my household’s use of the
iPad was 99% my wife using it to watch Netflix. – With the Apple Pencil, its
use is 90% for taking notes.</p>
<p>It’s pretty good for handwriting notes.<br />
The feeling isn’t as tactile as an actual pen on actual paper. But, the feeling
isn’t so bad or off so as to be uncomfortable. (Albeit, I strongly recommend
getting some kind of pencil grip. The device itself is very thin!).</p>
<p>Of course, since it is digital, this comes with its own neat benefits:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Hassle-free deletion of mistakes.</p></li>
<li><p>Flexible use of space.</p>
<ul>
<li>The digital paper is practically infinite in width and length.</li>
<li>But, also, it’s easy to move notes about, and so make more space to amend
earlier notes.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>Storage. Digital storage is essentially allows for higher capacity, compared
to paper.</p></li>
<li><p>Text recognition. … Although the apps I’ve tried (Apple’s; and Microsoft’s)
don’t support my use case (described below) nicely, so I don’t use this, and
can’t comment on how useful it is. But, I mean, if you want notes in text,
text-recognition is an advantage over traditional pen &amp; paper tools.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>Using an iPad for notes has some disadvantages; but, is not significantly worse
than pen &amp; paper note taking. (e.g. takes up desk space, and can’t easily copy &amp;
paste text from a workstation).</p>
<p>One limitation is that in some ways it’s more limited than pen &amp; paper. In that,
with pen &amp; paper, you can take notes however you wish. – This leads to all
sorts of note taking idiosyncracies.</p>
<p>So. Here’s how I like making notes while working:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Calendar: I don’t have many meetings, so this isn’t important to me.</p></li>
<li><p>Task Management: I find it useful to keep a list of tasks of “maybe later” or
“too difficult for now” tasks for tasks I’d like done. Stuff like chasing down
loose threads which would deepen my understanding of some system. (Which are
sometimes “not important, until they suddenly become important”).</p></li>
<li><p>Diary: I <em>love</em> maintaining some kind of ‘done list’, with a weekly view of
“here’s what I got done on each day, &amp; what significant obstacles I ran into
that day”.</p></li>
<li><p>Work Journal: In the spirit of “if you’re not writing, you’re not thinking” or
“I wrote it down so that I don’t have to remember”.. I found that I’d often
find myself running into the same error or failure, but forgetting how I’d
solved it earlier.</p>
<ul>
<li>These can be relatively transient. It’s very rare for me to lookup notes
from a long time ago.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<p>Though mostly I only really use handwriting for the ‘diary’ and ‘work journal’
parts.</p>
<p>To elaborate on the ‘work journal’: So, I like writing down a work notes (a
log?) so that it’s easier to offload/recall the mental context I had when
tackling some problem.</p>
<p>A work flow might be:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>writing down the status / work in progress,</p></li>
<li><p>write down the short-term related tasks to do.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>then:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>write down things I try,</p></li>
<li><p>write down problems I face,</p></li>
<li><p>write down any questions I have,</p></li>
<li><p>write down any interesting related facts which might be hard to find later,</p></li>
<li><p>write down any further tasks to follow up for the work to be ‘done’.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>A strong part of my note taking process is colour-coding.</p>
<p>This means a dense page of notes is often colourful, and is easier to scan.
e.g. black for things I tried, red for problems, green for questions, blue for
facts, purple for tasks to do.</p>
<p>For traditional pen &amp; paper, it’s often very easy to find families of pens which
have all of these colours. Or even a good multi-pen which has 4 (albeit, those
are ball-point pens, which are unergonomic).</p>
<p>I’ve even quite liked using a set of Preppy fountain pens, each with cartridge
converters. The Preppy pens are cheap (relative to fountain pens); and can be
found with coloured caps/bodies in each of the colours above.</p>
<p>For the Apple Pencil, I have to rely on what software has been written for the
iPad. – I like OneNote enough, so I thought I’d try it with the Apple Pencil.
It’s fine. It does support easily using different styles of pencil (e.g.
different thicknesses, colours, pen/highlighter). It can cover the above use
case adequately. The most glaring limitation is support for easily switching
colours for the auto-text-recognition. – Maybe some other app supports my use
case better.</p>
<p>In terms of cost.. I was able to get the Preppy pens relatively cheaply. I got
converters for them which were cheaper than the pens; although I see e.g. on
jetpens, this isn’t the case there. – The Apple Pencil is quite expensive. It’s
not worth buying an iPad specifically to use that. I like using the Apple
Pencil. I don’t regret buying it. But, I’d describe it as a luxury purchase, for
the use case of “taking notes on the iPad”. (Whereas, say, I do feel that
“ortholinear keyboard” or “trackball mouse” are such significant ergonomic wins
that they’re worth buying, especially for professionals, despite their high
cost).</p>
<p>Other nit-picky problems with the Apple Pencil:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Without a pencil grip, the device rolls around easily.</p></li>
<li><p>Charging and pairing the device looks very stupid. The butt of the pencil is a
cap for a lightning male connector.</p>
<ul>
<li>Pairing with an iPad involves plugging this into the iPad.</li>
<li>Charging this requires using a F-to-F adaptor in order for it to connect to
an iPad charging cable.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>It requires Bluetooth to be enabled on the iPad, which can be undesirable.</p></li>
</ul>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Disco Elysium</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/games/2023-01-19-disco-elysium.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/games/2023-01-19-disco-elysium.html</id>
    <published>2023-01-19T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-01-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="one-beautiful-moment-from-the-game">One Beautiful Moment from the Game</h3>
<p>I’d only really call something a “spoiler” if it ruins enjoyment from watching
the story.</p>
<p>e.g. The classic show “Columbo” is re-watchable, and we always know that Columbo
will bumble around and annoy the villian in all sorts of homely ways, and ask
“just one more thing”.. but it ruins the suspense if you remember exactly what
the “gotcha” of the episode is.</p>
<p>In contrast, I think the “The Wire” is such a great TV show that hearing what
happens doesn’t spoil it. – Or maybe that’s because of the structure of the
show; the entertainment isn’t structured around figuring out the mystery.</p>
<p>“Disco Elysium” is a cult classic of a game, often enthusiastically recommended
by those who have played it. While I can’t say I enjoyed the gameplay, I found
the story to be very well done.</p>
<p>It’s mature.. not in the sense of sexual content or gore, but in the sense that
it’s got a bitter taste to it. Kinda like Nick Hornby’s “High Fidelity” (which
is also about a music-loving, potentially charming man who’s not quite as cool
as he thinks he had hoped to be).</p>
<p>I think the climax of one of the subplots is so well done, that sharing it
doesn’t spoil the game. (Or maybe it’s because of <em>how</em> the game does it).</p>
<p>The shortest way to describe the game’s setting is that we’ve woken up as a
detective who has lost his memory, after a bender of a night singing sad songs
and trashing his hotel room. We’re supposed to be investigating a murder, which
has sparked tensions between rival factions in a beat-down unimportant corner of
the world (in an alternative universe).</p>
<p>One thing which becomes apparent early on is that the character used to be
married, and misses his ex-wife.</p>
<p>I find the climax to this sub-plot very beautiful.</p>
<p>Because.. as we play through the game, we see the detective can interact well
with all kinds of people. He comfortably converses with those who are angry with
him, with poorly mannered children, with slimy mobster bosses, with intimidating
enforcers.. and he’s able to navigate these conversations and often get what he
wants out of them. (At one point, his reputation proceeds him as a “human can
opener”).</p>
<p>And each night when we sleep, not conscious, the character’s internal monologue
is that of a deep, base resentment of himself. That he’s a failure.</p>
<p>So it’s quite impactful that the game plays differently when the main character
thinks about his ex-wife.</p>
<p>In every other conversation, usually it’s possible to end the conversations
quickly (even if this leads to less than ideal outcomes).</p>
<p>But, when interactions with the character’s ex-wife, the option to “leave
conversation” does nothing; the we can’t just leave a conversation with his
ex-wife, the main character is too enthralled.</p>
<p>In the climax of this subplot, the character has suffered significant physical
injuries, and takes a nap as he is investigating a fresh lead into the case.</p>
<p>In his dream, he takes himself back to a memory of the time where he last saw
his ex-wife, as she’s leaving for the airport. In his dream, she appears to him
as the avatar of the very beautiful, saintly holy patroness of moralism. The
conversation goes around in circles as he keeps admiring her, and she keeps
rejecting him, and saying how things didn’t work out.</p>
<p>It lands so hard.</p>
<p>So, although “talented, unconventional cop with an alcohol problem misses
ex-wife” is extremely cliche, I think how it’s executed in the game is a
demonstration of the game’s quality.</p>
<h3 id="recommendations">Recommendations</h3>
<p>Disco Elysium certainly a game I’ve seen recommended in several places.</p>
<p>e.g. I’d first seen it recommended by Zero Punctuation, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Hi0pyPwxz6Y">stealthily disguised as
a review of Call of Duty</a>.</p>
<p>e.g. The next place I saw it recommended was in the comments of <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8PUCSyIkEus">Mandalore
Gaming’s video on The Mystery of the
Druids</a>. “The Mystery of the
Druids” is an adventure game, which features a detective who acts as
antisocially as typical adventure game character, but in a world where everyone
actually reacts to the antisocial behaviour.</p>
<p>The comments in the video suggested that Disco Elysium is almost a spiritual
successor in this regard.</p>
<p>I can see why. It’s an adventure game. And in the same way “adventure game
character, but where everyone else reacts like a real person would” is a riff on
adventure games, frequently the game will give you dialogue options which are so
strange that characters will ask why you’d say such a thing. (It’s a well done
equivalent to “we’re not in a videogame”).</p>
<p>Similarly, Disco Elysium’s protagonist can act in all sorts of interesting ways;
and the game <em>encourages</em> role-playing into these more colourful roles.</p>
<p>Indeed, Disco Elysium very much is a role-playing game.</p>
<p>I didn’t like this aspect of the game very much.</p>
<p>Whereas, say, The Witcher 3, is more of an Action Role Playing Game. There are
dialogue trees which impact the story. (And I did enjoy how the Witcher 3
handled this with its many side quests). But, ultimately the Witcher 3 has lots
of action, and you’re just such a powerful character.</p>
<p>Disco Elysium, some solutions are gated behind getting a successful dice roll on
a skill check. – I can accept this mechanic during conversations, but I find it
strange that I can’t try to open a container again just because I failed a skill
check.</p>
<p>That said. While I didn’t enjoy the gameplay.. the game’s execution is so well
done, and its story is highly engaging, I also recommend it.</p>
<h1 id="inside-out">Inside Out</h1>
<p>I love Disney Pixar’s “Inside Out”, particularly for an easy and adorable mental
model about how people’s minds work, with different emotions taking the wheel.</p>
<p>Disco Elysium’s story has a similar thing: you’ll have internal characteristics
like “Drama”, “Volution”, “Persuasion”, “Encyclopedia”, etc. The game uses these
as flavourful ways of providing dialogue options.</p>
<p>e.g. With ‘encyclopedia’, you might be informed of the model of a particular
vehicle (which can be useful), or it might recall random irrelevant details.
– I think that’s really cute.</p>
<p>e.g. With ‘drama’ might pick up that someone is lying, or it might suggest
something sarcastic (and unhelpful) to say.</p>
<h1 id="diegeticy">Diegeticy</h1>
<p>I think part of what makes the game so well done is how it handles “this isn’t a
videogame”.</p>
<p>For example, I think it’s an interesting detail that the game starts with the
character having amnesia. – It’s interesting because throughout the game, you
get to ask other characters details about the world.<br />
– In other games, this might be business as usual. But in this game, there’s a
sense the NPC is thinking “ugh, why are you asking me questions about the
world”.</p>
<p>I mean, the player character not knowing about the world is ‘diagetic’ in the
sense that the player doesn’t know the world (which is the point of the trope),
but that this not knowing also plays out significantly in the gameplay. (As
opposed to, say, the Bourne Identity, wherein the player’s amnesia drives the
plot more than it really hinders the protagonists’ perceived competency).</p>
<p>I think a lot of the writing is like this; it’s almost like the protagonist acts
like a detective in a detective videogame (e.g. “I found this item I can
interact with, so it must be significant to the case”), and a lot of the writing
reminds him that he’s not the protagonist in a videogame.</p>
<p>The game as a whole probably serves as a good demonstration that tropes aren’t
necessarily bad; it’s about how they’re used.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Post Factorio Playthrough Ramble</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/games/2022-12-27-post-factorio-playthrough-ramble.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/games/2022-12-27-post-factorio-playthrough-ramble.html</id>
    <published>2022-12-27T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2022-12-27T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Okay, so maybe Factorio is “hyper-engaging”.</p>
<p>After playing through the game a bit on the Nintendo Switch,
I decided that I’d go back and play the game
in order to complete a few more
of the game’s achievements.</p>
<p>So I went to load my savegame from when I’d completed a
game on peaceful, only to discover that this savegame
was from an old pre-1.0 version of the game, and so
wouldn’t load.</p>
<p>Darn.</p>
<p>Guess my best option was to start a new game.</p>
<p>(Having played through the game on the standard non-peaceful,
I’d decided that I prefer to play on peaceful).</p>
<p>I’d describe my time as a “bender”.</p>
<p>I did learn some things, though.</p>
<p>This time, I made use of Factorio’s railway systems.
I’d previously thought this was intimidatingly difficult.
Fortunately, one of the Guides in the Steam Community provides
blueprints for a set of rails with the following nice
properties:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>4 lanes of rails, spaced such-that the outer-pair of rails
form a neat U-turn shape.</p></li>
<li><p>To simplify the train signals, each rail only allows
trains to go one-way.</p></li>
<li><p>The outer pair of rails is intended for trains to then
leave/enter train stations, whereas the inner pair of rails
is intended for ‘express’.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>I do generally worry that just using other people’s blueprints
takes out half of the fun of the game. (Especially if the blueprint
is well-optimised, and not something you’d naturally think of).
– With these rails designs, I felt I was able to enjoy the game
more without having to do this thinking though.</p>
<p>I did also borrow from <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MPUcU37hXH4">a mall design that KatherineOfSky</a> presented
a few years ago. I didn’t notice that this was for an older version of
the game.</p>
<p>One other thing I did better this game was “get comfortable with
the nuclear power system”. The nuclear power system is complicated
because it involves dealing with heat (which behaves differently than
other resources systems in the game), and dealing with the two kinds of uranium (which comes with its own issues).</p>
<p>My goal was to clear some of the achievements which deal with the late game.
I hadn’t achieved “research all technology”, the top “produce X amount of iron”,
the last “produce 20M green circuits” achievements; and a post-game “have 100 robot followers” achievement.</p>
<p>I find the game to be hyper-engaging up until researching blue science; at which
point there are <em>so many</em> exciting things to do, that I have to slow down to
focus task by task on what to achieve.</p>
<p>In particular, ‘blue science’ is when the construction &amp; logistic robots become available.<br />
And so while Factorio is overall a game about designing systems..
the construction robots are the game mechanic where this really takes off.<br />
The construction robots will automatically place buildings/etc. from blueprint designs. (It’s also possible to ad-hoc copy-paste buildings using the construction bots). – So if you’ve placed your buildings in such a way that they can be tiled, this allows rapidly scaling parts of your factory up. (Or, if you’ve got blueprint designs from previous playthroughs/wherever, bots will be able to start constructing these).<br />
The logistic robots can bring items to you so long as your factory has the robo-ports built in a ‘network’. (You can come up with a tiling design of robo-ports such that you can use construction bots to construct a large roboport network area…). And, later, certain storage boxes can have requirements set, so that the logistic robots will ensure the boxes have those items. (This allows e.g. creating a ‘cache’ area, so you can quickly have whatever items you want delivered to you).</p>
<p>I mean, I knew the robots were good previously.
But, I find the game shifts gears when they’re unlocked.</p>
<p>Previously, I’d always puttered along in the last mile when reaching the game’s
end objective of launching a rocket. But, since I wanted some achievements which
require multiple rocket launches, I was able to continue developing my factory.</p>
<p>This meant I was able to try out more of the late-game combat stuff. (Even
though the game was peaceful, I still did have to clear out enemy bases which
got in my way).</p>
<p>The robot followers are very powerful, and kinda allow just waltzing through
an enemy base.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://wiki.factorio.com/Spidertron">spidertron</a> was a lot of fun to use.</p>
<p>The post-game technologies increased the range and firing speed of the rail
artillery; which became my favourite tool for clearing out big areas of land. –
I’d not used laser turrets before. (My main non-peaceful playthrough had been
for getting a “no lasers” and “no solar power” achievement). The laser turrets
were very convenient for defending the rail artillery! (The enemy would rush the
site where the artillery fired from).</p>
<p>The main ‘insight’ I gained was from using the trains / railway network. Rather,
because I’d never used the trains for transporting resources, I’d always just
used the standard transport belts.. with trains, trains allow ‘decoupling’
resource movement.</p>
<p>That is: with trains, you have a station where you load some resource, and a
station where you unload that resource. With Factorio, stations can be named by
their role, and a train can be routed to follow a route like “refuel -&gt; load
resource X -&gt; unload resource X”. The train station’s name is an indirection; it
doesn’t concretely matter where the station is.</p>
<p>Whereas, the with the transport belts, the belts must be explicitly placed on
the map. There’s no indirection, no flexibility. If some resource is depleted,
you can place more belts; but that’s all you can do.</p>
<p>Logistic bots similarly can automatically move resources from one location to
another, but with a more limited throughput and a more limited distance compared
to trains.</p>
<p>Rather. I found it neat to be able to consider “load input, move it, unload” as
an abstraction. – Although, a lot of Factorio is dealing with the details of
the implementation.</p>
<p>I saw on YouTube there are speedruns of the game in under two hours; speedruns on random seeds in under three; speedruns of getting 100% achievements in under four or five hours!<br />
These are all impressive.</p>
<p>In speedruns, the player will also bootstrap the factory with techniques which
don’t scale well. An assembly machine will be placed &amp; will require the player
to manually insert the input ingredients. – This doesn’t ‘scale’ since it’s
infeasible for the player to continue doing this for the whole game; but for
bootstrapping the factory, it’s quicker than setting things up ‘the right way’.</p>
<p>I’ve also heard the term “city blocks” in the community.</p>
<p>I got the achievement for producing 20M green circuits.</p>
<p>By that time, my factory was producing about 60 of each science per minute. The
“megafactories” that some enthusiasts go for aim for 1000 of each science per
minute.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, I hadn’t really scaled up the green circuit production. So,
getting the achievement was more from “playing the post-game for quite some
time” than from “you have a factory which is producing many green circuits”.</p>
<p>The remaining achievements I haven’t yet unlocked are related to completing the
game quickly.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Factorio on the Switch Still Scratches the Itch</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/games/2022-12-11-factorio-on-the-switch-still-scratches-the-itch.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/games/2022-12-11-factorio-on-the-switch-still-scratches-the-itch.html</id>
    <published>2022-12-11T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2022-12-11T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Factorio is a game which is widely regarded as addictingly fun to play.</p>
<p>The ostensible goal of the game is to assemble &amp; launch a rocket ship.</p>
<p>The start of the game is reasonably familiar: you control a character, mine some
ores from resource deposits, and then use these resources to assemble tools or
whatever item you need. (e.g. you’ll mine some iron ore, put this ore in a
furnace,
and use the resulting iron plates to assemble an iron pickaxe).<br />
– Factorio allows for automating these process. A mining machine can
automatically gather resources; conveyor belts can automatically move these
resources along; an assembly machine can automatically assemble some item, and
inserter arm machines can automatically insert items from the convey belts into
the assembly machines.</p>
<p>The first time you play the game (if you don’t read guides first), you’ll
probably end up with a factory which works, but you’ll certainly end up with
something that’s difficult to maintain or improve on. You’ll end up with
a disorganised mess.<br />
(Then you hear the term “main bus”, and that helps organise things <em>a lot</em>).</p>
<p>The dynamic of the game ends up feeling very similar to programming or
electrical engineering.<br />
So much so that, while I think most programmers who play the game find it
addictively engaging, there are also those who don’t want to play it. – I think
it’s one of two responses: “it’s similar to what I do for work, but without
having to do what others tell me to do, and without having to be reliable. Fun!”
or “it’s similar to what I do for work, but I don’t benefit from putting in the
effort.
Why would I do that?”.<br />
I mean, there’s a satisfying feeling of constructing a system which works (as
well as ‘debugging’ why some system doesn’t work).</p>
<p>I think complementing this is that usually there are multiple things that you
can do to reduce the mess in your factory; and that improvements often have some
delay before you see the tangible benefits from them. So there’s often some task
you can aim towards that feels satisfying to do. (Sid Meier’s Civilization games
are similarly entralling).</p>
<p>Probably “fun is in the eye of the beholder”.<br />
There are parts of Factorio where I think it’s fun for me to come up with my own
solution to the problem. There are parts where I’d rather lookup a guide for how
to do it on the Factorio wiki, or some YouTube video.</p>
<p>I found it fun to play Factorio with particular challenges/goals in mind. One
achievement requires that you craft only the minimal number of items by hand
(and use assembly machines to bootstrap the rest). Another achievement was to
play the game on non-peaceful, but without using solar power.</p>
<p>“Non-peaceful” mode is the default setting for the enemies’ aggression mode.
The player’s factory produces pollution; the enemies react to the pollution by
getting stronger and attacking the player every now and then in waves. Whereas,
in peaceful mode, enemies will only attack if attacked first (and attacking
one enemy base doesn’t ‘aggro’ other enemy bases).<br />
In my experience, non-peaceful mode ‘just’ requires the extra pushback/effort of
automatically building (sufficient) ammunition/defenses, etc. – It adds a bit
of pressure/flavor to the game, and isn’t extremely stressful, but I prefer to
play with peaceful mode.</p>
<p>At the higher end of things, some players enjoy seeing how frequently their
factory is able to assemble/launch a rocket (since this requires a well organised
factory at significant scale). – I’ve not yet tried doing this.</p>
<p>For the playthroughs I’ve spent significant time on, I inevitably had the same
task/notes system I use when programming. (Start the day by writing down status
of WIP; write down tasks to-do, and obstacles faced which need to be resolved).</p>
<p>Anyway.</p>
<p>The game was recently released for the Nintendo Switch. I was travelling for a couple of
weeks, have a Nintendo Switch, and have enjoyed playing Factorio.</p>
<p>I can vouch that the game scratches the same itch as it does on PC.</p>
<p>The controls are reasonably nice, although using the controller won’t be as fast
as using the mouse.</p>
<p>I think if someone were (somehow) playing through Factorio for the first time on
the Nintendo Switch, I think they’d opt to play on PC by the time they got to
the blue science technologies. (About halfway through the game). – Because at
that point, you’ve unlocked trains and the construction robots and solar power
and electric furances… there’s lots of stuff which can all be used to improve
your factory. (Trains are earlier; but, I didn’t bother assembling rail stuff
until after I’d assembled blue science).</p>
<p>I’d bet that the Switch is suited to people having the large post-game factories.
I never noticed performance issues in my playing, though.</p>
<p>If someone were wondering whether to by Factorio for PC or for the Switch, I’d
say “yes”. Well, I don’t think anyone’s going to regret buying this game. I
think PC is the better environment to play it on. But, on the Switch it still
stratches the same itch just the same.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>The CapsLock Key was not the Problem</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2022-10-28-the-capslock-key-was-not-the-problem.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2022-10-28-the-capslock-key-was-not-the-problem.html</id>
    <published>2022-10-28T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2022-10-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s fashionable among developers to give a tip about the CapsLock key: you can switch out its functionality, replacing it with the Escape key.</p>
<p>When I did this, in order to then type out something like <code>SEQUENCE_OF_UPPERCASE_WORDS</code>, I’d hold down the shift key using my left pinky finger, and type out the letters as necessary.<br />
– And if you can do that, then the CapsLock key is redundant.</p>
<p>These days, I prefer using a fancy, symmetrical keyboard. (I think buying an expensive fancy keyboard is justifiable if it’s symmetrical, and offers more keys for the thumb to press; and I don’t think it makes sense to spend a lot of money on a keyboard which isn’t symmetrical, etc.).<br />
And the fashionable (and I think superior) way of arranging the modifier keys Shift, Ctrl, Windows/Cmd, Alt keys is to put these as dual-use tap-hold keys
on the home row. (Which allows access to these keys without having to move your hand).</p>
<p>With such a keyboard, and with home row modifiers, the “use an improper position which stretches your weak pinky finger” technique doesn’t really work.<br />
Instead, to type <code>UPPERCASE</code>, you end up having to alternate use of the shift key; pressing shift for the opposite side of the letter being pushed.<br />
– I can do this; but I find it to be slower, and error prone. (It’s easy to miss the timing, and type ‘THhiS’ instead of ‘THIS’, as the Shift key requires holding down ‘h’).</p>
<p>For long sequences of uppercases letters, it does make sense to have the CapsLock key available. – Though, with a fancy keyboard, you can have the CapsLock key accessible on (or hidden away on) a layer.</p>
<p>Rather. The CapsLock functionality itself isn’t inherently useless, and needn’t be banished.<br />
It’s that, in a standard keyboard, the real-estate of “on home row, easy to reach” that the CapsLock key occupies is put to much better use by using it for Escape (or Ctrl, or dual-use Escape/Ctrl).<br />
Since a fancy keyboard is nicer to use (the modifier keys are easy to each, and layers allow bringing more keys to within easy reach), you get to use the CapsLock key without it taking up space which could be better utilized.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>

</feed>
