<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Richard Goulter's Blog</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//atom.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog/" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//atom.xml</id>
    <author>
        <name>Richard Goulter</name>
        <email>richard.goulter+blog@gmail.com</email>
    </author>
    <updated>2015-07-12T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <entry>
    <title>Comical Conservative</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/argument/2015-07-12-comical-conservative.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/argument/2015-07-12-comical-conservative.html</id>
    <published>2015-07-12T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-07-12T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on July 12, 2015
    
        by Richard Goulter
    <br/>
    
    Tags: <a href="/tags/politics.html">politics</a>, <a href="/tags/righteous%20mind.html">righteous mind</a>, <a href="/tags/liberals.html">liberals</a>, <a href="/tags/conservatives.html">conservatives</a>
    
</div>

<p>Came across <a href="https://www.facebook.com/TheComicalConservative/photos/a.133361476797039.26402.133352176797969/626100744189774/?type=1">this</a> on Facebook:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Liberal: I am pro-choice<br />
Me: Can I choose my own health care?<br />
Liberal: No.<br />
Me: Can I choose what I do with money I earn?<br />
Liberal: No.<br />
Me: Can I choose how I defend my family and possessions?<br />
Liberal: No.<br />
Me: What can I choose?<br />
Liberal: An abortion, and a same sex marriage.<br />
Me: I don’t agree with your opinions.<br />
Liberal: OH MY GOD STOP OPPRESSING ME YOU RACIST SEXIST BIGOT!</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It’s not particularly hard to figure out that this comes from a socially-conservative poster.<br />
I wouldn’t criticise this post for the quality of its opinion; but what’s perhaps disappointing is the “the guy I disagree with is so stupid” nature to it. It’d be unfair, though, to say that this attitude is unique to this post (or to social conservatives).</p>
<p>Lately I’ve been listening to some of Jonathon Haidt’s talks/lectures.<br />
In particular</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=b86dzTFJbkc">‘Why conservatives don’t like social justice and science’</a>, in which Haidt discusses is “Righteous Mind” thesis, how humans develop morality in regards to care/loyalty/etc., and discussing socially liberal and conservative attitudes in regards to this. Haidt finishes the talk with a resounding criticism of the social sciences discrimination against conservatives. (– Ha, Karen Straughan chips in in the comments section).</li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=v3o-F94S4FI">‘How Common Threats Make for Common Ground’</a> (TED talk), in which Haidt points out this hyper-partisanship makes each side deny the looming threats we face, since each threat has become a political issue.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iOu_8yoqZoQ">‘Three Stories About Capitalism’</a> (TED talk), in which Haidt discusses that some problems are “wicked problems” since they invoke our moral beliefs to resolve them, and the political disagreement over capitalism,</li>
<li>and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1OnTTWkAv_E">this talk to some law students</a> (somewhat pessimistic).</li>
</ul>
<p>Haidt is a social psychologist; one of his main theses is that, lately, American politics has become extremely polarised. Roughly, in “The Righteous Mind” he points out our morality brings people together, but also divides us, as we sacrilise things which are “good”, and so anything opposing it is “bad”.<br />
e.g. social liberals ‘sacrilise’ women’s rights, so the women’s right to choose abortion is far more important than a fetus’ “right to live” or so.<br />
– The utterly refreshing thing about these lectures from Haidt is the utterly neutral way he discusses the social left/right.</p>
<p>With that in mind, (great if you’ve seen any of the videos, but in any case):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Liberal: I am pro-choice</p>
</blockquote>
<p>“Pro-choice” is a heavily charged term used to refer to a pro-abortion attitude (as opposed to “pro life” [or “anti-choice”]).<br />
It seems a slightly mis-placed phrasing. Though, as with many arguments, what’s under attack is the Liberal’s <strong>sincerity</strong> about “people should be free to do what they want”.</p>
<p>Haidt discussed that, while everyone values “liberty”.<br />
The social left means “liberty” as in enabling everyone to have the freedom to choose what to do. (e.g. everyone should be able to go to college.).<br />
The social right means “liberty” as in not interfering with individual choices. (e.g. don’t tax successful people more for being successful.).</p>
<p>Next, the post somewhat attacks the liberal attitudes on some points:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Me: Can I choose my own health care?<br />
Me: Can I choose what I do with money I earn?<br />
Me: Can I choose how I defend my family and possessions?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Briefly,<br />
‘Can I choose my own health care?’ ObamaCare seems to’ve been quite nasty for the middle class.<br />
‘Can I choose what I do with money I earn?’ is slightly poorly phrased. Social conservatives prefer small government / lower taxes; but any taxation would still be the govt imposing what an individual does with the money. I mean, I think with better phrasing, (perhaps “Will I be rewarded for working harder than others, and taxed at the same rate as everyone else?”) it’d be easier to push a conservative viewpoint.<br />
‘Can I choose how I defend my family and possessions?’ is an unfortunate one; the second amendment issue seems politically charged, and I understand only in the US is anyone so in favour of ‘civilians having assault rifles’. (Though, e.g. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RSk1UkqBx58">Dana Loesch</a> seems to be able to argue quite well in favour).</p>
<p>Again, this is all “look how un-liberal the social left’s attitudes are”.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Me: What can I choose? Liberal: An abortion, and a same sex marriage.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Somewhat interesting to note that these two things are abhorrent to the religious right.</p>
<p>You’d think a socially conservative attitude, in favour of a limited government, would be argue something more like “it’s not the government’s duty to interfere with individual liberty in these matters, [even if they are abhorrent]”.<br />
It’s certainly a more interesting argument than “it’s morally right for this to be able to happen, why is it not legal?”.</p>
<p>Still, this certainly makes the post look tacky.<br />
For the social left, it’s great that a woman can have an abortion, and that two people who love each other can marry!<br />
– I guess what’s intended is a mocking along the lines of “this is the only ‘liberty’ the social left cares about[; they don’t <strong>really</strong> care about liberty, like we do]”. And America is all about liberty/freedom.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Me: I don’t agree with your opinions. Liberal: OH MY GOD STOP OPPRESSING ME YOU RACIST SEXIST BIGOT!</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This part doesn’t flow at all from the rest.<br />
Again, with regards to Haidt, the social left ‘sacrilises’ the oppressed; so, anyone who disagrees with the left is a ‘racist’, is a ‘sexist’.<br />
Also fun is that these words short-circuit argument. To be ‘racist’ is to be a heathen to the social left. Anything ‘racist’ is bad, and so it’s not worth considering the argument, because of course anything ‘racist’ cannot be true.</p>
<p>Adding to the depiction of the Liberal as someone who doesn’t care about liberty, this paints the Liberal as someone who isn’t into civilised discourse, as well as someone who is incapable of defending their opinion.</p>
<p>I guess what’s disappointing is that, rather than simply saying “social conservative attitudes aren’t dumb”, the post reaches further and says “social left attitudes are dumb”. It’d be just as easy to make a similar “social right attitudes are dumb” post, which would almost certainly be similarly tacky.</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Beware Radicalisation</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/argument/2015-07-01-beware-radicalisation.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/argument/2015-07-01-beware-radicalisation.html</id>
    <published>2015-07-01T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-07-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on July  1, 2015
    
        by Richard Goulter
    <br/>
    
    Tags: <a href="/tags/feminists.html">feminists</a>, <a href="/tags/feminism.html">feminism</a>, <a href="/tags/hacker%20culture.html">hacker culture</a>, <a href="/tags/sjw.html">sjw</a>, <a href="/tags/community.html">community</a>
    
</div>

<p>Shot(s): <a href="https://medium.com/@maradydd/when-nerds-collide-31895b01e68c">When Nerds Collide</a> by <span class="citation">@maradydd</span> / Meredith Patterson, 2014 Mar (Bonus: <a href="https://medium.com/@maradydd/okay-feminism-its-time-we-had-a-talk-about-empathy-bd6321c66b37">Okay, Feminism, It’s Time We Had a Talk About Empathy</a>, 2013 Oct).<br />
Chaser: <a href="http://esr.ibiblio.org/?p=6642">Meredith Patterson’s valient effort is probably doomed</a> by <span class="citation">@esrtweet</span> / Eric S. Raymond, 2015 Jan.</p>
<p>Well, at least ERS hedges by saying ‘probably’.</p>
<p>I read the above two pieces from Patterson some time ago.<br />
‘When Nerds Collide’ is a particularly brilliant piece of writing you should go read. In short, it’s a response to the tensions which come up in terms of tech and ‘inclusivity’. THe piece is filled with a plethora of amazing points, but at its core discusses the idea of a “weird nerd”, who was previously rejected by mainstream culture but now happens to wield power.<br />
The ‘peace offering’ here is more of a “you want inclusivity? here’s how you can have that.”; it’s a call for respect/construction rather than aggression/destruction.</p>
<p>(The second essay isn’t bad, either, but whereas the aforementioned essay is inclined to use progressive lingo, this one uses techie lingo and suggests that many of the efforts in the “women in tech” issue make for anti-patterns.).</p>
<p>I came across ERS’ above essay when someone linked to it on Twitter as part of a culture-war over some GitHub repo.<br />
The key line used was “total rejection of the SJW doctrine”.</p>
<p>It’s not a bad piece of writing.<br />
But it’s not a piece of writing which is going to make any friends. It’s clearly not written to be the kind of article which makes friends. – <em>except maybe</em>, maybe those who transcend the tribalism and genuinely care about “justice and inclusion”.</p>
<p>Yet, ERS’ does include the key phrase “defense of hacker culture”; maradydd’s writing more/less features this term, also.<br />
– If there is any kind of peace offering in ERS’ piece, “shut up and show us the code”; the same conclusion maradydd’s piece ends with.</p>
<p>I don’t think any “kumbaya, let’s all sit around the campfire and be friends” attitude can outright reject ERS’ piece. At least, “ERS = bad, maradydd = good” seems as unlikely to win friends as “SJWs = bad, hackers = good”.<br />
Hostile tone aside, iterate the points of ERS’ piece without hostility. (e.g.; as with <strong>pretty much every argument</strong>, “the other side aren’t <strong>sincere</strong> in caring about the values they say they care about, otherwise they’d do …”, “some bullying happens guised as ‘being inclusive’. This is concerning.”, etc.). – Perhaps a more neutral way of phrasing a conclusion would be “be inclusive, but have zero tolerance for bullying” or so.</p>
<p>In any case, what I note foremost from this is how ERS’ post manages to be much more hostile than maradydd’s (“they’re the enemy / we can’t let them gain an inch”) while following the same kinds of points.<br />
ERS’ piece is much more radical / radicalising than maradydd’s more grounded piece.<br />
And it’s concerning that such a tribalistic “they’re the enemy / we’re the good guys” (and therefore, any action we do is righteous, and action they do is evil) follows so closely from a more reasonable piece.</p>
<p>– Whether “code is without morality” (similar to “numbers don’t lie, interpretations do”?) holds or not is <em>probably</em> a point of contention to be had, among other points, but that can be considered some other time.<br />
I’d be more interested to transcend the arguing here and consider the tribalism and all this “kumbaya” shit, how people interact &amp; communicate (or don’t) in online places; the evils of (self-)righteousness, why it’s so much easier to spot that the other guy is an asshole (and of course you aren’t).</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Romance Tropes in Anime vs Romance Novels</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/romance/2015-06-29-romance-tropes-in-anime-vs-romance-novels.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/romance/2015-06-29-romance-tropes-in-anime-vs-romance-novels.html</id>
    <published>2015-06-29T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-06-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on June 29, 2015
    
        by Richard Goulter
    <br/>
    
    Tags: <a href="/tags/anime.html">anime</a>, <a href="/tags/romance%20novels.html">romance novels</a>, <a href="/tags/if%20my%20heart%20had%20wings.html">if my heart had wings</a>, <a href="/tags/valkyria%20chronicles.html">valkyria chronicles</a>
    
</div>

<p>Recently I’ve finished playing <strong>Valkyria Chronicles</strong> and <strong>If My Heart Had Wings</strong>.<br />
<strong>Valkyria Chronicles</strong>, recently released for PC (earlier released on PlayStation 3) is a strategy game; featuring a bunch of cute boys &amp; girls in cutesy uniforms with rifles in an almost WWII-esque setting.<br />
<strong>If My Heart Had Wings</strong> is a ‘visual novel’; the story is about friends at a school who build &amp; fly a glider.</p>
<p>Spoilers prob’ly follow. You’ve been warned.</p>
<p>Both of these stories are anime-esque (coming from Japan), and both feature elements of romance; though, IMMHW is more focused on this aspect.<br />
I’d love to compare how the elements of narrative used in these stories compared to the (written-in-the-US) Romance Novels I know &amp; love.<br />
Admittedly, it’s a rather small and not particularly representative “sample”; I doubt many of the comparisons here extend too far.</p>
<p>VC is awfully concise in its narrative; there’re some very sweet romance-y bits in the story, though. The story is a bit camp, but one of the lines which sticks with me from the romance between Alicia and Welkin is Alicia’s declaration: “with you I’m not scared anymore”. (Or something like that).<br />
– Compared to RNs: it wouldn’t be so out of place; though, VC naturally lends itself to a much more action-oriented plot than most RNs tend to have. - My impression, though, is RNs, with so much focus on for-women-by-women, will tend to try and have more ‘girl power’ to them. So, dialogue like “I can’t live without you” isn’t uncommon, but I’m sure I can’t recall any story where anyone said “I rely on you” to the other.<br />
Overall, VC doesn’t spend so much time on its romances. The boy and the girl like each other. They do stuff together. There’s kindof a “look I love you” moment, but not particularly any ‘internal conflict’ between the characters. But it’s not particularly a huge focus of the game/story, so oh well.</p>
<p>I’d’ve thought IMMHW would’ve had more sex scenes in it, from the hoo-hah everyone seems to make about the restoration-patch, and all the “people think I’m a loser, but jokes on them, I’ve got a wheelchair-girlfriend” type comments/reviews on Steam.<br />
See, in some of the sexier RNs, there’s gotta be sex by, like, page 20 otherwise it’s considered boring. – IMMHW isn’t so quick to the chase. (Difference in medium may have something to do with that.).<br />
– Sexuality/identity, and sexual representation are waaay different in IMHHW than in the RNs. I mean, those who’re inclined to be offended by a ‘sexist’ trope would find plenty to complain about in IMMHW.</p>
<p>– Part of this is inevitably due to the difference in media between VNs and RNs: even in RNs plenty of people will get upset at the way a story was told. (Things like: ‘the hero was kindof a douchebag, the heroine deserved better’.). With VNs, choices are made which determine the outcome of which girl the main character ends up with.<br />
Sometimes IMMHW did this nicely; you choose which girl you want to spend time with, and the dialogue builds intimacy between the characters. – One particular choice, though, “whose swimsuit/boobs look the best?” is … certainly not something you’d see in RNs.</p>
<p>– On the otherhand, perhaps there’s also plenty to celebrate? In IMMHW, there’re many female characters: The school council’s president is female: authorative, fair, and compassionate. The senior student who was building the glider is female: she’s slightly eccentric, super smart, though with some faults. The other members of the glider club, who study hard to understand aeronautics, work hard to build and maintain the glider, are female. – None of these girls are treated as less for being female; the narrative shows no surprise or novelty that these characters are female. These characters aren’t treated as one-dimensional sex kittens.<br />
– It’s a cute tease, but IMMHW does pass the Bechdel test. (Not sure how many RNs would pass that; though, Bechdel test seems more of an arbitrary thing for people to be able to cry ‘sexist’ over, so <em>shrug</em>.).<br />
RNs main strength is character; mostly just the main hero/heroine. IMMHW has many characters, perhaps not all with the same depth as the H/H in RNs, but not paricularly flat characters, either.</p>
<p>That there’s a ‘choice’ of which partner to pick is somewhat quaint.<br />
In (modern) RNs, it’s fairly conventional that by the end of the second chapter or so, you’ll know who the main Hero and Heroine are, and that they’ll be end the story Happily-Ever-After. - In IMMHW, it’s not (to me) as apparent, given the breadth/depth of characters featured.<br />
(I’ve only played through one ‘route’ of IMMHW. I’m not sure how inferior/shorter other ‘routes’ of the story may be. – In some sense, VNs compare to Choose Your Own Adventure stories. Choose Your Own Romance?).<br />
– Maybe a bad example, but if Twilight where CYOR, it’d make the whole ‘Team Edward’/‘Team Jacob’ thing more fun. ;P</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Pretty HG Log Style</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2015-06-01-pretty-hg-log-style.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2015-06-01-pretty-hg-log-style.html</id>
    <published>2015-06-01T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-06-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on June  1, 2015
    
        by Richard Goulter
    <br/>
    
    Tags: <a href="/tags/hg.html">hg</a>, <a href="/tags/mercurial.html">mercurial</a>, <a href="/tags/git.html">git</a>, <a href="/tags/terminal.html">terminal</a>, <a href="/tags/log-style.html">log-style</a>
    
</div>

<p>There’s a somewhat famous styled git log I have in my config. The guy I grabbed it from said it was from <a href="https://github.com/ndbroadbent/scm_breeze">scm-breeze</a>, I think maybe he meant tiimgreen’s <a href="https://github.com/tiimgreen/github-cheat-sheet#styled-git-log">github-cheat-sheet</a>. In any case, The Git one is like:</p>
<pre><code>alias gl=&quot;git log --graph --pretty=format:&#39;%Cred%h%Creset -%C(yellow)%d%Creset %s %Cgreen(%cr) %C(bold blue)&lt;%an&gt;%Creset&#39; --abbrev-commit&quot;</code></pre>
<p>Consulting <a href="http://git-scm.com/docs/pretty-formats">the docs</a>, (who does that, right?), it’s not insane to figure out what this is doing:</p>
<ul>
<li><code>%h</code> - abbrev commit hash</li>
<li><code>%d</code> - ref names (like <code>(origin/master)</code>)</li>
<li><code>%s</code> - subject (first line of commit)</li>
<li><code>%cr</code> - committer date, relative.</li>
<li><code>%an</code> - author name.</li>
</ul>
<p>Great.<br />
But I’ve been using HG. Can Mercurial haz it, too?<br />
Sources:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/3575189/mercurial-log-with-one-liners">S/O: “Mercurial Log with One-Liners”</a> Because one-liner logs themselves can be useful.<br />
 This one has:<br />
 <code>alias hl=&quot;hg log --template '{node|short} | {date|isodatesec} | {author|user}: {desc|strip|firstline}\n'&quot;</code></li>
<li><a href="hgbook.red-bean.com/read/customizing-the-output-of-mercurial.html">HG Book: Customizing Output</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.selenic.com/hg/help/templates">HG Help / Manpages</a></li>
</ul>
<p>This helps us get a plain one-liner</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/3625725/can-i-add-custom-colors-to-mercurial-command-templates">HG Template Colours</a></li>
</ul>
<p>I’m trying for “direct equivalence”. YMMV, since Git/HG don’t exactly share all concepts. (e.g. every commit in HG has the notion of a ‘branch’, etc.).<br />
So, note that when building the template, this is the stuff to put within the <code>{}</code>:</p>
<ul>
<li><code>node|short</code> - commit hash</li>
<li><code>rev</code> - int, revision number.</li>
<li><code>branches</code>/<code>branch</code> - branchname.</li>
<li><code>desc|strip|firstline</code> - ‘subject’</li>
<li><code>date|age</code> - human-readable difference in time.</li>
<li><code>author|person</code> - Richard from Richard <script type="text/javascript">
<!--
h='&#x67;&#x6d;&#x61;&#x69;&#108;&#46;&#x63;&#x6f;&#x6d;';a='&#64;';n='&#114;&#x69;&#x63;&#104;&#x61;&#114;&#100;&#46;&#x67;&#x6f;&#x75;&#108;&#116;&#x65;&#114;';e=n+a+h;
document.write('<a h'+'ref'+'="ma'+'ilto'+':'+e+'" clas'+'s="em' + 'ail">'+e+'<\/'+'a'+'>');
// -->
</script><noscript>&#114;&#x69;&#x63;&#104;&#x61;&#114;&#100;&#46;&#x67;&#x6f;&#x75;&#108;&#116;&#x65;&#114;&#32;&#x61;&#116;&#32;&#x67;&#x6d;&#x61;&#x69;&#108;&#32;&#100;&#x6f;&#116;&#32;&#x63;&#x6f;&#x6d;</noscript></li>
</ul>
<p>So, my <code>.hgrc</code> has:</p>
<pre><code>[color]
custom.rev = red
custom.decorate = yellow
custom.date = green
custom.author = blue bold</code></pre>
<p>With the hg alias: <code>alias hl=&quot;hg log --style ~/.hgrc.d/fancy.style&quot;</code>. (Or do this from your shell, whatever).</p>
<p>And, finally, <code>~/.hgrc.d/fancy.style</code> is:</p>
<pre><code>changeset = &quot;* {label(&#39;custom.rev&#39;, node|short)} - ({label(&#39;custom.decorate&#39;, branch)}) {desc|strip|firstline} ({label(&#39;custom.date&#39;, date|age)}) &lt;{label(&#39;custom.author&#39; , author)}&gt;\n&quot;</code></pre>
<p>Screenshot:<br />
<img src="http://i.imgur.com/OWImYAS.png" alt="" /></p>
<p>(The repo is old, because I don’t use HG so much, okay?).</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>I Could Solve This in Five Minutes</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/narrative/2015-04-28-i-could-solve-this-in-five-minutes.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/narrative/2015-04-28-i-could-solve-this-in-five-minutes.html</id>
    <published>2015-04-28T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-04-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on April 28, 2015
    
        by Richard Goulter
    <br/>
    
    Tags: <a href="/tags/romance.html">romance</a>, <a href="/tags/books.html">books</a>
    
</div>

<p>So, at the moment I’m sludging through Sherry Thomas’ latest, &amp; first Contemporary, “The One in my Heart”.<br />
There’s lots to not-enjoy about it. (Like the character lamenting the lack of timeless marriage, at the same time as looking at her phone during lunch with her partner). Whatever. The bigger issue for the Romance Novel here is that there’s zero (internal) conflict between the characters: the hero is utterly perfect, and utterly in love with the heroine; has been for ages. And the heroine is utterly perfect, and utterly in love with the hero; has been for ages. <strong>Sighhhhh.</strong></p>
<p>So. Romance Novel, but main characters aren’t great. Gotcha.<br />
There has to be at least <strong>some</strong> conflict*, though: the hero wants to reconcile with his parents (minus having to say sorry. <strong>Sighhhhhh.</strong>). The heroine wants a relationship with the hero. So, naturally, doesn’t want a fake-relationship with the hero. Because. <strong>Sighhhhhhhhhhh.</strong>.<br />
– The thing is, and the narrative even admits, both of these problems could be solved in five minutes. If the hero just talked to his parents. Or the heroine just said to the hero, (who obviously, completely obviously digs her) that she likes him.<br />
And because it can be solved so quickly, it’s <strong>really</strong> hard to get behind the characters. It’s just really silly.</p>
<p>The fun thing is, though, like: with Romance Novels, you know it’s going to be a “Happily Ever After”. It doesn’t matter that you know (roughly) what the ending is going to be, it’s more interesting how the conflict is going to be resolved.</p>
<p>Rather, if the problem can be solved in five minutes, then the pages between the establishment of the narrative, and the climax/conclusion of the book, are really just words filling in space. – <strong>Which can be fine.</strong> But it’s usually better to distract the reader, throw them off the scent that the conflict isn’t hard.</p>
<p>(Come to think of it, “deus ex machina” is kindof the opposite; a super-hard problem is established, but ‘solved’ in a super-short amount of time..).</p>
<p>It’s not just Romance Novels which are guilty of this, as such.<br />
SciFi/Fantasy can totally play the same game, too.<br />
RASalvatore’s stories were notorious at this: early on, the narrative shows some cool bag-of-tricks which the bad guy has. e.g. the ability to teleport someone in order to assassinate them. Like. If you can do that, you can kill the ‘good guy’ in five minutes. Of course there are “rules” to it. But when the narrator arbitrarily awards convenience magic to good/bad guys.. the plot can hardly be more than 5 minutes from resolution at any point in time.<br />
– Perhaps the best example would be “Siege of Darkness”, where during a relentless siege the ‘bad guys’ just happen to pack up &amp; leave.</p>
<p>In terms of “pages filling space”, Salvatore’s writing was fairly solid here: the heroes are tired, but have to press on. Then some more fighting, so the heroes are even more tired, but they have to press on even more urgently, but then there’s even more fighting, etc. etc.</p>
<p>– But considering stories I’ve liked:<br />
“Seducing Mr Knightly”: I love this book so much. In terms of the core plot: the body of the story is filled with flirtations between Annabelle and Knightly. It might be possible to trim this down to a skeleton of around three key encounters. Maybe. But since so much of the story is about Annabelle’s growth/transformation, it’s never 5-minutes away from the end.<br />
“Devil in Winter”: There’s just so much character development/growth going on here, that it’s not 5-minutes-then-done.<br />
“High Fidelity”: This book isn’t really about ‘plot’, so much as a collection of biographic-esque monologues, for different situations.</p>
<p>– So. Conflicts which can be solved “in 5 minutes” aren’t inherently bad. But it takes a lot of effort, and a lot of talent to maintain a plotline through a holding place, waiting for the end of the story. (Oddly enough, reader is probably also waiting for things to progress..).</p>
<hr />
<p>*Ideas to make this pairing more interesting: The heroine is a materials scientist. The Hero is a doctor/surgeon. It’s okay for them to be a “love interest” in an “aliens invading the city, these two have to find a counter-weapon” plot. Explosions, excitement!<br />
Or, sticking to the romance-novel genre: give points of tension between the character, which can’t be solved quickly: maybe the hero is with a girl. Not a girl who’s vain/materialistic/morally-bad, etc., but a girl who would make a good HEA. <strong>That</strong> would make the story more interesting.<br />
Or perhaps the hero/heroine disagree on things which are important to them: maybe he finds his work important, she finds his time important (or vice versa).<br />
etc. but the given conflict is “not really a problem”. :/</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>You Know You Should Be Using VCS For That</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2015-03-29-you-know-you-should-be-using-vcs-for-that.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2015-03-29-you-know-you-should-be-using-vcs-for-that.html</id>
    <published>2015-03-29T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-03-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on March 29, 2015
    
        by Richard Goulter
    <br/>
    
    Tags: <a href="/tags/git.html">git</a>, <a href="/tags/vim.html">vim</a>, <a href="/tags/fugitive.html">fugitive</a>
    
</div>

<p>It’s kindof cute that all programmers, if they’ve worked on any project for a long enough time before learning about VCS, surely all take the same approach to novice “version control”. e.g. Keeping folders/copies as snapshots of how the code looked at that time. – We weren’t all born knowing how to use VCS. (Though, maybe those who didn’t bother to play around with programming a lot outside of class never faced this).</p>
<p>I’d be astounded if anyone with even only a basic grasp of VCS kept to doing things this way. VCS is obviously that much better at keeping versions.</p>
<p>But, uh. One thing which is still not uncommon to see is, as an answer to the anxiety of “not sure if <em>this function</em> is something I’m going to need later (even though I don’t need it now). I’d better just comment it out.”.<br />
It’s really quick and easy to use a decent text editor to comment/uncomment out a chunk of code. (Even the kids who don’t learn vim/emacs can do this in the text editors of IDEs).<br />
This strikes me as a ‘dirty’ solution; it sounds like you’d want some <em>version</em> of the function handy. – And surely with VCS available, there shouldn’t be any doubt as to being able to get a copy of this function back if you delete it.</p>
<p>I’m not sure I’ve met anyone who can do this well. I don’t think that’s necessarily a reflection on skill in VCS (it’s not as if anyone <strong>really</strong> needs to do somersaults in VCS all the time. … It’s probably not very good if you do have to), but perhaps this is a “common enough” thing which VCS doesn’t make accessible?<br />
Rephrasing so as to be more precise/specific: if there’s some hunk of text (e.g. a function which we’d otherwise comment out) is removed in a commit, which isn’t necessarily the only modification in a commit, how to ‘recover’ this hunk of text into the current working copy of the file? (Bonus points if the function we want to recover isn’t the only modified hunk in the commit).</p>
<p>Common enough answer of ‘how to do this’ is to look at the commit, copy-paste the hunk, and maybe remove the +‘s/-’s (the first column of the modified lines in the commit difference).<br />
This also feels ’dirty’, and a bit wasteful. Especially if there’re many lines in the hunk. (Vim’s visual mode would mitigate this, sortof, but still).</p>
<p>Checking out a commit/file, and copying the function directly, also feels … tedious.<br />
I was surprised to learn Vim/Fugitive makes this not insanely brutal to pull off, though: the command <code>Glog</code> on a file in VCS will put the history of the file in a location list, so the different versions of a file can be easily traversed.<br />
Though, again, it may be tedious to find which function you want to copy. (In principle, anyway, if not in practice!).</p>
<p>I <em>think</em> what I’m after is closer to the following:<br />
<code>git diff R R^ &gt; foo.diff</code> outputs a (“reverse”) of the commit. You can then either edit this <code>foo.diff</code> file, deleting the hunks you don’t want (tedious!, except for the pertinent hunk), which we can then <code>git apply foo.diff</code>. (Assuming the hunk is still relevant!).<br />
Alternatively, just applying the diff (without editing it), one could then <code>git checkout --patch -- .</code> (assuming the repo was otherwise in a clean state before applying the diff..).<br />
This is tedious, still, but it’s plausible that a script could perform this (“recover some hunk(s) from a commit [which removed them]”), with that assumption that a hunk could be applied to the working copy. (As far as I understand, if a file has changed so much that Git/VCS can’t figure out how to apply the diff, then this can’t work either).</p>
<p>None of this seems a “great” solution to the problem, though.</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Case Study of Conflict in Narrative</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/narrative/2015-03-28-case-study-of-conflict-in-narrative.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/narrative/2015-03-28-case-study-of-conflict-in-narrative.html</id>
    <published>2015-03-28T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-03-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on March 28, 2015
    
        by Richard Goulter
    <br/>
    
    Tags: <a href="/tags/katherine%20ashe.html">katherine ashe</a>, <a href="/tags/at%20the%20billionaire%27s%20wedding.html">at the billionaire&#39;s wedding</a>, <a href="/tags/conflict.html">conflict</a>, <a href="/tags/character.html">character</a>
    
</div>

<p>Maybe in my previous postings on this topic I’ve come across as a little harsh on RASalvatore, and perhaps it seems that I think all Romance Novels do character well.</p>
<p>Okay. That’s obviously not going to be true.<br />
But I’d still like to consider Katherine Ashe’s novella from the “At the Billionaire’s Wedding” anthology with regards to conflict in the narrative. And, like, how well “character development = internal conflict, plot = external conflict” model holds up.</p>
<p>The “At the Billionaire’s Wedding” anthology takes place in the setting of the wedding of Maya Rodale’s Duke Austen and Jane Sparks. (If you figured out giving the husband’s surname to the wife makes for “Jane Austen”, you’re quicker than me). The four authors have previously done an anthology called “At the Duke’s Wedding”. (I guess they didn’t like the name “At Duke’s Wedding”).<br />
– These are pretty good samplers to get a taste for how each author writes, I reckon. Since reading AtDW, I’ve read at least one novel from each of the authors.</p>
<p>Anyway. Wasn’t a big fan of KAshe’s part of AtBW.<br />
The cool thing about the novella is it’s an “interpretation”/rendition/render of “Pride and Prejudice”. (Written by Jane Austen so it’s kindof meta, ha..). [I reckon Austen hates people more than KAshe does, so, that’s one limitation]. I dunno. Considering how much of a well-loved classic P&amp;P is, I’d say it’s more audacious to do something like this as opposed to otherwise rewriting/remixing types/tropes. – I didn’t enjoy it. Your Mileage May Vary.</p>
<p>Probably a big part of why I didn’t like it was the shrill, heavy-handed advocacy of Social Justice: The heroine suffers all sorts of woes. As far as I recall: crappy job, rape-y boss, other sexual discrimination, poor, sick sister who depends on her, abusive father. – I think that’s an album or two of country music right there. – But, also, naturally the heroine is a righteous-as-hell activist and woe the world is so evil and all.<br />
– With Heroines like Penelope Featherington (even in “Offer from a Gentleman”) or Evie from “Devil in Winter” or Annabelle Swift in “Seducing Mr. Knightly”, I can’t help but want to hug these women and protect them, etc.; here I felt none of that. :/</p>
<p>In terms of “internal”/“external” conflict, this character has zero room for character growth (unless the writer thinks that the character sounds like a twat. I think this author doesn’t think that the character sounds like a twat). ALL the conflict is external; all the conflict the character suffers are due to other people, or things outside the character.<br />
Flat, boring characters can be fine, even as main characters. But it’s kindof dull in a genre filled with strong characters. (People who complain about a lack of strong female characters surely haven’t read Romance Novels recently).</p>
<p>The Hero character in the story is similarly developed: the Hero is rich, handsome as anything, a super good lover; moreover, is deeply, totally in love with the heroine, and completely agrees with her on every moral/activist issue.<br />
– I feel there’s not a lot of potential for conflict here.<br />
The Hero expresses his love by following the heroine around and secretly funding her project and not talking to her or anything. But it’s totally not creepy. Because.<br />
Anyway. The Hero also works at his father’s company, which is big and evil and corporate and stuff. His father also is arrogant and evil and corporate and stuff. – I suppose it’d be a spoiler to say whether or not the Hero leaves this company by the end (as a token of his love?) of the novella? I’d better not spoil it, then.</p>
<p>Again. There’s zero room for “internal conflict” (and as per the model) character growth here.<br />
It’s like a “prince comes to rescue the princess” story, where both prince/princess characters are flat. cf. “Lord of Scoundrels”, wherein the prince is the Heroine, who “sees value/treasure in things everyone else overlooks”; and the princess trapped in a castle. LoS has the princess do at least some of the work to rescue himself (after a large amount of effort from the prince). i.e. maybe the prince doesn’t grow as a character much, but it’s a helluvan interesting princess.</p>
<p>Where the novella does present conflict is every time the Hero professes “I wuv you lots” the heroine has the angst of “obviously he’ll get bored of me eventually” (a classic trope, fair enough), as well as “my mum loved my dad but then that turned bad”. (And, of course, since the Hero works at big bad company, prejudice says that he must be big and bad. – thus the “prejudice” in “P&amp;P”.).<br />
Hurrah! The “parental issues” totally counts for this whole “internal conflict” the character needs to overcome. (Like, hey, if all you’ve known tells you to distrust a situation, how d’you overcome that?).<br />
As far as I recall, though, the resolution involves the Hero leaving his job and the heroine deciding “ok, I’ll date you.”. I can’t help but feel that one party is giving more to a compromise than the other. – “Okay, I’ll date the handsome/sexy/rich guy who agrees with everything I say” doesn’t feel like a prominent character development, in any case.</p>
<p>Maybe some of this is forgivable for the narrative being a novella. It’s surely more difficult for a novella to have solid characters than a full novel. – I completely adored KAshe’s novella “Kisses, She Wrote”, though; even characters who were given less than a page. So it’s neither the author nor the format at issue here. – And I guess different people are after different things. P&amp;P has enough in it such that people get different things out of it.<br />
Clearly the shoe “lack of internal conflict = boring characters” seems to fit; it’s not clear, though, that the story would obviously be better with whatever “internal conflict”. (Easy fix may be a “I would love the Hero but..”; e.g. ugly Hero [“I’d love him but he’s ugly”], arrogant Hero [“I’d love him but he’s arrogant”], etc.).<br />
And maybe even if the characters are awfully constructed, that the romance is ‘solid’ is nice anyway.</p>
<p>But for characters which aren’t flat, have growth &amp; conflict to resolve, it’s the “internal conflict = not bad character” model seems to work well enough for the Romance Novels as for the action/adventure stories.</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Devil in Winter</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/romance/2015-03-27-devil-in-winter.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/romance/2015-03-27-devil-in-winter.html</id>
    <published>2015-03-27T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-03-27T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on March 27, 2015
    
        by Richard Goulter
    <br/>
    
    Tags: <a href="/tags/lisa%20kleypas.html">lisa kleypas</a>, <a href="/tags/devil%20in%20winter.html">devil in winter</a>
    
</div>

<p>So. Recently I re-read Lisa Kleypas’ “Devil in Winter”.<br />
Not the first time I’ve re-read that book.</p>
<p>There are some less-than-stellar parts of the book. (Notably, an awkward sequel-setup, which then doesn’t get follow-through in the next book besides “oh. that. haha. oops.”.).<br />
But it’s such an amazing, fantastic book! I can’t believe there’re those who don’t think it a 5-outta-5.</p>
<p>It really puts in the punches, constantly chapter-to-chapter the characters grow and interact and fight and flirt.<br />
Presumably you’ve read it if you’re reading this?<br />
I’m not sure I could summarise DiW well. I’m writing this post because I love the book.<br />
I will say there’re so many moments I love in the book!</p>
<p>– In the first chapter. When Sebastian insults Eva, and notices she doesn’t flinch at all. (What kindof upbringing would harden her to that?).<br />
When Sebastian takes care of her on the arduous ride.<br />
The wedding ceremony.<br />
Evie’s concern for her husband when he’s in a fight! Evie’s jealousy of her husband! Sebastian’s jealousy of Evie!<br />
When Sebastian’s wounded on the floor, Evie embrace. :’)<br />
When they’re in the office, Sebastian’s familiar intimacies with his wife.<br />
Sebastian coming into his own, putting his otherwise misdirected skills to good use.</p>
<p>And while I’ve re-read it many times, I still find it hard to put down when I pick it up.</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>On Women in Tech</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/argument/2015-03-27-on-women-in-tech.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/argument/2015-03-27-on-women-in-tech.html</id>
    <published>2015-03-27T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-03-27T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on March 27, 2015
    
        by Richard Goulter
    <br/>
    
    Tags: <a href="/tags/gender.html">gender</a>
    
</div>

<p>So. This is a topic I see come up at various times.<br />
Broadly, tech/STEM/etc. has many more men in it than women, and so naturally there we need to make efforts to remedy this.</p>
<p>This post has also been a post which has been sticking around in my “Draft” pile for a while. Figured I should get it off the shelf sometime.<br />
This post is also quite long. There may be mistakes. Hopefully no one’s forcing you to read it.</p>
<p>If you’re wondering whether anything here intends to offend or not, then of course it’s meant to offend. Probably you, personally.</p>
<h2 id="the-problem">The Problem</h2>
<p>I don’t think the topic of “representation in tech” need be only about gender. I doubt tech has a good representation of class/race, also. But since the rallying cry I hear is always “we need more women in tech”, and attention/effort for other underrepresented groups is rare, I’ll stick to this.</p>
<p>Anyway, let me take a moment to consider the statement “there aren’t a lot of women in tech”.<br />
The assumption as to it being a ‘problem’ is potentially problematic itself.<br />
Because the underlying assumption of “gender ratio should be 50/50” is awfully difficult to be consistent about, (is it problematic that there’re more women than men in university?); and the accusation is that this is said about positions of power or prestiege (e.g. need more women in higher paying positions), rather than with an indifferent lens.<br />
(It’s fine, I think, to say “tech is high paying and so it serves women’s interests to be more involved in tech”).</p>
<p>Part of this question is about perspective:<br />
Commonly, “why aren’t more women in tech?”. Given that there’re more women in university than men, it’s probably more pertinent to ask “why aren’t more men doing not-tech?”.<br />
Similarly, “why are there so many men in tech?” or “why are there so many women in non-tech?” could also be asked.</p>
<p>Regardless, it’d probably still be interesting to ask “why are there so few women in tech?” (without necessarily presuming there should be more women in tech).<br />
If the answer is “because many women choose to do other things”, then perhaps that there’re less women in tech is an example of women’s right and ability to choose. (If we’re willing to suppress this, and consider that maybe we know better than women what’s good for them, then Ashe Schow’s <a href="http://www.washingtonexaminer.com/a-modest-proposal-for-closing-the-gender-wage-gap/article/2556131">modest proposal</a> isn’t so unreasonable, right? – At least, “stop fucking studying sociology, then” is a common enough response I hear regarding woman &amp; tech in university).<br />
But I guess what’s more interesting is what obstacles there may be for the women who do go into CS. Since there are some women in tech, it’s apparent that the obstacles aren’t total / insurmountable. (e.g. that there’s no rule saying you can’t enroll in a CS course if you’re a woman). – But if there are obstacles which prevent people from entering tech for arbitrary reasons, it’s going to be worth getting rid of those obstacles. (Because more people in tech = awesome, because tech is awesome. Though, I think if you ask the Art guy, he’ll say Art is awesome, etc. so..).</p>
<p>– If women as a whole do prefer to study things other than CS, I understand the next tactic to take (by a certain class of people) is to call this “societal/patriarchal oppression”, and then figure out what ways we should change society so as to get more women into CS.<br />
– This is slightly different than considering what obstacles there are for the women who enter into CS now.<br />
It’s also not very respectful of women’s choices; i.e. women aren’t really “respectable” unless they behave the same way men behave. (Or, these women deciding what they want to do are obviously not choosing correctly).</p>
<p>I’ve seen the response “there need to be more people in tech; more of those people need to be women.”<br />
For example, <a href="http://www.wired.com/2014/11/code-documentary-gender-gap/">here</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“How many more Snapchats do we need?” Reynolds asks. “What we need are apps that are going to solve world hunger, medical issues, and environmental problems.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>That’s right, folks. If you have a penis, you surely can’t write an app to solve world hunger.<br />
– Let’s not restrict anyone from entering, sure. But if you’re going to say there’s a <em>need</em> for more of a certain group, your reasoning had better be good. (‘fewer role models = less inspiration or motivation’, which sounds sensible, is less sexist).</p>
<h3 id="cmu">CMU</h3>
<p>– I was fascinated to come across <a href="https://www.cs.cmu.edu/afs/cs/project/gendergap/www/papers/sigcse97/sigcse97.html">this from CMU</a> which discussed the question.<br />
A couple of takeaways would be that the guys entered into CS because they enjoyed tinkering around with computers; the girls entered because for the purpose of harnessing tech for some purpose. All entered into CS with the misunderstanding that CS was ‘just programming’. Girls entered into CS with no prior experience, and initially they underestimated their ability.<br />
– I guess not much changes in 20 years. From my experience as a tutor of an Intro CS course, I’d remark that prior experience can be a hinderance to learning. (i.e. if the hobbyist picks up the bad habits, and isn’t able to adapt to pick up the good habits). I’d also remark as a CS Undergrad that estimation of peer ability is going to be overestimation. (Generally, it’s easy to assume that everyone knows what you know, and that you’re the only one who doesn’t know anything your friends know).<br />
But what interests me further is this takes the question away from an “oh those sexist white men in the patriarchy” narrative to a “how can we better market and introduce CS so as to make it more accessible for women”. (Though I guess this comes from the “women don’t know they need to be in CS” perspective).</p>
<h2 id="feministhackerbarbie-and-cs-culture">#FeministHackerBarbie and CS Culture</h2>
<p>So.<br />
<a href="http://knowyourmeme.com/memes/barbie-i-can-be-a-computer-engineer-parodies">KnowYourMeme</a> has, as usual, a good detailing of this.<br />
Someone noticed a Barbie-as-a-computer-engineer book which featured a ditsy Barbie. (Y’know. There’s a lot of hoo-hah about representation of women. The notion of ‘this is harmful for girls’ gets passed around an awful lot. e.g. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QZqHxw-E2Y4">Caroline Kitchens discussing GoldieBlox</a>).<br />
So the feminist was upset at the political nuances of a toy, particularly one which propagated/enforced an unhealthy stereotype, and we get #FeministHackerBarbie.</p>
<p>Sure. But what’s amusing is the followup I saw on my Twitter feed: #FeministHackerBarbie ‘fixed’ the Barbie by having her be an expert.<br />
But more significantly, above and beyond portraying Barbie as a capable and competant woman, she always did things The Right Way (TM), and almost exclusively #FeministHackerBarbie was complaining about someone else’s incompetency.<br />
– Perhaps to the feminists, calling women stupid is bad. The sin of calling the folk in tech ‘stupid’ here invoked the greater umbrage. Feminism met CS culture, and CS culture jumped at the opportunity of mocking the incompetent.</p>
<p>– And this is relevant because it’s an example of CS culture.<br />
There are two very important points to make here:<br />
Firstly, when I say above it’s good to remove obstacles for new entrants to CS, I generally agree, but I have mixed feelings about “don’t be a dick”. (#FeministHackerBarbie is a dick. Not in a “it’s a powerful woman, and that’s scary” kindof way, but in a mocking and belittling lesser people kindof way).<br />
Secondly, the notion of ‘imposter syndrome’. (The feeling that everyone else is much better than you are, and that you’re an imposter among them since you’re not as good).</p>
<h3 id="dont-be-a-dick">“Don’t be a dick”</h3>
<p>This one I have mixed feelings about.<br />
Moreso because despite what I may say about CS culture and it’s inherent relationship with “being a dick”, I’ve a lot of love and respect for my peers.</p>
<p>Jeff Atwood <a href="https://twitter.com/codinghorror/status/541839452914847744">had a similar thought</a>. Heh.</p>
<p>You’d tend to think there’s no room for discussion about this; you’d think “being a dick” is a bad (and unwelcoming) thing to do, and so any line of thought could start and end with “being a dick is bad, just stop.”.<br />
But even in popular culture, the “genius hero” is often enshrined as a dick. Dr. House is a supergenius doctor, and a major jerk. Sherlock as portrayed by Benedict Cumberpatch is another example. – Even in wider internet culture, it’s not uncommon to see examples of the “smart” people mocking the “dumb” people; e.g. for bad grammar in particular (which perhaps falls close to the dickishness in CS culture).</p>
<p>Programmers love arguing over the most useless of things. The more useless a subject is, the more likely a programmer is willing to argue about it. e.g. which text editor is best, tabs vs spaces, and version numbers are famous examples of this. And yet while these things are useless (mostly), ‘argument’ is still fueled by righteous indignation that one’s own way is better, and the other person is being an idiot for not seeing it.<br />
I don’t think this in and of itself is so bad. But I mean that this “disrespect” is par for the course.</p>
<p>And, you see, there’s a pedantry about all this behaviour; pedantic by training (if not by nature), since the programming languages are formal, so even minor typos and bad grammar, unlike in English (for the most part), are not insignificant. – e.g. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Binary_search_algorithm#Implementation_issues">Binary search can be difficult</a>.<br />
It’s not so much being a dick because CS folk are nasty, so much as any normal “you hurt my feelings” just isn’t relevant when discussing algorithms and programming. – And just like wider society’s intolerance for typos/bad grammar (which is fine if you’re a writer, but overzealous otherwise), there’s a kind of “intolerance” bred for the inefficient. Or the stupid. (e.g. “Why would you do it that way?”).</p>
<p>Since contributing program or suggestion better be good, you’d better take the time to make sure anything you contribute is of quality.<br />
– e.g. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SkdrYWhh-8s">Ben Orenstein’s Expert Level Vim talk</a>. Maybe using the word <em>Expert</em> is just hubris. Maybe it’s that Vim users (ought to) hold an attitude of always looking to improve. But the comments are like ‘<em>This “expert-level vim” is really “first-hour vim”.</em>’. (That, or from people who clearly don’t know enough to call him out on this. But this is a Ruby conference, after all).</p>
<p>For myself, while it’s certainly surprising to find out there’re things I know that some of my classmates don’t, it can be downright disappointing that students attending a “I’m-so-smart-me” prestigious course wouldn’t know fundamental programming/development concepts. Mocking incompetence is bad, sure, but where there’s expectation/demand for some level of competence, then unreasonable inability is an affront.<br />
Of course, there’re many things I’m quite incompetent at. It would be awful if I claimed to be competent in any such area. And so I’d hate to ask a stupid question if I gave the impression that I otherwise knew what I was talking about.</p>
<p>– If I write the above in favour of “being a dick”, it’s because it seems self-evident that in a discussion about being friendlier, “being a dick” can be negative.<br />
But the negative impact of this dickishness is much more insidious than simply “people aren’t nice to each other, and that’s <em>bad</em>.”.<br />
While intolerance for incompetence may drive people to work harder; it’s surely damaging that people aren’t so willing to admit mistakes, or limitations in ability.</p>
<p>– Perhaps another way of rephrasing the problem is “I may be a dick, but you can’t deny I’m effective.”; and characters who live this motto (like Dr House, or recent renditions of Sherlock Holmes) seem to be popular enough. - And I’m not exactly sure what to make of that.</p>
<h4 id="when-nerds-collide">‘When Nerds Collide’</h4>
<p>Since I began writing this post, <span class="citation">[@maradydd's &quot;When Nerds Collide&quot;]</span>(https://medium.com/<span class="citation">@maradydd/when-nerds-collide-31895b01e68c</span>) came up on my feed.<br />
The author deals with an insidious aspect of this conversation; I would phrase it as the “social justice” movement’s incursion into “tech culture”. (I suppose the “social justice” movement would describe it as giving power to the oppressed / displacing bigotry..).<br />
In any case, the author proposes by the end a “hey, here’s what you could do so that there’d be less backlash.”, after discussing reasons why the “identity politics” of the incurring isn’t going down so well with a culture which values ideas &amp; proofs so highly.<br />
It’s a fascinating read on the issue. There’re some pretty choice quotes/ideas in the piece.</p>
<h3 id="imposter-culture">Imposter Culture</h3>
<p>So, again. #FeministHackerBarbie is super pretentious/elite about everything she touches.<br />
Fun as that is, it reminds me of “Imposter Syndrome”. - Which is along the lines of “Of course you’re the one idiot who has no clue what they’re doing. Maybe if you ‘pretend’ well enough, no one will notice.”.</p>
<p>Then so long as you never appear to be stupid, no one will know you’re an imposter.<br />
So, appearing “stupid” is bad.<br />
– That’s a batshit insane ethos to hold in tech culture. When you acknowledge there’s something you don’t know, maybe someone else can inform you about what you don’t know. (Or, given how social CS culture is, you can look it up on your own). - Rather, it’s surely unhealthy to feel an “imposter” when you’re par-for-the-course; to feel an “outsider” when others can immediately relate to your experience.</p>
<p>And how this relates to “women in tech”?<br />
It’s intimidating to the students entering into CS, especially if they’re not one of these “hackers” / of the culture. It’s surely no wonder in the aforementioned CMU study the girls’ underrated their ability.</p>
<p>Maybe the above isn’t really a “problem” if it only involves people’s feelings being hurt; perhaps instead people should just put on their big-person shoes and get over it?<br />
Maybe. But I can’t help but thing a culture which doesn’t allow for making mistakes also isn’t all that great for creativity and productivity. (..and individuality, at that.).</p>
<p>There’s a common anecdote of I think something those who don’t program probably don’t understand about computers/programming: “How do you solve this problem? Google it, try the whatever comes up. If that doesn’t work, repeat from Step 1.”. (When you understand the tools you’re using, you don’t need to do this; but when learning tools, it’s unusual to think of anyone doing it any other way.).<br />
I mean, like. If CS is as “world changing” and beneficial as it promises to be, then those who might be discouraged by “but programming is hard / not something I can do” probably need to be told that’s bullshit. (Some problems are hard. But perhaps also programming is so easy that it makes more problems when programs aren’t made in the “right way”. Hmm. cf. <a href="https://queue.acm.org/detail.cfm?id=2349257">“A Generation Lost in the Bazaar”</a>.).</p>
<p>– Maybe it’s nice for CS to have so much ‘elite prestiege’ about it. (Because what could go wrong about telling a society of people who value ideas how smart they are? It’s sure to improve character!). I’m a little concerned to see that the requirements for entry to study CS are becoming so high. - My classmates point out that they wouldn’t have been allowed in on such a restriction. (One such classmate, as a weekend project, decided to reverse white/black on their LED watch. It takes a skilled and willful individual to do such a thing; it’s uncommonly impressive, I’d say. And his grades weren’t so great in high school.).</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Conflict in Narrative, RE: Genre</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/narrative/2015-03-22-conflict-in-narrative-re-genre.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/narrative/2015-03-22-conflict-in-narrative-re-genre.html</id>
    <published>2015-03-22T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-03-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on March 22, 2015
    
        by Richard Goulter
    <br/>
    
    Tags: <a href="/tags/analysis.html">analysis</a>, <a href="/tags/romance.html">romance</a>
    
</div>

<p>I rambled recently about some genres, romance and action/adventure, particularly that one genre did characters well and the other was strong in plot.<br />
I wondered whether romance genre was inherently worse at plot.</p>
<p>A tool which would help this thought would be the notion of whether conflict is ‘internal’ or ‘external’.<br />
Gunfights, explosions and whatnot would be ‘external’.<br />
Angst, and mustering courage, etc. would be ‘internal’.<br />
Or something like that.</p>
<p>Notably, I was introduced to this concept seeing a comment in a review of a Romance Novel which pointed out all the conflict in the book was ‘external’: everything between Hero &amp; Heroine is fine &amp; dandy.<br />
If we try and map that to action movies, it’s like the heroes arrive on the scene and the battle has already been won; the cavalry arrive and the enemy have already been defeated. It’s not to say the narrative is a bad one; just that you’re not really going to be scoring points in the genre.</p>
<p>So, Romance Novels are character strong, and this depends (at least a bit) on ‘internal’ conflict. If we try and fit it into an either/or, Action/Adventure is great at ‘plot’, which largely depends on ‘external’ conflict.</p>
<p>– And with this tool in hand, it strikes me that one of the reasons RASalvatore sucks so much at writing character is he dresses up ‘external’ conflict, pretends it’s “internal” conflict. e.g.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Drizzt has a mask which would make him look acceptable to other people. Drizzt has angst as to whether wearing this mask is good or not.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Emphasised in the narrative is ‘racism is bad’, and so the key conflict is external (“other people are racist”) and not internal. Hell. RASalvatore’s novels even feature sentient. fucking. objects (e.g. talking sword which tries to influence wielder); so character growth which potentially could be ‘internal’ (“do I have mastery of my sword?”) becomes ‘external’ in Salvatore’s writing. (“do I have mastery of <em>this</em> sword, which is another living being?”).<br />
There are examples in Salvatore’s writing which feature proper character; it’s easy to see how these fit in terms of ‘internal’/‘external’. e.g.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Drizzt realises running off by himself to save the day was silly, and that he relies on his friends more than he thought.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>is ‘internal’, and one of the few moments (in 9 or so books) where Drizzt is more than a cardboard character. Another example in Salvatore’s writing:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Robilard the wizard is cynical due to some past turmoil. Interacting with the light-hearted Harple, Robilard shows some happiness.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>also ‘internal’, even though he’s interacting with someone else. (Because the <em>conflict</em> being dealt with is internal to a person).</p>
<p>It would be difficult to say all conflict fits easily into ‘internal’ or ‘external’, though. Romance Novels are maybe more interesting about this, since it’s rare for a character to grow just by internal reflection.<br />
Consider some from “Devil in Winter”: e.g.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Sebastian says rude words around his wife, Evie. Evie chastises him. Sebastian says “deal with it”. Sebastian isn’t ever seen saying rude words to his wife in this manner after this.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Perhaps inter-personal conflict is particularly unsuited to this ‘internal’/‘external’ model?<br />
More fun is considering examples where it really does blur, though. e.g.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Some of the gaming-house workers are having a tussle. Sebastian must break them up in order to show his worth as a leader.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The development isn’t “Sebastian beats up some guys and saves the day”, but “Sebastian proves his worth as a leader” kindof thing.<br />
Hmm. Maybe not the best example.</p>
<p>Regardless, it’s an interesting tool to have in the toolbox.</p>
<p>So, going back to “do Romance Novels have plots with less conflict?”, it’s clear that RNs (probably) don’t, but instead the conflict they do have is ‘internal’ rather than ‘external’.<br />
And ‘internal’ conflict is to character as ‘external’ conflict is to … ? “Plot”?<br />
In any case. Worth considering next is how much RNs need ‘external’ conflict in their narratives. “Devil in Winter” features plenty. Maya Rodale’s “Seducing Mr. Knightly” features ‘external’ conflict in the form of legal inquiries. Sherry Thomas’ “Tempting the Bride” is, as far as I can recall, free of “external conflict”. (Oh. Hmm. There is Mrs Martin, whose meddling drives a key part of the plot). “Romancing Mr. Bridgerton” has a driving conflict of the mystery of ‘who is Lady Whistledon?’. “Pride and Prejudice” features conflict with Mr. Wickham. – None of this is really “guns and explosion” type stuff, but is all undoubtedly ‘extenal’ conflict.<br />
Hmm.</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>

</feed>
