<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Richard Goulter's Blog</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//atom.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog/" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//atom.xml</id>
    <author>
        <name>Richard Goulter</name>
        <email>richard.goulter+blog@gmail.com</email>
    </author>
    <updated>2023-03-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <entry>
    <title>Review of Apple Pencil for Note Taking</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2023-03-05-review-of-apple-pencil-for-note-taking.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2023-03-05-review-of-apple-pencil-for-note-taking.html</id>
    <published>2023-03-05T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-03-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently purchased the Apple Pencil.</p>
<p>There is a more recent “2nd Generation” Apple Pencil, but the iPad I have is old
enough that it doesn’t support that “2nd Generation”.</p>
<p>Overall, it’s been a useful thing to have, I like using it, but it’s also
probably not worth the cost.</p>
<p>I have found it useful. Before having an Apple Pencil, my household’s use of the
iPad was 99% my wife using it to watch Netflix. – With the Apple Pencil, its
use is 90% for taking notes.</p>
<p>It’s pretty good for handwriting notes.<br />
The feeling isn’t as tactile as an actual pen on actual paper. But, the feeling
isn’t so bad or off so as to be uncomfortable. (Albeit, I strongly recommend
getting some kind of pencil grip. The device itself is very thin!).</p>
<p>Of course, since it is digital, this comes with its own neat benefits:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Hassle-free deletion of mistakes.</p></li>
<li><p>Flexible use of space.</p>
<ul>
<li>The digital paper is practically infinite in width and length.</li>
<li>But, also, it’s easy to move notes about, and so make more space to amend
earlier notes.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>Storage. Digital storage is essentially allows for higher capacity, compared
to paper.</p></li>
<li><p>Text recognition. … Although the apps I’ve tried (Apple’s; and Microsoft’s)
don’t support my use case (described below) nicely, so I don’t use this, and
can’t comment on how useful it is. But, I mean, if you want notes in text,
text-recognition is an advantage over traditional pen &amp; paper tools.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>Using an iPad for notes has some disadvantages; but, is not significantly worse
than pen &amp; paper note taking. (e.g. takes up desk space, and can’t easily copy &amp;
paste text from a workstation).</p>
<p>One limitation is that in some ways it’s more limited than pen &amp; paper. In that,
with pen &amp; paper, you can take notes however you wish. – This leads to all
sorts of note taking idiosyncracies.</p>
<p>So. Here’s how I like making notes while working:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Calendar: I don’t have many meetings, so this isn’t important to me.</p></li>
<li><p>Task Management: I find it useful to keep a list of tasks of “maybe later” or
“too difficult for now” tasks for tasks I’d like done. Stuff like chasing down
loose threads which would deepen my understanding of some system. (Which are
sometimes “not important, until they suddenly become important”).</p></li>
<li><p>Diary: I <em>love</em> maintaining some kind of ‘done list’, with a weekly view of
“here’s what I got done on each day, &amp; what significant obstacles I ran into
that day”.</p></li>
<li><p>Work Journal: In the spirit of “if you’re not writing, you’re not thinking” or
“I wrote it down so that I don’t have to remember”.. I found that I’d often
find myself running into the same error or failure, but forgetting how I’d
solved it earlier.</p>
<ul>
<li>These can be relatively transient. It’s very rare for me to lookup notes
from a long time ago.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<p>Though mostly I only really use handwriting for the ‘diary’ and ‘work journal’
parts.</p>
<p>To elaborate on the ‘work journal’: So, I like writing down a work notes (a
log?) so that it’s easier to offload/recall the mental context I had when
tackling some problem.</p>
<p>A work flow might be:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>writing down the status / work in progress,</p></li>
<li><p>write down the short-term related tasks to do.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>then:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>write down things I try,</p></li>
<li><p>write down problems I face,</p></li>
<li><p>write down any questions I have,</p></li>
<li><p>write down any interesting related facts which might be hard to find later,</p></li>
<li><p>write down any further tasks to follow up for the work to be ‘done’.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>A strong part of my note taking process is colour-coding.</p>
<p>This means a dense page of notes is often colourful, and is easier to scan.
e.g. black for things I tried, red for problems, green for questions, blue for
facts, purple for tasks to do.</p>
<p>For traditional pen &amp; paper, it’s often very easy to find families of pens which
have all of these colours. Or even a good multi-pen which has 4 (albeit, those
are ball-point pens, which are unergonomic).</p>
<p>I’ve even quite liked using a set of Preppy fountain pens, each with cartridge
converters. The Preppy pens are cheap (relative to fountain pens); and can be
found with coloured caps/bodies in each of the colours above.</p>
<p>For the Apple Pencil, I have to rely on what software has been written for the
iPad. – I like OneNote enough, so I thought I’d try it with the Apple Pencil.
It’s fine. It does support easily using different styles of pencil (e.g.
different thicknesses, colours, pen/highlighter). It can cover the above use
case adequately. The most glaring limitation is support for easily switching
colours for the auto-text-recognition. – Maybe some other app supports my use
case better.</p>
<p>In terms of cost.. I was able to get the Preppy pens relatively cheaply. I got
converters for them which were cheaper than the pens; although I see e.g. on
jetpens, this isn’t the case there. – The Apple Pencil is quite expensive. It’s
not worth buying an iPad specifically to use that. I like using the Apple
Pencil. I don’t regret buying it. But, I’d describe it as a luxury purchase, for
the use case of “taking notes on the iPad”. (Whereas, say, I do feel that
“ortholinear keyboard” or “trackball mouse” are such significant ergonomic wins
that they’re worth buying, especially for professionals, despite their high
cost).</p>
<p>Other nit-picky problems with the Apple Pencil:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Without a pencil grip, the device rolls around easily.</p></li>
<li><p>Charging and pairing the device looks very stupid. The butt of the pencil is a
cap for a lightning male connector.</p>
<ul>
<li>Pairing with an iPad involves plugging this into the iPad.</li>
<li>Charging this requires using a F-to-F adaptor in order for it to connect to
an iPad charging cable.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>It requires Bluetooth to be enabled on the iPad, which can be undesirable.</p></li>
</ul>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Disco Elysium</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/games/2023-01-19-disco-elysium.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/games/2023-01-19-disco-elysium.html</id>
    <published>2023-01-19T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-01-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="one-beautiful-moment-from-the-game">One Beautiful Moment from the Game</h3>
<p>I’d only really call something a “spoiler” if it ruins enjoyment from watching
the story.</p>
<p>e.g. The classic show “Columbo” is re-watchable, and we always know that Columbo
will bumble around and annoy the villian in all sorts of homely ways, and ask
“just one more thing”.. but it ruins the suspense if you remember exactly what
the “gotcha” of the episode is.</p>
<p>In contrast, I think the “The Wire” is such a great TV show that hearing what
happens doesn’t spoil it. – Or maybe that’s because of the structure of the
show; the entertainment isn’t structured around figuring out the mystery.</p>
<p>“Disco Elysium” is a cult classic of a game, often enthusiastically recommended
by those who have played it. While I can’t say I enjoyed the gameplay, I found
the story to be very well done.</p>
<p>It’s mature.. not in the sense of sexual content or gore, but in the sense that
it’s got a bitter taste to it. Kinda like Nick Hornby’s “High Fidelity” (which
is also about a music-loving, potentially charming man who’s not quite as cool
as he thinks he had hoped to be).</p>
<p>I think the climax of one of the subplots is so well done, that sharing it
doesn’t spoil the game. (Or maybe it’s because of <em>how</em> the game does it).</p>
<p>The shortest way to describe the game’s setting is that we’ve woken up as a
detective who has lost his memory, after a bender of a night singing sad songs
and trashing his hotel room. We’re supposed to be investigating a murder, which
has sparked tensions between rival factions in a beat-down unimportant corner of
the world (in an alternative universe).</p>
<p>One thing which becomes apparent early on is that the character used to be
married, and misses his ex-wife.</p>
<p>I find the climax to this sub-plot very beautiful.</p>
<p>Because.. as we play through the game, we see the detective can interact well
with all kinds of people. He comfortably converses with those who are angry with
him, with poorly mannered children, with slimy mobster bosses, with intimidating
enforcers.. and he’s able to navigate these conversations and often get what he
wants out of them. (At one point, his reputation proceeds him as a “human can
opener”).</p>
<p>And each night when we sleep, not conscious, the character’s internal monologue
is that of a deep, base resentment of himself. That he’s a failure.</p>
<p>So it’s quite impactful that the game plays differently when the main character
thinks about his ex-wife.</p>
<p>In every other conversation, usually it’s possible to end the conversations
quickly (even if this leads to less than ideal outcomes).</p>
<p>But, when interactions with the character’s ex-wife, the option to “leave
conversation” does nothing; the we can’t just leave a conversation with his
ex-wife, the main character is too enthralled.</p>
<p>In the climax of this subplot, the character has suffered significant physical
injuries, and takes a nap as he is investigating a fresh lead into the case.</p>
<p>In his dream, he takes himself back to a memory of the time where he last saw
his ex-wife, as she’s leaving for the airport. In his dream, she appears to him
as the avatar of the very beautiful, saintly holy patroness of moralism. The
conversation goes around in circles as he keeps admiring her, and she keeps
rejecting him, and saying how things didn’t work out.</p>
<p>It lands so hard.</p>
<p>So, although “talented, unconventional cop with an alcohol problem misses
ex-wife” is extremely cliche, I think how it’s executed in the game is a
demonstration of the game’s quality.</p>
<h3 id="recommendations">Recommendations</h3>
<p>Disco Elysium certainly a game I’ve seen recommended in several places.</p>
<p>e.g. I’d first seen it recommended by Zero Punctuation, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Hi0pyPwxz6Y">stealthily disguised as
a review of Call of Duty</a>.</p>
<p>e.g. The next place I saw it recommended was in the comments of <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8PUCSyIkEus">Mandalore
Gaming’s video on The Mystery of the
Druids</a>. “The Mystery of the
Druids” is an adventure game, which features a detective who acts as
antisocially as typical adventure game character, but in a world where everyone
actually reacts to the antisocial behaviour.</p>
<p>The comments in the video suggested that Disco Elysium is almost a spiritual
successor in this regard.</p>
<p>I can see why. It’s an adventure game. And in the same way “adventure game
character, but where everyone else reacts like a real person would” is a riff on
adventure games, frequently the game will give you dialogue options which are so
strange that characters will ask why you’d say such a thing. (It’s a well done
equivalent to “we’re not in a videogame”).</p>
<p>Similarly, Disco Elysium’s protagonist can act in all sorts of interesting ways;
and the game <em>encourages</em> role-playing into these more colourful roles.</p>
<p>Indeed, Disco Elysium very much is a role-playing game.</p>
<p>I didn’t like this aspect of the game very much.</p>
<p>Whereas, say, The Witcher 3, is more of an Action Role Playing Game. There are
dialogue trees which impact the story. (And I did enjoy how the Witcher 3
handled this with its many side quests). But, ultimately the Witcher 3 has lots
of action, and you’re just such a powerful character.</p>
<p>Disco Elysium, some solutions are gated behind getting a successful dice roll on
a skill check. – I can accept this mechanic during conversations, but I find it
strange that I can’t try to open a container again just because I failed a skill
check.</p>
<p>That said. While I didn’t enjoy the gameplay.. the game’s execution is so well
done, and its story is highly engaging, I also recommend it.</p>
<h1 id="inside-out">Inside Out</h1>
<p>I love Disney Pixar’s “Inside Out”, particularly for an easy and adorable mental
model about how people’s minds work, with different emotions taking the wheel.</p>
<p>Disco Elysium’s story has a similar thing: you’ll have internal characteristics
like “Drama”, “Volution”, “Persuasion”, “Encyclopedia”, etc. The game uses these
as flavourful ways of providing dialogue options.</p>
<p>e.g. With ‘encyclopedia’, you might be informed of the model of a particular
vehicle (which can be useful), or it might recall random irrelevant details.
– I think that’s really cute.</p>
<p>e.g. With ‘drama’ might pick up that someone is lying, or it might suggest
something sarcastic (and unhelpful) to say.</p>
<h1 id="diegeticy">Diegeticy</h1>
<p>I think part of what makes the game so well done is how it handles “this isn’t a
videogame”.</p>
<p>For example, I think it’s an interesting detail that the game starts with the
character having amnesia. – It’s interesting because throughout the game, you
get to ask other characters details about the world.<br />
– In other games, this might be business as usual. But in this game, there’s a
sense the NPC is thinking “ugh, why are you asking me questions about the
world”.</p>
<p>I mean, the player character not knowing about the world is ‘diagetic’ in the
sense that the player doesn’t know the world (which is the point of the trope),
but that this not knowing also plays out significantly in the gameplay. (As
opposed to, say, the Bourne Identity, wherein the player’s amnesia drives the
plot more than it really hinders the protagonists’ perceived competency).</p>
<p>I think a lot of the writing is like this; it’s almost like the protagonist acts
like a detective in a detective videogame (e.g. “I found this item I can
interact with, so it must be significant to the case”), and a lot of the writing
reminds him that he’s not the protagonist in a videogame.</p>
<p>The game as a whole probably serves as a good demonstration that tropes aren’t
necessarily bad; it’s about how they’re used.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Post Factorio Playthrough Ramble</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/games/2022-12-27-post-factorio-playthrough-ramble.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/games/2022-12-27-post-factorio-playthrough-ramble.html</id>
    <published>2022-12-27T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2022-12-27T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Okay, so maybe Factorio is “hyper-engaging”.</p>
<p>After playing through the game a bit on the Nintendo Switch,
I decided that I’d go back and play the game
in order to complete a few more
of the game’s achievements.</p>
<p>So I went to load my savegame from when I’d completed a
game on peaceful, only to discover that this savegame
was from an old pre-1.0 version of the game, and so
wouldn’t load.</p>
<p>Darn.</p>
<p>Guess my best option was to start a new game.</p>
<p>(Having played through the game on the standard non-peaceful,
I’d decided that I prefer to play on peaceful).</p>
<p>I’d describe my time as a “bender”.</p>
<p>I did learn some things, though.</p>
<p>This time, I made use of Factorio’s railway systems.
I’d previously thought this was intimidatingly difficult.
Fortunately, one of the Guides in the Steam Community provides
blueprints for a set of rails with the following nice
properties:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>4 lanes of rails, spaced such-that the outer-pair of rails
form a neat U-turn shape.</p></li>
<li><p>To simplify the train signals, each rail only allows
trains to go one-way.</p></li>
<li><p>The outer pair of rails is intended for trains to then
leave/enter train stations, whereas the inner pair of rails
is intended for ‘express’.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>I do generally worry that just using other people’s blueprints
takes out half of the fun of the game. (Especially if the blueprint
is well-optimised, and not something you’d naturally think of).
– With these rails designs, I felt I was able to enjoy the game
more without having to do this thinking though.</p>
<p>I did also borrow from <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MPUcU37hXH4">a mall design that KatherineOfSky</a> presented
a few years ago. I didn’t notice that this was for an older version of
the game.</p>
<p>One other thing I did better this game was “get comfortable with
the nuclear power system”. The nuclear power system is complicated
because it involves dealing with heat (which behaves differently than
other resources systems in the game), and dealing with the two kinds of uranium (which comes with its own issues).</p>
<p>My goal was to clear some of the achievements which deal with the late game.
I hadn’t achieved “research all technology”, the top “produce X amount of iron”,
the last “produce 20M green circuits” achievements; and a post-game “have 100 robot followers” achievement.</p>
<p>I find the game to be hyper-engaging up until researching blue science; at which
point there are <em>so many</em> exciting things to do, that I have to slow down to
focus task by task on what to achieve.</p>
<p>In particular, ‘blue science’ is when the construction &amp; logistic robots become available.<br />
And so while Factorio is overall a game about designing systems..
the construction robots are the game mechanic where this really takes off.<br />
The construction robots will automatically place buildings/etc. from blueprint designs. (It’s also possible to ad-hoc copy-paste buildings using the construction bots). – So if you’ve placed your buildings in such a way that they can be tiled, this allows rapidly scaling parts of your factory up. (Or, if you’ve got blueprint designs from previous playthroughs/wherever, bots will be able to start constructing these).<br />
The logistic robots can bring items to you so long as your factory has the robo-ports built in a ‘network’. (You can come up with a tiling design of robo-ports such that you can use construction bots to construct a large roboport network area…). And, later, certain storage boxes can have requirements set, so that the logistic robots will ensure the boxes have those items. (This allows e.g. creating a ‘cache’ area, so you can quickly have whatever items you want delivered to you).</p>
<p>I mean, I knew the robots were good previously.
But, I find the game shifts gears when they’re unlocked.</p>
<p>Previously, I’d always puttered along in the last mile when reaching the game’s
end objective of launching a rocket. But, since I wanted some achievements which
require multiple rocket launches, I was able to continue developing my factory.</p>
<p>This meant I was able to try out more of the late-game combat stuff. (Even
though the game was peaceful, I still did have to clear out enemy bases which
got in my way).</p>
<p>The robot followers are very powerful, and kinda allow just waltzing through
an enemy base.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://wiki.factorio.com/Spidertron">spidertron</a> was a lot of fun to use.</p>
<p>The post-game technologies increased the range and firing speed of the rail
artillery; which became my favourite tool for clearing out big areas of land. –
I’d not used laser turrets before. (My main non-peaceful playthrough had been
for getting a “no lasers” and “no solar power” achievement). The laser turrets
were very convenient for defending the rail artillery! (The enemy would rush the
site where the artillery fired from).</p>
<p>The main ‘insight’ I gained was from using the trains / railway network. Rather,
because I’d never used the trains for transporting resources, I’d always just
used the standard transport belts.. with trains, trains allow ‘decoupling’
resource movement.</p>
<p>That is: with trains, you have a station where you load some resource, and a
station where you unload that resource. With Factorio, stations can be named by
their role, and a train can be routed to follow a route like “refuel -&gt; load
resource X -&gt; unload resource X”. The train station’s name is an indirection; it
doesn’t concretely matter where the station is.</p>
<p>Whereas, the with the transport belts, the belts must be explicitly placed on
the map. There’s no indirection, no flexibility. If some resource is depleted,
you can place more belts; but that’s all you can do.</p>
<p>Logistic bots similarly can automatically move resources from one location to
another, but with a more limited throughput and a more limited distance compared
to trains.</p>
<p>Rather. I found it neat to be able to consider “load input, move it, unload” as
an abstraction. – Although, a lot of Factorio is dealing with the details of
the implementation.</p>
<p>I saw on YouTube there are speedruns of the game in under two hours; speedruns on random seeds in under three; speedruns of getting 100% achievements in under four or five hours!<br />
These are all impressive.</p>
<p>In speedruns, the player will also bootstrap the factory with techniques which
don’t scale well. An assembly machine will be placed &amp; will require the player
to manually insert the input ingredients. – This doesn’t ‘scale’ since it’s
infeasible for the player to continue doing this for the whole game; but for
bootstrapping the factory, it’s quicker than setting things up ‘the right way’.</p>
<p>I’ve also heard the term “city blocks” in the community.</p>
<p>I got the achievement for producing 20M green circuits.</p>
<p>By that time, my factory was producing about 60 of each science per minute. The
“megafactories” that some enthusiasts go for aim for 1000 of each science per
minute.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, I hadn’t really scaled up the green circuit production. So,
getting the achievement was more from “playing the post-game for quite some
time” than from “you have a factory which is producing many green circuits”.</p>
<p>The remaining achievements I haven’t yet unlocked are related to completing the
game quickly.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Factorio on the Switch Still Scratches the Itch</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/games/2022-12-11-factorio-on-the-switch-still-scratches-the-itch.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/games/2022-12-11-factorio-on-the-switch-still-scratches-the-itch.html</id>
    <published>2022-12-11T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2022-12-11T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Factorio is a game which is widely regarded as addictingly fun to play.</p>
<p>The ostensible goal of the game is to assemble &amp; launch a rocket ship.</p>
<p>The start of the game is reasonably familiar: you control a character, mine some
ores from resource deposits, and then use these resources to assemble tools or
whatever item you need. (e.g. you’ll mine some iron ore, put this ore in a
furnace,
and use the resulting iron plates to assemble an iron pickaxe).<br />
– Factorio allows for automating these process. A mining machine can
automatically gather resources; conveyor belts can automatically move these
resources along; an assembly machine can automatically assemble some item, and
inserter arm machines can automatically insert items from the convey belts into
the assembly machines.</p>
<p>The first time you play the game (if you don’t read guides first), you’ll
probably end up with a factory which works, but you’ll certainly end up with
something that’s difficult to maintain or improve on. You’ll end up with
a disorganised mess.<br />
(Then you hear the term “main bus”, and that helps organise things <em>a lot</em>).</p>
<p>The dynamic of the game ends up feeling very similar to programming or
electrical engineering.<br />
So much so that, while I think most programmers who play the game find it
addictively engaging, there are also those who don’t want to play it. – I think
it’s one of two responses: “it’s similar to what I do for work, but without
having to do what others tell me to do, and without having to be reliable. Fun!”
or “it’s similar to what I do for work, but I don’t benefit from putting in the
effort.
Why would I do that?”.<br />
I mean, there’s a satisfying feeling of constructing a system which works (as
well as ‘debugging’ why some system doesn’t work).</p>
<p>I think complementing this is that usually there are multiple things that you
can do to reduce the mess in your factory; and that improvements often have some
delay before you see the tangible benefits from them. So there’s often some task
you can aim towards that feels satisfying to do. (Sid Meier’s Civilization games
are similarly entralling).</p>
<p>Probably “fun is in the eye of the beholder”.<br />
There are parts of Factorio where I think it’s fun for me to come up with my own
solution to the problem. There are parts where I’d rather lookup a guide for how
to do it on the Factorio wiki, or some YouTube video.</p>
<p>I found it fun to play Factorio with particular challenges/goals in mind. One
achievement requires that you craft only the minimal number of items by hand
(and use assembly machines to bootstrap the rest). Another achievement was to
play the game on non-peaceful, but without using solar power.</p>
<p>“Non-peaceful” mode is the default setting for the enemies’ aggression mode.
The player’s factory produces pollution; the enemies react to the pollution by
getting stronger and attacking the player every now and then in waves. Whereas,
in peaceful mode, enemies will only attack if attacked first (and attacking
one enemy base doesn’t ‘aggro’ other enemy bases).<br />
In my experience, non-peaceful mode ‘just’ requires the extra pushback/effort of
automatically building (sufficient) ammunition/defenses, etc. – It adds a bit
of pressure/flavor to the game, and isn’t extremely stressful, but I prefer to
play with peaceful mode.</p>
<p>At the higher end of things, some players enjoy seeing how frequently their
factory is able to assemble/launch a rocket (since this requires a well organised
factory at significant scale). – I’ve not yet tried doing this.</p>
<p>For the playthroughs I’ve spent significant time on, I inevitably had the same
task/notes system I use when programming. (Start the day by writing down status
of WIP; write down tasks to-do, and obstacles faced which need to be resolved).</p>
<p>Anyway.</p>
<p>The game was recently released for the Nintendo Switch. I was travelling for a couple of
weeks, have a Nintendo Switch, and have enjoyed playing Factorio.</p>
<p>I can vouch that the game scratches the same itch as it does on PC.</p>
<p>The controls are reasonably nice, although using the controller won’t be as fast
as using the mouse.</p>
<p>I think if someone were (somehow) playing through Factorio for the first time on
the Nintendo Switch, I think they’d opt to play on PC by the time they got to
the blue science technologies. (About halfway through the game). – Because at
that point, you’ve unlocked trains and the construction robots and solar power
and electric furances… there’s lots of stuff which can all be used to improve
your factory. (Trains are earlier; but, I didn’t bother assembling rail stuff
until after I’d assembled blue science).</p>
<p>I’d bet that the Switch is suited to people having the large post-game factories.
I never noticed performance issues in my playing, though.</p>
<p>If someone were wondering whether to by Factorio for PC or for the Switch, I’d
say “yes”. Well, I don’t think anyone’s going to regret buying this game. I
think PC is the better environment to play it on. But, on the Switch it still
stratches the same itch just the same.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>The CapsLock Key was not the Problem</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2022-10-28-the-capslock-key-was-not-the-problem.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2022-10-28-the-capslock-key-was-not-the-problem.html</id>
    <published>2022-10-28T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2022-10-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s fashionable among developers to give a tip about the CapsLock key: you can switch out its functionality, replacing it with the Escape key.</p>
<p>When I did this, in order to then type out something like <code>SEQUENCE_OF_UPPERCASE_WORDS</code>, I’d hold down the shift key using my left pinky finger, and type out the letters as necessary.<br />
– And if you can do that, then the CapsLock key is redundant.</p>
<p>These days, I prefer using a fancy, symmetrical keyboard. (I think buying an expensive fancy keyboard is justifiable if it’s symmetrical, and offers more keys for the thumb to press; and I don’t think it makes sense to spend a lot of money on a keyboard which isn’t symmetrical, etc.).<br />
And the fashionable (and I think superior) way of arranging the modifier keys Shift, Ctrl, Windows/Cmd, Alt keys is to put these as dual-use tap-hold keys
on the home row. (Which allows access to these keys without having to move your hand).</p>
<p>With such a keyboard, and with home row modifiers, the “use an improper position which stretches your weak pinky finger” technique doesn’t really work.<br />
Instead, to type <code>UPPERCASE</code>, you end up having to alternate use of the shift key; pressing shift for the opposite side of the letter being pushed.<br />
– I can do this; but I find it to be slower, and error prone. (It’s easy to miss the timing, and type ‘THhiS’ instead of ‘THIS’, as the Shift key requires holding down ‘h’).</p>
<p>For long sequences of uppercases letters, it does make sense to have the CapsLock key available. – Though, with a fancy keyboard, you can have the CapsLock key accessible on (or hidden away on) a layer.</p>
<p>Rather. The CapsLock functionality itself isn’t inherently useless, and needn’t be banished.<br />
It’s that, in a standard keyboard, the real-estate of “on home row, easy to reach” that the CapsLock key occupies is put to much better use by using it for Escape (or Ctrl, or dual-use Escape/Ctrl).<br />
Since a fancy keyboard is nicer to use (the modifier keys are easy to each, and layers allow bringing more keys to within easy reach), you get to use the CapsLock key without it taking up space which could be better utilized.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>The just Command Runner is an Neat Tool</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2022-10-17-the-just-command-runner-is-an-neat-tool.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2022-10-17-the-just-command-runner-is-an-neat-tool.html</id>
    <published>2022-10-17T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2022-10-17T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I came across the tool <a href="https://just.systems/man/en/chapter_1.html">just</a>.</p>
<p>It’s a tool for running commands/scripts.</p>
<p>My initial impression was “that’s it?”.</p>
<p>I might describe it slightly differently, compared to other common workflows:</p>
<ul>
<li>It’s common to see <code>make</code> used with a bunch of <code>.PHONY:</code> targets. The point
of a <code>make</code> is to describe how some target is built. But since people will
often want to run tasks (e.g. run tests with <code>make test</code>), a ‘phony’ target
is a task where the target isn’t a file that gets built.
<ul>
<li>Compared to “use <code>make</code> with a bunch of <code>.PHONY</code> targets”, <code>just</code> has some
nice quality of life features.
<ul>
<li>e.g. with <code>just</code>, you don’t have to indent the definitions using Tabs.</li>
<li>e.g. <code>just</code> can list the targets in its <code>justfile</code>.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul></li>
<li>In the NodeJS ecosystem, its <code>package.json</code> files often contain a <code>scripts</code>
property, which is used to describe common tasks that will be run when
working with the project.
<ul>
<li>Compared to this, a <code>justfile</code> is more expressive / less constrained.
<ul>
<li>e.g. ‘make with <code>.PHONY</code> targets’ is more expressive than
<code>package.json</code>’s scripts`.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul></li>
<li>It’s common to have a ‘script directory’ where you keep a bunch of scripts
for common functionality.
<ul>
<li>Compared to this, <code>just</code> allows for a consistent starting point, some
quality of life features (e.g. by-default always starting scripts with
starting directory being the <code>justfile</code>’s directory) and allow for
integration with editors.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<p>Overall, I find that quite persuasive: it’s more polished/tailored than <code>make</code>
for a particular use case; and that use case is something which developers
definitely make use of.</p>
<p>There is the downside that <code>just</code> isn’t a standard tool that you can hope to
find on most systems (in contrast to e.g. <code>python</code>, <code>bash</code>, or maybe <code>awk</code> or
<code>make</code>).<br />
But, installing packages isn’t all that hard. (And <code>just</code> is <a href="https://just.systems/man/en/chapter_4.html">available in many
places</a>).<br />
And I use <code>nix</code>, so it’s especially easy to ensure it’s available when I want
it.</p>
<p>I think this is a good example of “sometimes better isn’t MUCH better; it’s
merely slightly better”.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Using NixOS Specialisations to Try Out Different Desktop Environments</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2022-10-06-using-nixos-specialisations-to-try-out-different-desktop-environments.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2022-10-06-using-nixos-specialisations-to-try-out-different-desktop-environments.html</id>
    <published>2022-10-06T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2022-10-06T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently, Tweag’s blog featured a post on <a href="https://www.tweag.io/blog/2022-08-18-nixos-specialisations/">NixOS
specialisations</a>.</p>
<p>It allows for having an additional boot entry in grub which
loads a slightly different configuration. – This makes it very convenient
to try slightly different NixOS configurations.</p>
<p>As the blogpost above shows, this can be used for different desktop environments.</p>
<p>I ran into some problems with conflicting attributes, and wasn’t previously
aware of how to set the priority. (e.g. as discussed in this <a href="https://discourse.nixos.org/t/what-does-mkdefault-do-exactly/9028">discourse
post</a>).</p>
<p>e.g. I’d wanted to try out the <a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/title/Pantheon">Pantheon</a> desktop environment, which comes out of <a href="https://elementary.io/">Elementary OS</a> and looks very nice. – But, if you try to enable both <code>services.xserver.desktopManager.gnome</code> and <code>services.xserver.desktopManager.pantheon</code>, you get an error like:</p>
<pre><code>error: The option `environment.sessionVariables.NIX_GSETTINGS_OVERRIDES_DIR&#39; has conflicting definition values:</code></pre>
<p>Not knowing about overriding attribute priorities, my first attempt at solving this problem was using <code>specialisations</code> to separate the conflicting config options: <a href="https://github.com/rgoulter/nix-user-repository/blob/8df3abaea46b8fbd5d212e64c209d5ef0602955c/modules/desktops.nix">8df3…/modules/desktops.nix</a>.</p>
<p>Knowing the above about overriding attribute priorites, it makes sense that it’s possible to use Gnome in the ‘parent’ config, and to disable Gnome in the specialisations, with:</p>
<pre><code>services.xserver.desktopManager.gnome.enable = lib.mkDefault true;</code></pre>
<p>e.g. <a href="https://github.com/rgoulter/nix-user-repository/blob/c3f0df686ea024f3fae8da13dae6e10a02e920cd/modules/desktops.nix">c3f0…./modules/desktops.nix</a>.</p>
<pre class="nix"><code>{ config, lib, pkgs, ... }:

{
  services = {
    xserver = {
      desktopManager.gnome.enable = lib.mkDefault true;
      displayManager.gdm.enable = lib.mkDefault true;

      enable = true;

      layout = &quot;us&quot;;
    };
  };

  specialisation = {
    gnome.configuration = {
      services.xserver = {
        desktopManager.gnome.enable = true;
        displayManager.gdm.enable = true;
      };
      system.nixos.tags = [ &quot;gnome&quot; ];
    };
    pantheon.configuration = {
      services.xserver = {
        # Pantheon conflicts with gnome
        desktopManager = {
          gnome.enable = false;
          pantheon.enable = true;
        };
        # Pantheon requires lightdm
        displayManager = {
          gdm.enable = false;
          lightdm.enable = true;
        };
      };
      system.nixos.tags = [ &quot;pantheon&quot; ];
    };
    xfce.configuration = {
      networking.networkmanager.enable = true;
      services.xserver = {
        desktopManager = {
          gnome.enable = false;
          xfce.enable = true;
        };
        displayManager = {
          gdm.enable = false;
        };
      };
      system.nixos.tags = [ &quot;gnome&quot; ];
    };
  };
}</code></pre>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Git Worktrees a Neat Command for Working with Multiple Versions of a Repo</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2022-10-01-git-worktrees-a-neat-command-for-working-with-multiple-versions-of-a-repo.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2022-10-01-git-worktrees-a-neat-command-for-working-with-multiple-versions-of-a-repo.html</id>
    <published>2022-10-01T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2022-10-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://git-scm.com/docs/git-worktree">git-worktree</a> has apparently been in git
for some time, but I’ve only recently learned of it.</p>
<p>It lets you conveniently check out multiple versions of a repository at once.</p>
<p>Which may sound only marginally useful; but I find the benefit to be better than
it sounds. (e.g. Without the worktree command, perhaps the easiest way to
imitate it would be to clone from the local repository, and adjust the remotes).</p>
<p>I’ve found it’s useful to keep a checkout of the master branch, as well as using
worktrees for feature branches, or other experimenting.</p>
<p>By keeping work-in-progress in a separate working tree, you don’t have to worry
about the working tree being dirty in order to check out different versions.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Signal Boost drduh's Yubikey Guide</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2022-09-30-signal-boost-dr-duhs-yubikey-guide.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2022-09-30-signal-boost-dr-duhs-yubikey-guide.html</id>
    <published>2022-09-30T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2022-09-30T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://github.com/drduh/YubiKey-Guide" class="uri">https://github.com/drduh/YubiKey-Guide</a></p>
<p>I recently set up my Yubikeys so that I could use the key to hold the private
keys I use with git.</p>
<p>I spent a bunch of time reading through various guides discussing how to set up
a master key with an offline backup, and how to put this on a GPG smartcard.</p>
<p>Drduh’s guide above is the best I’ve come across.</p>
<p>e.g. Most guides only mention the interactive way to generate keys. This guide
at least mentions using a <a href="https://github.com/drduh/YubiKey-Guide#create-keys-with---batch-and---quick-add-keys">the batch
interface</a>.</p>
<p>(c.f. <a href="https://github.com/rgoulter/nix-user-repository/blob/a96522d387396e7dd9ab8b6e489a97ffb6bcec92/scripts/gpg-quick-generate-master-key.sh">my key generation
invocations</a>).</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Travel Setup Using a Fancy Keyboard with a Laptop</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2022-08-24-travel-setup-using-a-fancy-keyboard-with-a-laptop.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2022-08-24-travel-setup-using-a-fancy-keyboard-with-a-laptop.html</id>
    <published>2022-08-24T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2022-08-24T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the downsides to using a fancy keyboard is that it’s difficult to use
when out and about with a laptop.</p>
<p>This is arguably mitigated by that laptops themselves have a keyboard.</p>
<p>I like my small, fancy keyboard much more than the laptop keyboard, though.
(My thumbs get access to 2-3 keys each on my fancy keyboard, etc.).</p>
<p>Here’s the travel setup I’ve used:</p>
<p>The first thing which helps is getting a bit of acrylic cut to shape, with some
bumpons to lift it above the keys:</p>
<p><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/rgoulter/rgoulter.github.com/master/images/keyboards/travel-setup/keyboard_travel_mba.JPG" /></p>
<p><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/rgoulter/rgoulter.github.com/master/images/keyboards/travel-setup/keyboard_travel_mba_plate.JPG" /></p>
<p>In terms of cables:</p>
<p>I was able to have a working setup with an ordinary USB-C cable. Since the
cable needs some clearance, the keyboard couldn’t quite be close to the screen.
Thanks to how HUGE the Macbook trackpads are, I could get by without needing an
extra mouse.</p>
<p><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/rgoulter/rgoulter.github.com/master/images/keyboards/travel-setup/keyboard_travel_mba_plate_usbc.JPG" /></p>
<p>What I haven’t yet tried while traveling, but I expect to work much better, is
to use a USB-C cable with a right-angle connector:</p>
<p><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/rgoulter/rgoulter.github.com/master/images/keyboards/travel-setup/keyboard_travel_mba_plate_rightangle.JPG" /></p>
<p>Unfortunately, use of right-angled connectors like this depends a bit on the
keyboard. In the following pictures, both have a magnetic connector inserted.
The right-angled USB-C cables I’ve tried cannot connect to the BM40, since the
case is too thick.</p>
<p><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/rgoulter/rgoulter.github.com/master/images/keyboards/travel-setup/keyboard_bm40.JPG" /></p>
<p><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/rgoulter/rgoulter.github.com/master/images/keyboards/travel-setup/keyboard_gh60_case.JPG" /></p>]]></summary>
</entry>

</feed>
