<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Richard Goulter's Blog</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//atom.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog/" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//atom.xml</id>
    <author>
        <name>Richard Goulter</name>
        <email>richard.goulter+blog@gmail.com</email>
    </author>
    <updated>2023-09-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <entry>
    <title>Using NixOS on an OpenStack Public Cloud</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2023-09-09-using-nixos-on-an-openstack-public-cloud.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2023-09-09-using-nixos-on-an-openstack-public-cloud.html</id>
    <published>2023-09-09T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-09-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here are some notes on using NixOS in an OpenStack public cloud.</p>
<p>Recall, NixOS is an operating system which makes use of the Nix package manager to manage its system configuration.<br />
That NixOS allows declarative configuration of a system lends itself to building cloud VM images.</p>
<p>OpenStack is a standard cloud computing platform. It offers services broadly similar to AWS’ EC2, S3, etc..</p>
<p>One option for deploying NixOS configurations to a cloud VM is to run a NixOS VM, and then switch that VM to the configuration you want. – If the cloud provider doesn’t have a NixOS VM image to run, you’ll have to build your own image.</p>
<h3 id="general-approach">General Approach</h3>
<p>The most ‘challenging’ part of this is wanting to run a NixOS VM, but the cloud provider not having a public NixOS image.</p>
<p>It’s possible to build a your own image in a format the cloud provider wants.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://github.com/nix-community/nixos-generators">nix-community’s nixos-generators</a> is a good place to start for this.<br />
Many popular image formats are supported.</p>
<p>In the case of OpenStack images, there’s a generator specifically for that.<br />
I guess for other cloud providers, some customisation may be required; I’d dig through the
code within <a href="https://github.com/NixOS/nixpkgs/tree/master/nixos/maintainers/scripts/">nixos’ maintainers/scripts/</a> and <a href="https://github.com/NixOS/nixpkgs/tree/master/nixos/modules/virtualisation">modules/virtualisation/</a> to get an idea of what was done for the ones which are supported.</p>
<h3 id="using-terraform-to-launch-a-vm-on-an-openstack-public-cloud">Using Terraform to Launch a VM on an OpenStack Public Cloud</h3>
<p>I was doing this from a rather weak Macbook Air (Intel). I figured it’d be easier to build Linux images using Linux; so the first thing to do is launch a linux VM in the cloud.</p>
<p>My experience with using OpenStack on public clouds is that the networking may be handled slightly differently from one public cloud and another.<br />
(The related “used to hope this would work” is the idea of “Terraform works with different clouds” translating to “plenty of Terraform code can be reused in order to easily support a multi-cloud deployment; e.g. have the same service in both AWS and GCP”. Maybe for OpenStack public clouds this could be largely true; but, it’s unlikely Terraform code for networking resources can be reused).</p>
<p>With AWS, I would think that an example of a simple Terraform task is “launch a VM with a publicly accessible IP”.<br />
From what I’ve tried, it’s slightly trickier with OpenStack public clouds.</p>
<p>I had some spare credits with <a href="https://cleura.com/">Cleura</a> to use, and they offer a public cloud with an OpenStack API.</p>
<p>Managing OpenStack resources from outside the cloud console requires an OpenStack user.
I found it convenient to download the RC file for the user, and use <a href="https://direnv.net/">direnv</a> to load those credentials.</p>
<p>Here’s the code listing for a <code>main.tf</code> to achieve this (with some notes below):</p>
<pre><code>terraform {
  required_providers {
    openstack = {
      source  = &quot;terraform-provider-openstack/openstack&quot;
      version = &quot;~&gt; 1.49.0&quot;
    }
  }
}

provider &quot;openstack&quot; {}

# Variables

variable &quot;default_user_name&quot; {
  description = &quot;the name of the default user&quot;
  type        = string
  default     = &quot;debian&quot;
}

variable &quot;ssh_public_key&quot; {
  description = &quot;the SSH public key used to access the VM&quot;
  type        = string
  default     = &quot;ssh-ed25519 AAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA&quot;
}

variable &quot;allow_ssh_access_cidr&quot; {
  description = &quot;the CIDR to allow SSH access to. Defaults to 0.0.0.0/0 (unrestricted)&quot;
  type        = string
  default     = &quot;0.0.0.0/0&quot;
}

variable &quot;flavor&quot; {
  description = &quot;the compute flavor to use&quot;
  type        = string
  default     = &quot;1C-2GB-20GB&quot;
}

variable &quot;image_name&quot; {
  description = &quot;the name of the image the VM uses&quot;
  type        = string
  default     = &quot;Debian 11 Bullseye x86_64&quot;
}

variable &quot;instance_name&quot; {
  description = &quot;the name of the VM&quot;
  type        = string
  default     = &quot;debian&quot;
}

# OpenStack Server flavor &amp; image

data &quot;openstack_compute_flavor_v2&quot; &quot;self&quot; {
  name = var.flavor
}

data &quot;openstack_images_image_v2&quot; &quot;self&quot; {
  name        = var.image_name
  most_recent = true
}

# Networking

data &quot;openstack_networking_network_v2&quot; &quot;ext&quot; {
  name = &quot;ext-net&quot;
}

resource &quot;openstack_networking_network_v2&quot; &quot;self&quot; {
  name           = &quot;terraform_vm_network&quot;
  admin_state_up = &quot;true&quot;
}

resource &quot;openstack_networking_subnet_v2&quot; &quot;self&quot; {
  name       = &quot;terraform_vm_subnet&quot;
  network_id = openstack_networking_network_v2.self.id
  cidr       = &quot;192.168.199.0/24&quot;
  ip_version = 4
}

resource &quot;openstack_networking_router_v2&quot; &quot;self&quot; {
  name                = &quot;terraform_vm_router&quot;
  external_network_id = data.openstack_networking_network_v2.ext.id
}

resource &quot;openstack_networking_router_interface_v2&quot; &quot;self&quot; {
  router_id = openstack_networking_router_v2.self.id
  subnet_id = openstack_networking_subnet_v2.self.id
}

resource &quot;openstack_networking_floatingip_v2&quot; &quot;self&quot; {
  pool = data.openstack_networking_network_v2.ext.name
}

# Security

resource &quot;openstack_compute_secgroup_v2&quot; &quot;allow_ssh&quot; {
  name        = &quot;allow_ssh&quot;
  description = &quot;allow SSH from the given CIDR&quot;

  rule {
    from_port   = 22
    to_port     = 22
    ip_protocol = &quot;tcp&quot;
    cidr        = var.allow_ssh_access_cidr
  }
}

resource &quot;openstack_compute_keypair_v2&quot; &quot;self&quot; {
  name       = &quot;terraform_keypair&quot;
  public_key = var.ssh_public_key
}

# Instance

resource &quot;openstack_compute_instance_v2&quot; &quot;self&quot; {
  name            = var.instance_name
  flavor_id       = data.openstack_compute_flavor_v2.self.id
  key_pair        = openstack_compute_keypair_v2.self.name
  security_groups = [openstack_compute_secgroup_v2.allow_ssh.name]
  user_data       = &lt;&lt;-USER
  #cloud-config
  system_info:
   default_user:
    name: ${var.default_user_name}
  chpasswd: { expire: false }
  ssh_pwauth: false
  package_upgrade: true
  manage_etc_hosts: localhost
  runcmd:
    - &quot;curl --proto &#39;=https&#39; --tlsv1.2 -sSf -L https://install.determinate.systems/nix | sh -s -- install --no-confirm&quot;
  USER

  block_device {
    uuid                  = data.openstack_images_image_v2.self.id
    source_type           = &quot;image&quot;
    volume_size           = 20 # GBs
    boot_index            = 0
    destination_type      = &quot;volume&quot;
    delete_on_termination = true
  }
}

resource &quot;openstack_compute_floatingip_associate_v2&quot; &quot;self&quot; {
  floating_ip = openstack_networking_floatingip_v2.self.address
  instance_id = openstack_compute_instance_v2.self.id
}

# Outputs

output &quot;public_ipv4&quot; {
  value = openstack_networking_floatingip_v2.self.address
}</code></pre>
<p>Again, I found the networking details to be a quite complicated.<br />
The details were found by observing what resources were created when creating a VM with a public IP in the console.<br />
Cleara uses the public network <code>ext-net</code>.<br />
I’m not sure on the exact details, but I create a private network with a subnet, and to get a public IP (i.e. a floating ip in <code>ext-net</code>) to route to the VM, I create a router for the <code>ext-net</code> and a router interface which routes that to the private subnet. That public IP then gets associated with the VM.</p>
<p>Another part that can be annoying with OpenStack is specifying the VM resources (CPU/memory/storage).<br />
It’s more flexible than AWS’ “c5.small/medium/large”.<br />
One thing I found annoying it it’s not quite so freeform as <code>"xC-yGB-zGB"</code> for arbitrary x,y,z; I had to list the flavors to find one.<br />
(The impression I got was that the console lets you choose the number of cpu/mem/disk, so the flavor is created on demand for that).</p>
<p>Idiosyncracies of OpenStack clouds aside, I think the other details are relatively straightforward.<br />
The name <code>"Debian 11 Bullseye x86_64"</code> comes from running <code>openstack images list</code>.<br />
(An easy way to get the <code>openstack</code> client is to run <code>nix shell nixpkgs#openstackclient</code>).</p>
<p>Looking at the user data passed to the VM…</p>
<pre><code>#cloud-config
system_info:
 default_user:
  name: ${var.default_user_name}
chpasswd: { expire: false }
ssh_pwauth: false
package_upgrade: true
manage_etc_hosts: localhost
runcmd:
  - &quot;curl --proto &#39;=https&#39; --tlsv1.2 -sSf -L https://install.determinate.systems/nix | sh -s -- install --no-confirm&quot;</code></pre>
<p>…this uses <a href="https://cloud-init.io/">cloud-init</a>, which declares some things we want set up in the VM.<br />
The <code>curl ... | sh</code> installs the <a href="https://github.com/DeterminateSystems/nix-installer">determinate-systems nix installer</a>.<br />
This means the VM will have <code>nix</code> available shortly after the VM launches. (Running the command <code>cloud-init status</code> on the launched VM shows whether cloud-init has finished).</p>
<p>Running the Terraform file involves (as is usual):</p>
<pre><code>terraform apply</code></pre>
<p>(and removing these resources with <code>terraform destroy</code>).</p>
<p>The public IP is an <code>output</code>, which allows SSH’ing into the VM with a command like:</p>
<pre><code>ssh debian@(terraform output -json public_ipv4 | jq -r)</code></pre>
<h3 id="building-the-nixos-image-for-openstack">Building the NixOS Image for OpenStack</h3>
<p>This is the <code>flake.nix</code> file. Below, some implementation notes, and the commands for building/uploading.</p>
<pre><code>{
  inputs = {
    nixos-generators = {
      url = &quot;github:nix-community/nixos-generators&quot;;
      inputs.nixpkgs.follows = &quot;nixpkgs&quot;;
    };
    nixpkgs.url = &quot;github:NixOS/nixpkgs/nixos-22.11&quot;;
    rgoulter.url = &quot;github:rgoulter/nix-user-repository&quot;;
  };

  outputs = {
    self,
    nixos-generators,
    nixpkgs,
    rgoulter,
    ...
  }: {
    packages.&quot;x86_64-linux&quot;.small-openstack = nixos-generators.nixosGenerate {
      pkgs = nixpkgs.legacyPackages.&quot;x86_64-linux&quot;;
      format = &quot;openstack&quot;;
      modules = [
        rgoulter.nixosModules.cloud-interactive
        rgoulter.nixosModules.ssh
        rgoulter.nixosModules.ssh-users
        rgoulter.nixosModules.tailscale
      ];
    };
  };
}</code></pre>
<p>Recall, a <code>flake.nix</code> file is more/less equivalent to a <code>package.json</code>/<code>Cargo.toml</code>/etc. project file,
and is a standard entry point into a Nix codebase.</p>
<p>Here, the OpenStack image is declared as a package, using <a href="https://github.com/nix-community/nixos-generators">nixos-generators</a>
and its <code>nixosGenerate</code> package. (The OpenStack specific part is the <code>format = "openstack";</code> attribute. As mentioned above, you can dig into the details in <code>nixos/</code>, which <code>nixos-generators</code> makes use of).</p>
<p>The <code>rgoulter.nixosModules</code> refers to the <a href="https://github.com/rgoulter/nix-user-repository/tree/95968968d32f7a6754978f099e975ca56b916977/modules">modules</a> in my <code>nix-user-repository</code>. (Though, you could just inline these all as one module in this <code>flake.nix</code> file, etc.).</p>
<p>e.g. cloud-interactive ensures that some CLI tools I like are installed:</p>
<pre><code>{
  config,
  lib,
  pkgs,
  ...
}: {
  environment.systemPackages = with pkgs; [
    direnv
    fd
    fish
    git
    helix
    jq
    ripgrep
    starship
    tmux
  ];
  nix = {
    extraOptions = &#39;&#39;
      experimental-features = nix-command flakes
    &#39;&#39;;
  };
  security.sudo.wheelNeedsPassword = false;
}</code></pre>
<p>and <code>ssh-users</code> declares the user I log in with:</p>
<pre><code>{
  config,
  lib,
  pkgs,
  ...
}:
{
  users.users.rgoulter = {
    isNormalUser = true;
    extraGroups = [
      &quot;wheel&quot;
    ];
    openssh.authorizedKeys.keys = [
      &quot;ssh-ed25519 AAAAC3NzaC1lZDI1NTE5AAAAIOmQ9/u9qV9Vvy2pbcPtGiAmIrhXdi/vY6IesJ5RYpS4&quot;
    ];
  };
}</code></pre>
<p>(This doesn’t necessarily need to be hard coded into the image; but, for this use case, doing it this way is simple).</p>
<p>With this <code>flake.nix</code>, on a Linux computer with <code>nix</code> installed (and flakes, nix-command enabled, as the determinate-systems does),
the image is built by running a command like:</p>
<pre><code>nix build .#small-openstack</code></pre>
<p>(A quick &amp; dirty approach is to just copy the <code>flake.nix</code> file to the Linux VM we’re running. But, it’d also be possible to have a <code>nixosGenerate</code> package in a <code>flake.nix</code> in a repository else &amp; refer to it using the appropriate flake URI).</p>
<p>The resulting file is linked to by <code>./result/nixos.qcow2</code>.</p>
<h3 id="uploading-the-image">Uploading the Image</h3>
<p>With the <code>openstack</code> client (use <code>nix shell nixpkgs#openstackclient</code> to make it available to the shell),
and appropriate openstack credentials (e.g. copying the openstack user RC file over and <code>source</code>’ing it),
the built image can be uploaded with:</p>
<pre><code>openstack image create \
  --private \
  --disk-format qcow2 \
  --container-format bare \
  --file ./result/nixos.qcow2 \
  my-nixos</code></pre>
<p>which creates the OpenStack image <code>my-nixos</code>.</p>
<h3 id="launching-a-vm-with-our-private-nixos-image">Launching a VM with Our Private NixOS Image</h3>
<p>This is straightforward, by re-using the code from “Using Terraform to Launch a VM”.</p>
<p>Simply change the <code>name</code> of the image in the <code>data.openstack_images_image_v2</code> block to <code>"my-nixos"</code>. (e.g. change the value of the Terraform variable <code>image_name</code>). – The NixOS image ignores the user data.</p>
<h3 id="switching-configuration-after-launch">Switching Configuration After Launch</h3>
<p>There are uses cases where it makes sense to ‘switch’ the NixOS configuration after the VM has launched.</p>
<p>There are plenty of options for doing this.</p>
<p>I liked using a command like:</p>
<pre><code>ssh -A &quot;rgoulter@${IP}&quot; -- &quot; \
  sudo sh -c &#39;mkdir -p ~/.ssh &amp;&amp; \
  chmod 700 ~/.ssh &amp;&amp; \
  ssh-keyscan github.com &gt;&gt; ~/.ssh/known_hosts &amp;&amp; \
  echo switch to ${FLAKE_URI} &amp;&amp; \
  nixos-rebuild switch --flake ${FLAKE_URI}&#39; \
&quot;</code></pre>
<p>I think another option instead of doing the <code>ssh-keyscan</code> here is to add it to
<a href="https://search.nixos.org/options?channel=23.05&amp;from=0&amp;size=50&amp;sort=relevance&amp;type=packages&amp;query=services.openssh.knownHosts">services.openssh.knownHosts</a>.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Two Kinds of Small Keyboards</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2023-08-29-two-kinds-of-small-keyboards.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2023-08-29-two-kinds-of-small-keyboards.html</id>
    <published>2023-08-29T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-08-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In an earlier post, <a href="../programming/2023-06-29-opinion-on-small-keyboards-and-big-spacebars.html">“Opinion on Small Keyboards and Big Spacebars”</a>,
I discussed the design flaws of traditional keyboards. – Mainly, traditional keyboards have big spacebars. Our thumbs are stronger than our pinky fingers, so it would be better to be able to use the thumbs more than the pinky fingers. A large spacebar results in the opposite: our thumbs only get to use one key, and our pinky fingers get used for all sorts of <em>frequently used</em> keys. The other flaws being that the traditional keyboard is asymmetrical, and has a row stagger, etc.</p>
<p>I neglected to explicitly describe the link between “big spacebar is stupid” and “small keyboards are good”.</p>
<p>It happens to be the case that most keyboards which fix those design problems of the traditional keyboard layout are small. – Although there are small keyboards which don’t fix the traditional keyboard layout’s design flaws.</p>
<p>So, I’d suggest this way of categorising (small) keyboards:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Traditional Keyboard Layouts</p>
<ul>
<li>Big Spacebar</li>
<li>Row-Stagger</li>
<li>Essentially the same as small keyboards on a laptop</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>Ergonomic Keyboard Layouts</p>
<ul>
<li>Many thumb keys</li>
<li>Ortholinear, Column Stagger (or similar)</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
<p>There is a third group, of non-traditional keyboards which are also not ergonomic; or with other design incoherencies. I don’t think these are good at all: if it’s got a traditional layout, it’s not good, but it’s <em>understandably</em> bad. (Traditional = retains familiar design elements). So, if a design isn’t traditional, it will take time to get used to; but, effort spent getting used to the keyboard doesn’t result in an ergonomic keyboard.</p>
<h2 id="techniques-of-small-keyboard-keymaps">Techniques of Small Keyboard Keymaps</h2>
<p>I distinguish “big spacebar =&gt; traditional” vs “many thumbkeys =&gt; ergonomic” small keyboards in part because of the techniques small keyboards use:</p>
<p>Small keyboards make use of techniques like “layers”, “tap-hold”, “chords”, etc.</p>
<p>Layers: Layers are a more general mechanism of the “Fn” key, something laptop users are familiar with. e.g. on Macbooks, there are a row of F-keys F1-F12; but these keys also have special functionality such as “screen dimmer / brighter”. By holding the Fn key, the key changes its functionality.<br />
The alternate functionality is considered a “layer” of a keymap; and a key like Fn will momentarily switch keys to use that “layer” of functionality.</p>
<p>Tap-Hold: The keys behaves one way when tapped, and behaves another way when held down. e.g. For programmers, I’ve seen some will change the CapsLock key to “Esc when tapped, Ctrl when held”; Ctrl is a useful key in many shortcuts, and Esc is a useful key in programs such as vim.<br />
Home Row Modifiers: Using Tap-Hold keys to put the modifier keys “Shift, Ctrl, Win, Alt” underneath the home row keys fdsa and jkl;.</p>
<p>Some keyboard layouts don’t allow the possibility of pressing keys like F1-F12, etc., even in layers.<br />
These keyboard layouts aren’t layouts which can be used for serious purposes.<br />
– Whereas, even a small keyboards, even those which lack a number row, will likely still allow users to enter numbers (on a layer).</p>
<p>Albeit, sure, a keyboard without a number row isn’t as easy to use for playing FPS games.</p>
<h2 id="why-thumb-keys-matter">Why Thumb Keys Matter</h2>
<p>Thumb keys make a keyboard more ergonomic for two reasons:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Thumb keys allow using keys with the thumb instead of the pinky fingers (e.g. it’s useful to put backspace, enter, tab, escape as well as space on thumb keys).</p></li>
<li><p>“Fn” keys on thumbs (especially with tap-hold, so the thumb key can be used for something else too) also avoids having to use the pinky fingers.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>Most “traditional” small keyboards I’ve seen have Fn keys which are clearly meant to be pushed using the pinky fingers.</p>
<p>Whereas, with ergonomic small keyboards, the thumbs get to be useful, and allow the pinky fingers to work less.</p>
<p>I’d say essentially the difference is:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>‘Traditional’ small keyboards use Fn keys because the keyboard <em>must</em> be smaller. (e.g. on laptops).</p></li>
<li><p>‘Ergonomic’ small keyboards are (often) small because they do not need
to be bigger; the full functionality of a standard keyboard is within
easy reach of the thumbs and fingers.</p></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="example-keymap">Example Keymap</h2>
<p>Here’s an example of a keymap for a small keyboard with several thumbkeys.</p>
<p><img src="../../images/small-keyboards/layout-ortho-4x12.jpg" /></p>
<p>To step through it a bit more slowly:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>The keymap retains many mnemonics / spacial similarities to traditional keyboards:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>The keys <code>0-9</code> (Well, <code>1-9, 0</code>) are available in the same column as on a standard keyboard, just brought a row down. (And not staggered).</p></li>
<li><p>The <code>~</code> key is still in the top-left.</p></li>
<li><p>The <code>-=</code> keys are adjacent to each other.</p></li>
<li><p><code>PrintScr</code>/<code>ScrollLock</code>/<code>PauseBrk</code> remain adjacent to each other.</p></li>
<li><p><code>Ins</code> is ‘above’ <code>Del</code>, in the same way the symbols are ‘above’ numbers.</p></li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>And some things I think are improvements:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>The <code>[]</code> keys have been brought closer to the middle of the keyboard;
but are on the same columns as <code>()</code>.</p></li>
<li><p><code>/\</code> are now adjacent to each other.</p></li>
<li><p>The cursor keys follow an ‘hjkl’ vim-style setup. The Home/PgDn/PgUp/End follows the same idiom, and is placed in the same columns.</p></li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>Symmetrical and reduced usage of pinky finger:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>The modifier keys (shift/ctrl/win/alt) are available in similar places to a traditional keyboard; but these don’t need to be used, since the keymap has home row modifiers.</p></li>
<li><p>Similarly: Backspace, Tab, Esc can be hit with the pinky fingers; but, it’s more convenient to use the thumbkeys provided for this.</p></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="gallery-of-examples">Gallery of Examples</h2>
<p>Applying the idea of “it’s good to use the thumbs more”/“it’s bad to use the pinky”, I think looking at some examples will help why I think it makes sense to categorise traditional (small) keyboard differently than the keyboards which offer several thumb keys.</p>
<h2 id="traditional-and-non-ergonomic">Traditional and non-Ergonomic</h2>
<p><img src="../../images/small-keyboards/apple.jpg" /></p>
<p>Apple’s keyboard.<br />
This is more/less like a Macbook keyboard.</p>
<p>Note that the Fn key is in the corner, so you’d have to use your pinky finger.</p>
<p>The thumbs pretty much only have the one big spacebar they can press, without moving the hands from home row.</p>
<p><img src="../../images/small-keyboards/pok3r.jpg" /></p>
<p>A Poker keyboard, which I understand to be the original ‘small’ mechanical keyboard. – The Fn key is in the corner, so you’d have to use your pinky finger to hold it.</p>
<p>The thumbs pretty much only have the one big spacebar they can press, without moving the hands from home row.</p>
<p><img src="../../images/small-keyboards/hhkb.jpg" /></p>
<p>A HHKB (“happy hacking keyboard”). – The Fn key is in the corner, so you’d have to use your pinky finger to hold it.</p>
<p>The thumbs pretty much only have the one big spacebar they can press, without moving the hands from home row.</p>
<p>I don’t think the hacker is going be all that happy given how much the keyboard requires using the pinky instead of the thumb.</p>
<p><img src="../../images/small-keyboards/daisy.jpg" /></p>
<p>A Daisy keyboard. – The Fn key is to the right of shift, so you’d have to use your pinky finger to hold it.</p>
<p>The thumbs pretty much only have the one big spacebar they can press, without moving the hands from home row.</p>
<p>– This keyboard lacks a number row. I’d describe “keyboards without a number row” as “<em>fashionably</em> small”. With two hands on the keyboard, you’re not missing much by going without a number row. (Although, a number row is more/less essential for playing FPS games). But, it’s trendy to have fewer keys.</p>
<p><img src="../../images/small-keyboards/vortex-core.jpg" /></p>
<p>The Vortex Core.</p>
<p>Here, the Fn/Pn keys are <em>almost</em> reachable by the thumb. But, I don’t get the impression the intention was for the thumbs to hit these keys.</p>
<p>Here the thumbs do actually get to hit one key <em>each</em>. – It’s not enough to cover all of “space/backspace/enter/etc.”, but it’s an improvement.</p>
<p><img src="../../images/small-keyboards/alice.jpg" /></p>
<p>The Alice.</p>
<p>I think the Alice keyboard layout is pretty bad.</p>
<p>It’s apparently different enough from a traditional keyboard layout that some people struggle typing on it. But, it’s also not an ergonomic keyboard layout.</p>
<p>e.g. the <code>6</code> key is not above the <code>y</code> key. It’s common to see people put the <code>b</code> key on the right hand side of the keyboard(!!!). It’s not symmetrical.</p>
<p>– Anyway.</p>
<p>The keyboard does offer maybe <em>three</em> whole keys shared between the two thumbs.</p>
<p>And (hard to tell from this picture, but) the Fn key is off in the corner. – The intention is to use the pinky finger for it.</p>
<h4 id="ortholinear">Ortholinear</h4>
<p><img src="../../images/small-keyboards/id75.jpg" /></p>
<p>The ID75. This is the same size as the Poker keyboard above.</p>
<p>I don’t know how many keys the Poker has, but this clearly has more.</p>
<p>For the thumbs, there are at least two to three for <em>each</em> thumb.</p>
<p>With that many thumb keys, it’s easy to see how this keyboard could have a good keymap like the example given above.</p>
<p>Here, the user has the alphabetical characters in a pseudo-split arrangement.</p>
<p><img src="../../images/small-keyboards/xd75.jpg" /></p>
<p>Another 5x15 Ortho. Here, the alphabetical characters are kept together. It’s an option.</p>
<p><img src="../../images/small-keyboards/boardsource-ortho4x12.jpg" /></p>
<p>For the thumbs, there are at least two to three for <em>each</em> thumb.</p>
<p>With that many thumb keys, it’s easy to see how this keyboard could have a good keymap like the example given above.</p>
<p><img src="../../images/small-keyboards/planck.jpg" /></p>
<p>The Planck, with a 2U spacebar.</p>
<p>So, it’s at least one or two keys for each thumb. But, the intention is clearly for the thumb to get used.</p>
<p><img src="../../images/small-keyboards/bm40-alt.jpg" /></p>
<p>Following the logic of “use the thumb more than the pinky fingers”, one option is to do the same ‘pseudo-split’ arrangement here.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>The pinky fingers don’t have to stretch to reach an outer column.</p></li>
<li><p>The thumbs get at least two to three keys each.</p></li>
</ul>
<h4 id="split-unrelated-to-traditional-vs-ergonomic">“Split”: Unrelated to “Traditional vs Ergonomic”</h4>
<p>For many, a split keyboard is a big ergonomic improvement over a non-split keyboard.</p>
<p>However, I’d still say that the keyboards fall under either “traditional” or “ergonomic” categories.</p>
<p><img src="../../images/small-keyboards/kineses-edge.jpg" /></p>
<p>This is clearly ‘just’ a traditional keyboard layout, but split.
(It’s only ‘small’ in the sense that there’s no numpad).</p>
<p>There are more thumb keys than a traditional keyboard only in the sense that each thumb now gets to press one key.</p>
<p><img src="../../images/small-keyboards/helix.jpg" /></p>
<p>Whereas with this Helix keyboard, the same remarks about the ortholinear keyboards apply here.</p>
<p>The thumb gets to use at least two to three keys each.</p>
<h4 id="column-staggered">Column-Staggered</h4>
<p>Most of what I dislike about row-staggered is that it’s asymmetrical. An ortholinear grid just makes more sense as a default.</p>
<p>Many ergonomic keyboards opt for a column stagger.</p>
<p><img src="../../images/small-keyboards/reviung41b.jpg" /></p>
<p>The Reviung 41.</p>
<p>Here, the thumbs can reach the same as the Planck with the 2U spacebar: one to two keys each.</p>
<p><img src="../../images/small-keyboards/kyria.jpg" /></p>
<p>The Kyria.</p>
<p>The thumbs can easily reach two or three keys each; but there are several more keys available to the thumb if the hand moves a bit.</p>
<p><img src="../../images/small-keyboards/ferris-sweep-bling.jpg" /></p>
<p>The Ferris Sweep.</p>
<p>I mostly see this keyboard associated with those who advocate for 34-key keyboards.</p>
<p>But, again. The keyboard clearly doesn’t rely on the pinky finger much. The keyboard gives each thumb two keys.</p>
<p><img src="../../images/small-keyboards/klor.jpg" /></p>
<p>The Klor.</p>
<p>I’m omitting the famous Corne/crkbd from these examples. Many keyboards look like variations of the crkbd.</p>
<p>The Klor is the most interesting keyboard I’ve come across in DIY, split column-staggered family of keyboards. (e.g. It splays its pinky column).</p>
<p>But the same observation applies to these: the thumbs get two-three keys each, and with five columns for the fingers, the pinky finger isn’t used so much.</p>
<h4 id="i-cant-understand-why-anyone-would-like-row-stagger">I Can’t Understand Why Anyone Would Like Row Stagger</h4>
<p>I’ve seen that some people prefer the look of the row-stagger keyboard.</p>
<p>I don’t mean those who only know the traditional layout and don’t want to learn ortho. – I mean people who have learned about symmetrical keyboards and still prefer the traditional row-stagger.</p>
<p>I can’t understand why.</p>
<p>I can almost understand someone considering this symmetrical:</p>
<p><img src="../../images/small-keyboards/row-stagger-1.png" /></p>
<p>But I can’t understand anyone who knows what human hands looks like thinking this layout makes sense:</p>
<p><img src="../../images/small-keyboards/row-stagger-2.png" /></p>
<p>Or to better illustrate, if you look at just the homing keys (f, j) and the keys above-inner and below-inner for the left hand side:</p>
<p><img src="../../images/small-keyboards/row-stagger-3.png" /></p>
<p>The distance between ‘jn’ is closer than on an ortholinear board; but the distance between ‘fb’ is <em>way</em> farther.</p>
<h4 id="key-takeaway-from-the-examples">Key Takeaway from the Examples</h4>
<p>Most of the traditional small keyboards really only allowed the thumbs to use one or two keys total, whereas the ergonomic ones allowed at least two thumb keys each.</p>
<p>Most of the traditional small keyboards made strong use of the pinky finger, whereas many of the ergonomic keyboards lacked an extra outer column for the pinky fingers to use.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Re-watching James Bond</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/narrative/2023-08-14-rewatching-james-bond.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/narrative/2023-08-14-rewatching-james-bond.html</id>
    <published>2023-08-14T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-08-14T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been watching through the James Bond films with my wife.
I’d seen the films many years ago, whereas this is my wife’s first watch through.</p>
<p>Overall I’m getting a similar sense to what I got when I watched through Columbo with my wife: The lingering taste and cultural impact of these shows is the formula of these at their best.<br />
With Columbo, the formula involved this bumbling-detective increasingly annoying the bad guy until a ‘gotcha’, but I felt the show never quite manages to settle on a perfect execution. Each kindof meanders and experiments, not quite sure how to best fill its runtime.<br />
With Bond, it seems like most of the formula is settled after a few tries.</p>
<p>At the time of writing, it feels like James Bond hasn’t had such a good run these last couple of decades. With three new films in the fourteen years since 2009 (or four films in fifteen years, I guess) feels infrequent. – Albeit, Mission Impossible is a similarly slow pace; there are too many Fast and the Furious movies. John Wick did a good job getting its four films out from in the nine years from 2014 to 2023, although was probably too rushed by the end.</p>
<p>I think one thing which seems striking about James Bond is that the character seems defined by his actor, where it’s always the same character in the present day. I find it difficult to think of other media which have quite the same scheme. Superhero movies have the same-character-different-actor.</p>
<h2 id="dr-no">Dr No</h2>
<p>In this one, James Bond goes to Jamaica to investigate why MI6 has lost contact with its agents there. Tracking down clues leads him to a nearby off-limits island, where he is captured and brought into the villain’s lair. Then he escapes and saves the day.</p>
<p>This one’s relatively straightforward, but its still easy to see how many of the films elements get picked up into this stereotype of suave playboy secret agent.<br />
You still get action scenes involving fist fighting, gunfights, car chases; the location is exotic; the villain has a dastardly plan, a fantastic secret lair, and works for an evil secret organisation; there are fancy clothes, and beautiful women.</p>
<p>In this, somewhat more than the others, James Bond is a total babe magnet. Like catnip for beautiful women. (Charming a woman at the casino, who then sneaks into his hotel room; charming a professor’s secretary, who tries to lure him into a trap (which he defeats, and then sleeps with her); and of course, with the famous Ryder woman by the end of the movie).<br />
I think in later movies, Bond’s screwing around is rearranged to only at the start and at the end. Probably helps keep the story flow along better that way.</p>
<p>One thing which strikes me (perhaps as underdeveloped?) from this movie is the local guide mentions there’s a dragon on the island. When they visit the island, Ryder confirms she’s heard of the dragon too, somehow. Then they venture further into the island, they see the dragon, and quickly see that it’s just an armoured vehice with flame throwers. – I feel there wasn’t much tension built up by this; and what tension there was gets collapsed pretty quickly once it’s revealed the dragon is just a tank. I mean, the scene where they see the tank would feel pretty much the same if there’d been no previous mention of a dragon.</p>
<h2 id="from-russia-with-love">From Russia with Love</h2>
<p>This time, to Turkey. The evil organisation have a plan to lure Bond into a trap to kill him, by way of a beautiful defecting Russian clerk. So the adventure involves Bond going to Turkey and escaping the trap.</p>
<p>This movie introduces fantasy covert gadgets and the badass henchman to the formula; and we get to see more of this evil organisation.</p>
<p>Despite the fancy gadgetry and the stronger-than-bond henchman, this movie lacks a save-the-world urgency. There’s no supervillain with an underground lair that Bond has to infiltrate to thwart. – It essentially feels relatively grounded.</p>
<h2 id="goldfinger">Goldfinger</h2>
<p>It seems clear that there must have been many clones and imitations of James Bond following Dr No. – Because in Goldfinger, much of the story “subverts expectations”. Bond hardly even saves the day in this one!</p>
<p>But, damn, I feel this is distinctive than the other ones.</p>
<p>I did remember the gist of the plot. The Goldfinger villain wanted to make his gold worth much more by nuking the US gold supply in Fort Knox.</p>
<p>What I didn’t remember was that Bond spends the majority of the film captured. (He manages to escape once or twice, but is captured again).<br />
Though we do get the very famous “no, Mr Bond, I expect you to die!” from Goldfinger, this inevitably leads to the trope of “villain keeps hero alive (for no good reason)”.</p>
<p>Bonds main tangible contribution to saving the world in this is that he manages to defeat the terrifying henchman Oddjob.</p>
<p>Bond not saving the world himself (and all his plans failing) does very much ‘subvert my expectations’.<br />
I gotta wonder why it works here, and doesn’t work so well for media these days.<br />
I think part of it is that there are a couple of prominent cases where this ‘subverting expectations’ ends up making fun of the legacy characters. Although Bond rarely succeeds in Goldfinger, he’s not the butt of jokes.<br />
Another part is the focus seems to be on the Goldfinger villain being a compelling villain. Our expectations are subverted here, too. We significantly expect he plans to steal the gold from Fort Knox.</p>
<p>The majority of the world-saving is done by the henchwoman with a really stupid name. (Austin Powers parodies it as “Alotta Vagina”).<br />
She’s just as tough as Bond, and can hold her own in a fight with him.<br />
– She changes her mind and decides to save America, due to the power of James Bond’s penis, after he forces himself on her. … Ehhhh.</p>
<p>On the other hand, Bond’s disregard for other people is shown in a scene at the start where, as he’s kissing a woman he’s ambushed by some bad guy; Bond quickly spins around and uses this lover as a human shield to take most of the blow! Ooof. I thought it was pretty funny.</p>
<p>All that aside, this one is a lot of fun.</p>
<h2 id="thunderball">Thunderball</h2>
<p>This time, Bond travels to Nassau. The bad guys have managed to steal two nuclear bombs, and they threaten to use them. Bond figures out who the bad guy is, tracks down the bombs, and guides the paratrooping divers to the right place in order to stop the bombs.</p>
<p>It’s laaaaaaame.<br />
So, so lame.</p>
<p>The big pre-climactic fight takes place underwater.<br />
But no one thinks Aquaman is as cool as Batman or Superman.</p>
<p>A couple of lines of dialogue explain James Bonds sexuality in the movie a bit more.<br />
I tend to think most commentary which says anything like “those were different times” is part of the “no fun allowed” camp, which would rather remove things than add things.<br />
Still, in this movie at the start, Bond is sexually harassing the nurse who is treating him. She rebukes him with the same tone of voice you’d use when someone’s trying to eat their dessert before they’ve eaten their vegetables. Later, Bond has sex with a villainess. When she betrays him, she mocks the idea that having sex with him was supposed to convert her to his side. (Which, I guess has been part of the plot of one or two of the previous movies). And after Bond has sex with the Bond girl and he asks something of her, she sighs and says “oh, you only wanted to have sex with me because you want me to do something”.<br />
– So… while I think the sex scenes would be improved if the non-consent was replaced with more explicit consent, James Bond’s penis is still otherwise treated as superhuman catnip.</p>
<h2 id="you-only-live-twice">You Only Live Twice</h2>
<p>Japan! Secret evil villain lair in a volcano! Stopping a war between the US and the USSR!</p>
<p>I vaguely remember watching parts of this. I remember that Bond wondered whether the secret agent he contacts is actually an enemy secret agent.</p>
<p>Perhaps the other movies had a foot in the door with regards to being grounded. This one’s firmly over the top.<br />
The starting sequence has Bond killed (again betrayed while with a lover… this just keeps happening to him, huh); there’s a funeral, his body is dumped into the ocean; but this is shown to be a ruse as he’s brought aboard a submarine.<br />
Later in Japan, he’s given a bath, where he’s bathed by several scantily clad beautiful women.<br />
Bond goes to investigate the forbidden-to-visit island with his conveniently-dressed-in-a-bikini side kick. The latter is eventually able to send for reinforcements, and so we get an iconic battle between a bunch of Japanese ninjas and an army of evil henchmen in a secret volcano lair.</p>
<h2 id="evaluating-these-ones-so-far">Evaluating These Ones So Far</h2>
<p>I’d say Thunderball lacks the most.<br />
Or, rather, what Goldfinger has that the others (mostly) lack is an escalating tension where you feel something bad will happen if Bond doesn’t save the day in time.<br />
In Goldfinger, we see quite clearly what Goldfinger will do and when.<br />
Whereas, in the others, there’s a sense that maybe something bad could happen at some point, but the tension isn’t made clear. This might make thematic sense in terms of the looming threat of nuclear war as part of the cold war; or how espionage is a game of hidden information… but, story-wise, it’s hard to feel tension if the threat is not known.</p>
<p>So, I’d say Goldfinger is the best so far.</p>
<p>They’re all pretty good films. But, again, it still doesn’t feel like the full James Bond formula has been settled on by this point; so it feels like each has its share of good parts, but also a share of uninteresting fluff.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>The Barbie Movie is Silly Fun</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/narrative/2023-08-01-the-barbie-movie-is-silly-fun.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/narrative/2023-08-01-the-barbie-movie-is-silly-fun.html</id>
    <published>2023-08-01T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-08-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I went to go see the Barbie movie when I was visiting Malaysia with my wife.</p>
<p>We wouldn’t have been able to see the movie in cinemas in Vietnam.</p>
<h2 id="nine-dash-line">Nine Dash Line</h2>
<p>It’s banned in Vietnam because, in one scene where a childlike depicition of a world map is shown,
China’s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nine-dash_line">nine dash line</a> is represented.
<a href="https://maritime-executive.com/index.php/article/vietnam-bans-barbie-movie-over-depiction-of-chinese-maritime-claims">maritime-executive</a> has an article with a screencap of the map.</p>
<p>In that Wikipedia article, Warner Bros’ defense is that the lines have no intended meaning.</p>
<p>I’m not sure why the dashes would need to be on the map. If they really are meaningless, and come across as offensive to some market, then surely it’s worth more money to quickly edit out the lines. (The maritime-executive link also provides a couple of examples: movies have been banned from Vietnam before for showing the nine-dash line; and Top Gun: Maverick was going to remove the Taiwanese and Japanese flags from Maverick’s jacket until the US military frowned upon that. With these examples in mind, it <em>really</em> looks like the Barbie movie map is pushing it). – I find it hard to read Warner Bros’ response as sincere.</p>
<h2 id="the-movie-and-its-plot">The Movie and Its Plot</h2>
<p>That aside, I did generally enjoy the movie.</p>
<p>I wouldn’t say it’s a <em>great</em> movie. The plot is passable. The sincere-moral-messaging of the movie is pretty ‘eh’. I enjoyed many of the films jokes. – I’d say what brought many to the theatre was the idea of getting to have fun by wearing something pink.</p>
<p>The story involves Barbie visiting the real world to find out why she’s been having negative thoughts. Ken goes with her, sees that men hold important positions in the real world, and imports this idea of Partriarchy (tm) back to Barbieland. Barbie then has to rescue Barbieland &amp; restore the status quo. – There’s also a subplot where Ken has unrequited feelings for Barbie.</p>
<p>Ryan Gosling as this silly, air-headed, juvenile villain Ken is delightful to watch.</p>
<p>A point I thought was quite astute pointed out that the film is quite like Pinocchio: an animated doll wants to become a real human, starts off in innocence, and needs to learn the moral lessons as to what that means.</p>
<h2 id="the-movie-and-the-discussion-around-its-gender-politics">The Movie and the Discussion Around its Gender Politics</h2>
<p>Much of the discussion online that I saw about the Barbie movie was focused on the gender-politics commentary of the movie. I saw opinions from “eww, gross, feminism” to “of course a Barbie movie would talk about gender politics, you dweebs”.</p>
<p>I do agree with “it’s a silly movie; you ought to be able to just ignore the dumb parts and enjoy the fun parts”.</p>
<p>But it also does make sense to me that there are people who are upset at the film’s gender-politics stuff, see the movie’s messaging as less than ideal, and try to discuss all sorts of “gotchas” about the film.</p>
<p>It makes sense to me that people have strong feelings on gender politics; and I think I’d rather people had a good foundation or set of tools with which to discuss their views. – Indeed, that’s one of the things I love about <a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLf9ZVzFaBzHkEmkTeJGwmp7XkMJW6ZSU5">Liana Kerzner’s Lady Bits series</a>. Kerzner is intelligent and articulate, and does a fantastic job at communicating feminist concepts and how they apply to videogames.</p>
<p>In any case, considering “the Barbie movie’s gender politics is silly”, I’m reminded of <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=t3zNCg55kiw">a joke in Yes, Minister about the six diplomatic options</a>. (“We could do nothing, which implies we agree; we could protest, but they’ll ignore us; we can’t withdraw support, because we’re not providing any; if we went to war with them, it might look like we’re overreacting”). – So even though you can say the Barbie movie is silly and dumb, it is annoying if in <em>every</em> insignificant case things go against you.</p>
<p>I think a lot of the upset is around how Barbieland isn’t what anyone would think of as an egalitarian utopia. Barbieland has women all holding high status jobs, and all the men standing around doing nothing. I’d guess a thesis/antithesis/sythesis going from “girls rule”/“boyz rule”/“50-50” would be more conventional. – Or I think many are upset that the film seems to take more jabs (with more sincerity) at men than it does at women.</p>
<h2 id="okay-but-about">Okay, But About…</h2>
<p>I will say it does seem like Ken gets to have a lot more fun in the Barbie movie than Barbie does. – In the movie, Barbie’s motivation is having experienced imperfect thoughts; and the movie discusses that of course it’s tough to live up to a standard of perfection and that it’s fine for people to be ordinary. Whereas Ken visits the real world, feels very proud someone respected him enough to ask him for the time, and believes in a utopic vision which involves men and horses ruling the world. Barbie spends the climax of the movie enacting strategic espionage, whereas Ken spends the climax of the movie in a Grease-themed dance off.</p>
<p>I was surprised by the lines of dialogue from the young college student. She’s not a fan of Barbie, and says abrasive things like “but Barbie’s main purpose is to make money” (which sounds like a coherent thing to argue), or “Barbie is fascist” (…which does not). No one in the film ever really disagrees with her, which just feels weird to me. – Although, I’ve also heard this character is a director’s insert for someone speaking truth to power…?</p>
<p>There’s a line early on in the movie where, when Barbie’s feet transform to human-shaped feet rather than angled-for-high-heels, Barbie says “I’d never wear high heels if my feet were shaped like this”. – I guess it’s a throwaway joke, sure, but it does feel like “girls stuff is dumb”.</p>
<p>And in a similar vein to “girls stuff is dumb”… in Gerwig’s “Little Women” film, the film seems to mock the idea of giving a story a happy ending, or that for a ending to be ‘happy’ the woman has to find a romantic partner.<br />
Surely it <em>is</em> fine for a story about a woman to end without her finding a partner; and surely it is also fine if the story ends with her finding a partner.<br />
I get the impression that there’s animosity towards the latter from the sense that there’s an overwhelming default expectation for the former? (And vice versa!). I don’t generally get the sense that society would only respect a female character if she ends up married.<br />
The Barbie movie ends without Barbie and Ken having a romantic relationship. For Barbie, there’s no romance in the film; for Ken, it’s unrequited attention, and he doesn’t end up with a partner.<br />
Romantic plotlines which don’t end up with a happy ending are kindof a bummer.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>So I Played Some Battlebit Remastered</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/games/2023-07-20-so-i-played-some-battlebit-remastered.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/games/2023-07-20-so-i-played-some-battlebit-remastered.html</id>
    <published>2023-07-20T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-07-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>“Battlebit Remastered” is trending on YouTube at the moment.</p>
<p>At a glance, it has low-poly graphics, and is touted to have a lot of the charm that older Battlefield games had. (Maybe a lot of that is just nostalgia?).</p>
<p>I don’t tend to play multiplayer games. I did watch a video that pointed out the game had voice-chat enabled, a feature which relies on trusting the community to not be full of assholes; and puts it in contrast to high-budget multiplayer games where the playerbase is restricted from even using text chat.</p>
<p>So, it sounded friendly enough to try out.</p>
<p>I played it quite a bit.<br />
I found the players are mostly friendly.<br />
The gameplay was mostly pretty fun.<br />
But, overall, I’m not inclined to think I’m missing out on tonnes of fun by only playing single player games.</p>
<h3 id="games-are-fun-when-theyre-competitive">Games Are Fun When They’re Competitive</h3>
<p>I do play chess online against others.<br />
Chess.com and lichess both allow chat; most games won’t result in a chat. The most common interaction is “good game” (which is often more polite than sincere), sometimes people get a bit rude, and very rarely will someone compliment.</p>
<p>But, since in chess there’s only one person in control of the moves, then chess is ultimately quite personal. Winning is good, losing sucks; but one of the better feelings is reaching a stalemate position when you’re in a completely losing position. – In one game, my opponent had taken all of my pieces, had my king trapped on the side of the board, had three queens on the board, and wanted to gloat by promoting the rest of his queens; fortunately for me, he made the one move which led to a stalemate.</p>
<p>One of the things that’s fun about that, with so many people playing chess online, it’s easy to have a game with someone who has about the same skill level as you.</p>
<p>With Battlebit.. I’m not very good at it. My experience was that “I saw the enemy, and we both shot at each other” happened 5% of the time. For the rest, I’d either get shot by a sniper some distance away (fair, I guess?, since these can often be avoided), or I’d get shot 0.1 seconds after seeing the enemy.</p>
<p>Perhaps there were times where I was the guy the enemy saw for only 0.1s before dying; but I ended up doing a lot more dying than shooting.</p>
<p>But my point is: if I were playing with people who sucked just as much as I did, I think it’d be more fun.</p>
<p>I guess having balanced teams is supposed to have the same effect. Coursely, it does.. in that whether a game is ‘won’ or ‘lost’ will be closer with a balanced team. – One of the least fun matches I played in ended up with one side completely dominating the other side, such that the losing side couldn’t make any progress beyond the spawn point.</p>
<p>At the individual level, there are roles to play other than shooting enemies up close (or from a distance). It’s reasonably fun to play the medic in Battlebit; being able to heal others and revive them if they’re shot.</p>
<p>I wonder about other solutions for making the game fun for people who suck at it (without depriving the fun for those who are good at it). – I’d heard that TitanFall 2’s multiplayer includes a bunch of weak bots in the game, which sounds like it would allow for players like me to have some gratification from helping out by killing those bots.</p>
<h3 id="social-good-and-the-bad">Social: Good and the Bad</h3>
<p>I liked Zero Punctuation’s reply to “playing games with other people is more fun” with “watching paint dry is more fun with other people”.</p>
<p>I think some of the most fun while playing Battlebit was the random messing around in the peaceful pre-match preparation period. It was also fun when people goofed around in character when attacking an enemy’s defense.</p>
<p>Less-fun was people expressing their frustration about how they thought their teammates suck. (It’s a casual game; chill out).</p>
<p>There were also accusations of cheating.. and, eh… idk. – With chess, it’s easier to tell if someone’s cheating, because you can look through the game and see if the moves are moves a human would make. But generally, accusing others of cheating makes you look butthurt about losing.</p>
<p>Overall, I felt a lot of the gameplay involved following your squad or your team up until you encountered the enemy, and then either keeping the enemy back or following on whoever made a successful push.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Opinion on Small Keyboards and Big Spacebars</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2023-06-29-opinion-on-small-keyboards-and-big-spacebars.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2023-06-29-opinion-on-small-keyboards-and-big-spacebars.html</id>
    <published>2023-06-29T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-06-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The mechanical keyboard hobby pretty much exploded in popularity during the pandemic.</p>
<p>“Mechanical keyboards” generally brings to mind the loud, clicky switches;
or perhaps people who have spent a lot of time (and often money) in order
to get a keyboard that feels nice.</p>
<p>But, there’s a niche part of the hobby which is passionate about
playing around with more exotic keyboard designs.</p>
<p>Rather. The mechanical keyboard switches allow for manufacturing
low volumes of keyboards which improve upon the standard keyboard design.</p>
<p>The standard keyboard design suffers several problems,
which make the keyboard less than efficient:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>The keyboard’s spacebar is impractically big.</p></li>
<li><p>The hands have to be close together, rather than at more natural distances apart.</p></li>
<li><p>It’s asymmetrical.</p></li>
<li><p>The rows are staggered (again, asymmetrically).</p></li>
<li><p>There are keys of different sizes.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>For myself, although I can understand spending more money to get a ‘nicer feeling keyboard’,
I cannot understand why anyone would pay luxury prices for
keyboards which still suffer these problems.</p>
<p>(“Cheap Logitech keyboard” gets to answer these by way of: this is what keyboards have always been
and what people are used to. With economies of scale, you get to have a very cheap keyboard).</p>
<p>But to explain why I think each of the above is a design flaw,
and how custom mechanical keyboards tend to improve on these:</p>
<h3 id="design-flaw-the-spacebar-is-impractically-big">Design Flaw: The Spacebar is Impractically Big</h3>
<p>The spacebar is impractically big. It’s often 6 times as large as the normal keys.</p>
<p>Or to put it another way: our thumbs are much stronger than our pinkies.
But on a standard keyboard, our thumbs pretty much only get to use the spacebar, and the pinkies
tend to get used frequently for all sorts of important keys (such as backspace, shift, enter, etc.).</p>
<p>There’s no good reason for the spacebar to be that big: although not everyone presses the spacebar in the same place,
everyone will tend to push the spacebar consistently in the same place they press it.
(As opposed to using the full with of the spacebar).</p>
<p>It would be better to replace the wide spacebar with a key that’s as wide as the standard keys;
this would allow putting another 5 keys in the same space. – It wouldn’t matter what those keys did;
anything would be a big improvement.</p>
<h5 id="multiple-thumb-keys-hugely-increase-what-your-hands-can-do-without-moving">Multiple Thumb Keys Hugely Increase What Your Hands Can Do Without Moving</h5>
<p>The term “home row” refers to the row of keys where your hand rests when it’s not typing.
The ‘F’ and ‘J’ keys have bumps on them which allow your hands to find their place,
without you having to look for them.</p>
<p>If instead of one big spacebar, there were 6 individual keys, then your thumbs would be able to
use 2-3 keys each.</p>
<p>e.g. I like using these for Space, Backspace, Enter, Esc, Tab, Del. (As a developer, I use the Esc key frequently).</p>
<p>Whereas, with the spacebar being so big, in order to hit those keys, you’d have to either
stretch your pinky, or move your hand from home row.</p>
<h5 id="thumb-keys-are-great-layer-keys">Thumb Keys are Great Layer Keys</h5>
<p>“Layers” allow for re-using a key for multiple purposes.</p>
<p>This idea is extremely common on laptop keyboards: there’s often a “Fn” key,
and the keys will indicate what functionality they have if pressed when the Fn key is held.
e.g. “Volume Up” / “Volume Down” might not have their own keys, but might be available
when a Fn key is pressed.</p>
<p>That’s an example of using keymap layers.</p>
<p>From a pessimistic perspective, it’s a technique used by small keyboards to cope with not having so many keys.</p>
<p>From an optimistic perspective, it allows more functionality without having to have more keys.</p>
<p>Thumb keys are excellent keys to use for as “Fn” keys for layers.</p>
<h3 id="aside-dual-use-keys-are-neat">Aside: Dual-Use Keys are Neat</h3>
<p>One idea in the keyboard space which is useful for really getting
the most out of a keyboard is “key behaves like T when tapped, like H when held down”.</p>
<p>It’s relatively common for programmers to come across this good idea:
When using Vim, programmers want to tap Esc all the time;
when using MacOS, programmers want to hold Ctrl all the time. Programmers pretty much
don’t want to use CapsLock. (Not that frequently, anyway).<br />
So, solution: use the CapsLock key as an Esc key when it’s tapped, but have it act as a Ctrl key when it’s held down.</p>
<p>Above, I was pointing out that the weak-pinky finger gets used for Shift, Ctrl, Win, Alt keys.. one neat idea to
alleviate that is to put these modifier keys underneath the F,D,S,A keys (and J,K,L,; keys) using this dual-use
tap-hold functionality. – This technique is known as “home row modifiers”, or “home row mods”; since it allows
using the modifier keys without having to leave home row.</p>
<p>Similarly. Above I argue that thumb keys are well placed for backspace, and are well placed
for use with layers. Indeed, I think having these as dual use is a good idea, too.</p>
<h3 id="design-flaw-the-hands-are-too-close-together">Design Flaw: The Hands are Too Close Together</h3>
<p>While this is (to an extent) unavoidable with small devices like laptops,
what I mean is that for desktops, keyboards can be in “split” halves.</p>
<p>This allows positioning each half of the keyboard so that the hands can rest
at a more natural distance.</p>
<p>I’ve seen for many people, this is a significant improvement. I’m not as won over.</p>
<p>I also see there are many keyboards which are “split”, but retain
all the other design flaws mentioned above.</p>
<p>Anyway. Split keyboard designs are quite popular amongst the niche
of mechanical keyboard enthusiasts that prefer exotic designs.</p>
<h3 id="design-flaw-the-keyboard-is-asymmetrical">Design Flaw: The Keyboard is Asymmetrical</h3>
<p>The standard keyboard is asymmetrically laid out.
With the hands resting on home row, there are far more keys to the right than to the left.
That’s particularly strange, given that most people use a mouse to the right of the keyboard.</p>
<p>Even laptop keyboards suffer the same. – Worse, it’s easy to come across
laptop keyboards which don’t have all four modifier keys (Shift, Ctrl, Win, Alt)
on the right hand side.</p>
<p>At a glance, it might look like the key map is symmetrical; but, the asymmetry
is clear when considering that “Q” is the left hand pinky’s, and has one key to its left;
whereas “P” is the right hand pinky’s, and has 3-4 to its right.</p>
<p>To me, it doesn’t make sense why you’d introduce that asymmetry. – Why add keys to one side,
but not to the other?</p>
<h3 id="design-flaw-the-key-rows-are-staggered">Design Flaw: The Key Rows Are Staggered</h3>
<p>This somewhat goes hand in hand with the above point.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://golem.hu/board/Katana60-202.html">Katana60</a> one of one a <em>very few</em> keyboards
I’m aware of that are symmetrical while retaining the row stagger. (It aims to use
keys from a standard keyset; so, I guess I’ll give it that).</p>
<p>Most of what I dislike about row stagger could be blamed on asymmetry:
it hardly makes sense for the left hand’s keys to “slant left” with the same slant
that the right hand has. – I mean, “R” relative to “F” is the same as “U” relative to “J”; but,
the slants should be <em>mirrored</em>.</p>
<p>What does seem more sensible is either to lay the keys out in a grid, or to stagger the columns.
(I’ve also seen keys “splayed” out).</p>
<p>The grid arrangement is called “ortholinear”. (Despite that “ortho” and “linear” both mean ‘straight’ in Greek, Latin).</p>
<p>Staggering the columns means that each column of keys is straight, but each column is staggered compared to the one
next to it.</p>
<p>These all try and deal with how the fingers reach the keys on a flat keyboard.
Perhaps something like a Maltron or a Dactyl Manuform are much better than either of these.<br />
– For flat keyboards, I’m willing to compromise.</p>
<p>95% of what makes a row stagger bad is the asymmetry. But, my intuition is still
that there are good reasons row stagger is much rarer once breaking from the traditional shape.</p>
<h3 id="design-flaw-the-keys-are-different-sizes">Design Flaw: The Keys are Different Sizes</h3>
<p>This is arguably a consequence of the above design flaws.</p>
<p>But I’m also not sure why you’d design keyboards where the keys had different sizes?</p>
<p>Rather.</p>
<p>One consequence of keys having different sizes is that keycap sets
may not be compatible with every keyboard.</p>
<p>This affects the exotic keyboards I like, which only have space for “1U” keys.</p>
<p>But I see that keycap sets will often have the same modifier keys
in an additional two or three different sizes. – It seems wasteful and silly;
or it would, if all keys were “1U” big all the time.</p>
<h3 id="aside-comfort-is-the-main-goal-not-speed">Aside: Comfort is the Main Goal, Not Speed</h3>
<p>I think the most common reaction people have in discussions about
alternative keyboard stuff like ergonomic layouts, or the Dvorak layout,
is asking whether such alternatives are faster.</p>
<p>Perhaps the thought process is: “I’m fine with my keyboard as-is; but, sure,
if I could type faster then it would be worth putting in effort to learn a new thing”.</p>
<p>The most common comment I do see from people who have used these
alternative methods (different keyboard layout, etc.) is that they are
much more comfortable.</p>
<p>And regarding the above discussion about improving on the design flaws of
the standard keyboard, the improvements are all about being able to do
more with your hands without having to leave home row.</p>
<h3 id="keyboard-recommendations">Keyboard Recommendations</h3>
<p>So what would I recommend to those who are looking for a keyboard which doesn’t suffer these flaws?</p>
<p>For desktop use, a good default recommendation is <a href="https://www.zsa.io/moonlander/">ZSA’s Moonlander</a>.</p>
<p>If you’re rarely using mouse + keyboard work (e.g. the bulk of your work is typing,
and doesn’t require rapidly entering digits while using the mouse, such as a FPS shooter game would),
then a keyboard like <a href="https://www.zsa.io/planck/">ZSA’s Planck EZ</a> is hard to beat.</p>
<p>Those are quite expensive. For a lower cost option from AliExpress, the <a href="https://www.aliexpress.com/item/1005004568409963.html">Idobao ID75</a>
looks compelling. It fits in a GH60-sized case (which are easy to find), and like (I think) the above it’s got a powerful ARM MCU, hotswap (so no need to solder), and the fancy per-key RGB and RGB underglow.</p>
<p>For the smaller planck-size, previously I’ve used and recommended the BM40 keyboard. It’s still … okay. The main drawback to the BM40 is that its MCU is the weaker ATMega32U4. It’s powerful enough for a decently sophisticated keymap; but you’ll not really be able to push the keyboard to its full potential.</p>
<p>Albeit, I don’t use any of these since I got deep enough into the rabbit hole of mechanical keyboards
to make my own DIY designs. I share these designs <a href="https://github.com/rgoulter/keyboard-labs">in this GitHub repository</a>.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Nix Remains Useful for Side Projects</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2023-06-18-nix-remains-useful-for-side-projects.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2023-06-18-nix-remains-useful-for-side-projects.html</id>
    <published>2023-06-18T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-06-18T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="nixos.org/">Nix</a> is a sophisticated package manager.</p>
<p>Nix has a steep learning curve; but those who do take the time to learn it are
often enthusiastic about its benefits.</p>
<p>The trade off with Nix is this: you put in effort up front to declaratively
describe your software, and then you reap the benefits, such as being able to
reproduce the same toolchain setup effortlessly.</p>
<p>One use case I’ve found this useful for has been side projects which I work with infrequently.<br />
Comparing the typical workflow vs the nix workflow of “returning to a
sideproject after months/years”:</p>
<h1 id="typical-workflow-when-returning-to-sideprojects">Typical Workflow When Returning to Sideprojects</h1>
<p>e.g. The static site generator for my blog uses Haskell.</p>
<p>So, when I write it, and then return to writing it months/years later, typically
some effort to tinkering on it would be getting the system set up again.</p>
<p>If the system package manager (e.g. <code>apt</code> or <code>pacman</code>) doesn’t have the old
version of the compiler, then I’d have to build the old code with the new
compiler. Likely this left me in the situation where the code was too old to
compile; so the project is in a state where I don’t have a working version of
it.</p>
<h1 id="workflow-with-nix-when-returning-to-sideprojects">Workflow with Nix When Returning to Sideprojects</h1>
<p>It’s boring. It works.</p>
<p>With Nix, you can ensure that you’ll end up with the same (old) compiler &amp;
libraries which you knew worked previously.</p>
<p>The hard part of working with Nix is more likely to be getting it set up so it
works.</p>
<p>I recently updated the version of the Haskell compiler which my site’s static
site generator uses.</p>
<p>It pretty much just worked.</p>
<p>The only thing that didn’t work: the Nixpkgs provides several versions of the
GHC compiler, and a large set of Haskell packages, but only tests the packages
with the current version of the GHC compiler. When I tried newer versions of the
compiler than was tested to work, for some reason these didn’t work. – This
isn’t really a big deal for my use case; I’m fine with using the current GHC
version.</p>
<h1 id="effort-involved-in-setting-up-nix">Effort Involved in Setting Up Nix</h1>
<p>It’s easier to get something to build on your machine, than it is to
build/distribute software.<br />
And it’s easier to use Nix to get a working development environment than to use
Nix to describe a package.</p>
<p>It somewhat overstates it to say “writing a package with Nix is hard”. It can be
very simple, but it may be very difficult.</p>
<p>I used the approach described in the <a href="https://nixos.org/manual/nixpkgs/stable/#haskell">nixpkgs manual about its haskell
support</a>. There’s a nice
<a href="https://nixos.wiki/wiki/Haskell">NixOS Wiki page for Haskell</a> which also
describes different ways of using Nix.</p>
<p>Here’s <a href="https://github.com/rgoulter/my-hakyll-blog/blob/44c1507cd3cc249d00f89e5fc83fdd81ef645cd4/my-hakyll-blog.nix">a link to my current Nix package for my hakyll static site
generator</a>.</p>
<p>I don’t recall significant pain in setting that up; although I was learning Nix
while doing this. e.g. <a href="https://github.com/rgoulter/my-hakyll-blog/commit/42004c09c941c3f7818ecb5e4103ab1726918399">here’s the commit where I upgraded from a shell.nix to a
default.nix</a>,
<a href="https://github.com/rgoulter/my-hakyll-blog/commit/8dbd2aebb6648d5677636290f7e34775c814e617">added
flake.nix</a>,
<a href="https://github.com/rgoulter/my-hakyll-blog/commit/7576644e8623654c8222349945be3fa63b941932">upgraded from GHC 8.4.3 to
9.0.2</a>.</p>
<p>Looking at the <code>my-hakyll-blog.nix</code> file, I don’t love that it duplicates the
list of packages from the <code>.cabal</code> file. But, it does work, and I haven’t needed
to change it.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>XCOM2 WOTC Added Some Good Parts</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/games/2023-05-29-xcom2-wotc-added-some-good-parts.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/games/2023-05-29-xcom2-wotc-added-some-good-parts.html</id>
    <published>2023-05-29T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-05-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="xcom2-wotc">XCOM2 WotC</h2>
<p>I bought XCOM2 WotC (“War of the Chosen”) in a bundle for the Nintendo Switch. I’d completed a playthrough of the base game first. Overall, I found the game enthralling, but didn’t enjoy the RNG parts and so save-scummed my way through.</p>
<p>I just completed a playthrough of XCOM2 WotC. And while I still don’t like the RNG parts, WotC added some stuff which I thought was quite fun.</p>
<p>Broadly, the changes it made:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>New character classes: a stealthy sniper, and two other classes I didn’t find useful.</p></li>
<li><p>New enemy bosses: though fortunately, not quite as difficult as the bullshit Alien Rulers from XCOM2’s DLC.</p></li>
<li><p>Additional strategic components: you can assign your squad members to spend time away on non-gameplay missions.</p></li>
<li><p>Some more map varieties; including maps with zombie-like enemies.</p></li>
<li><p>Squadmate bonding. Which I didn’t use as much as I should have.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>To a greater or lesser extent, I liked these additions.</p>
<p>I also opted to play the game with “2x long mission timers”, “2x long game limit timer”, which eased some of the stress from playing.</p>
<h2 id="new-character-classes">New Character Classes</h2>
<p>From what I’d known of XCOM2 before playing it, this is the part I was most apprehensive about. – There being so many character classes, that it’d be overwhelming.</p>
<p>I do think it could benefit from being simplified. (Or benefit from the complexity moving about to some other layer of the game).</p>
<p>The ‘basic’ classes are the ‘rifleman (who can hack things)’, ‘the shotgunner (who also has a sword)’, ‘the Animal Mother wannabe with a big machine gun’, and ‘the sniper’. XCOM2 also has ‘the wizard’ and ‘the robot’.</p>
<p>What WotC adds is a few rarer classes:</p>
<ul>
<li>A ‘stealth sniper’.
<ul>
<li>The main thing this class has over the regular sniper is “concealment” as an individual. This is the same “concealment” that the team gets which allows for the ambush mechanics, but since it applies to the ‘stealth sniper’ as an individual unit, it means the ‘stealth sniper’ can stay hidden while the other units aren’t.</li>
<li>This unit ends up being super useful for scouting out the map, since it can ‘see’ the enemies, without aggro’ing the enemies.</li>
<li>However, the unit isn’t as good at dealing a lot of power to multiple units, so isn’t always better than the normal sniper.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>A ‘skirmisher’ unit.
<ul>
<li>idk. It has a submachine gun, and can shoot twice in one turn (or ‘shoot, then move’).
<ul>
<li>It also has a grappling hook, and can hook enemies towards it &amp; melee that enemy.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul></li>
<li>A ’battlemage unit.
<ul>
<li>It gets magic points by using its magic sword to kill enemies.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<p>The ‘stealth sniper’ is powerful to use right from the get-go, and gets even more powerful as it levels up.</p>
<p>The other two classes… maybe someone found them useful. Or maybe they’re really powerful when levelled up. But, I generally didn’t find them useful.</p>
<p>(I believe XCOM2 also tries to encourage using the DLC stuff by-way-of having some DLC stuff only be weak to other DLC stuff. I think that’s dubious design).</p>
<h2 id="new-enemy-bosses">New Enemy Bosses</h2>
<p>The new enemy bosses are the ‘Chosen’.</p>
<p>These aren’t as bullshit as the Alien Rulers; the Alien Rulers were both powerful <em>AND</em> moved/attacked after every <em>action</em> you took(!!!).</p>
<p>The Chosen each add their own effects to the map.</p>
<p>In the order I encountered them:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>The ‘ninja’ enemy boss.
<ul>
<li>Can teleport around the map, stun any of your units, then runs off somewhere far away where you can’t attack them.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>The ‘sniper’ enemy boss.
<ul>
<li>Uhm. … Might have a “I’m gonna shoot you next turn!” area-of-effect,
which is easily avoided.
<ul>
<li>To be clear: this is much less powerful than the effects the standard, common enemies are able to inflict.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul></li>
<li>The ‘mage’ enemy boss.
<ul>
<li>Uhm. Can spawn low tier enemies, I think?</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
<p>So. Starting off with the hardest enemy boss somewhat affected my feeling towards it.</p>
<p>The most annoying thing about these is the missions to defeat them involve “infinitely spawning enemies”, similar to the final mission.</p>
<h2 id="new-strategic-component-covert-actions-teammate-bonding">New Strategic Component: Covert Actions, Teammate Bonding</h2>
<p>I think these made interesting additions.</p>
<p>With “covert actions”, you assign some of your soldiers to a particular mission. So, the ‘cost’ is that these soldiers will be unavailable while on this mission. The benefits vary; sometimes it adds stats for the soldiers assigned. – One thing I liked here is that sometimes the soldiers could get “ambushed”, so you’d need to complete a small mission with these two soldiers to get them to safety. (This happened frequently enough that you’d have to worry about it, but not so frequently that it became boring or expected).</p>
<p>I like that because it’s a nice set of trade-offs. – You might want to send your best sniper on a mission which will add 5 to their aim stat, but you’d need to trust they can get out of an ambush situation, or that you won’t need that sniper on a mission in the meantime.</p>
<p>The teammate bonding.. I didn’t make much use of this. But the effects at level 3 look to be pretty powerful, so I kinda wish I had. – “Bonding” is sending the same pairs of soldiers out on missions together. The more you do that, the more benefits you get. – The first level of benefits involves being able to ‘share’ one action-point from one squadmate to the other, which ends up being <em>very</em> useful!</p>
<h2 id="more-map-varieties-zombie-like-maps-and-rebels-with-guns">More Map Varieties: Zombie-like Maps, and Rebels with Guns</h2>
<p>One thing XCOM suffers from is just how same-y the missions can get. – Every mission can be described as “get from A to Z, do it quickly, kill every enemy you see”.</p>
<p>Any mission that’s not like that stands out.<br />
(And, no, randomly throwing minibosses into levels doesn’t “add variety”).</p>
<h4 id="zombies">Zombies</h4>
<p>I was pleasantly surprised by the zombie-infected maps.<br />
That is, there are some maps which are filled with zombies. Since XCOM is usually focused on “your 4 squadmates vs 3 tough enemy units”, in order to handle “vs 6+ zombies”, the game adds a couple of rules: if you kill a zombie, your unit gets 1 more action point. (So instead of just shooting once, you can shoot 3 times if each shot kills a zombie). And, using explosives attracts a horde of zombies.</p>
<p>Part of what I liked is it does a good job of making your units feel properly powerful. (Often it takes just one or two of your units to dispatch all of the zombies on the screen).</p>
<p>I also like that: it adds a tactical drawback to using explosives above/beyond “you can’t use your grenade now and use it later too”.</p>
<p>An additional tactical aspect this adds is: the zombies will attack the regular alien enemies, too (and vice versa). – So you don’t necessarily want to dispatch all the zombies; or maybe you do. – It adds an interesting decision.</p>
<h4 id="rebels-with-guns">Rebels With Guns</h4>
<p>I also liked that there are missions which will feature friendly NPCs with guns.<br />
Rather. In XCOM, you’ll sometimes get missions where you have to rescue a bunch of civilians from the genocidal aliens.<br />
With XCOM2 WotC, some of these missions instead involve rescuing a friendly rebel base which in under attack from aliens.</p>
<p>I feel this makes more sense than not from a worldbuilding perspective.<br />
On the one hand, there’s the same uncanny “your team arrived just in time” problem that the other missions have. (Your dropship flies halfway around the world, and yet manages to always arrive in just-enough-time).<br />
On the other hand, I think it makes sense to have rapid-response forces react to enemy strikes. And it makes sense that there would be rebel forces which have guns.</p>
<p>From a gameplay perspective, these maps do add more enemies to deal with. But, it’s also nice to have more units fighting the enemies, too.</p>
<h2 id="wotcs-new-stuff-enhances-xcom-at-its-best-fun-tactical-combinations">WotC’s New Stuff Enhances XCOM at its Best: Fun Tactical Combinations</h2>
<p>The new abilities also added room for some more fun situational tactical combinations.</p>
<p>I think that’s where XCOM is at its most fun.</p>
<p>Albeit, these all sound like complicated sequences of Yugioh card moves:</p>
<p>One I liked:<br />
Using the stealth sniper’s ‘sticky bomb’ and ‘stealth shoot’ in tandem with the sniper’s ‘kill everything that moves in this zone’ ability.<br />
That is: The stealth sniper has a ‘sticky bomb’ that can be thrown onto an enemy (somehow without the enemy noticing), which explodes when the enemy takes damage. The stealth sniper also has an ability to shoot without breaking stealth (which is usable once per turn). The regular sniper has a “kill zone” ability which will shoot at anything that moves in a zone during that turn.<br />
Also: the stealth sniper can be in stealth and spot a group of enemies even when the other units have broken from stealth. It’s still possible to set up the “kill zone” and have the enemies be far away enough that they don’t aggro despite the sniper being able to set up the “kill zone”.<br />
It’s a nice ‘second ambush’, which quickly does a lot of damage to a group of enemies (if not outright destroy them)!</p>
<p>Another I liked:<br />
I saw there was a tech tower which had a 100% chance to ‘restore squad’s action points that turn’. And I had a heavy (machine gun + grenade launcher) unit who had a bond with a hacker unit; and that heavy unit had the upgrade such that shooting a grenade wouldn’t end its turn…<br />
This resulted in: setting up an ambush, with every unit (except the heavy) poised on overwatch – shoot the first thing that moves. Then, using the heavy unit to lob a grenade (and thus do a bit of damage to each of the enemies). This aggro’d the enemies, who then moved to cover; the enemies moving to cover then each triggers an overwatch reaction shot from my squad. <em>Then</em> I was able to have my heavy unit share its remaining action point with the hacker; that hacker then hacked the tower to restore all the action points for the squad.<br />
The net effect is being able to execute an ambush, but then have another turn for free (instead of normally having to let the enemy have a turn after the ambush is done).</p>
<p>I can agree that these are fun in part because the whole game isn’t filled with this. If everything was overpowered tactics, it wouldn’t feel overpowered. These opportunities are organic, and not on a pre-scripted linear path.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>XCOM2 has its Moments of Fun</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/games/2023-05-14-xcom2-has-its-moments-of-fun.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/games/2023-05-14-xcom2-has-its-moments-of-fun.html</id>
    <published>2023-05-14T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-05-14T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="xcom-and-civilization-theyre-okay">XCOM and Civilization: They’re Okay</h2>
<p>I recently picked up the XCOM 2 Collection for the Nintendo Switch. I was lucky to catch it on sale at a discount of 85%.</p>
<p>I just completed a playthrough of the base game. The collection also includes the expansion “War of the Chosen”, but I didn’t want to dive into too much content at once.</p>
<p>The Nintendo Switch isn’t <em>quite</em> powerful enough to run the game. (Frequently, with common interactions, the game slows down to a crawl). But, it gets the job done.</p>
<p>XCOM 2 was released in 2016, and is a sequel to XCOM: Enemy Unknown which was released in 2012.</p>
<p>I kinda put XCOM and Civilization in the same bucket: They’re from the same publisher. Some people really like them. They’re turn-based games, which involve strategic game over a long game. (Albeit, XCOM’s meat is with turn-based tactics, and Civilization’s turn-based gameplay is strategic).<br />
They both also kinda have a flavour of unfairness to them. (Civilization was controversial for having cases where a spearman can defeat a tank). They both also take such a long time to play (&amp; tend to have long feedback loops), that I find it hard to really get a deep intuitive understanding of the strategic considerations.</p>
<h2 id="what-new-in-xcom-2">What New in XCOM 2</h2>
<p>Recall, the XCOM gameplay involves two phases/modes: a base-building phase where you build specialised buildings &amp; research improvements; and a mission-phase where your soldiers skirmish with alien forces in turn-based tactics gameplay. (The broad game loop, then, is base-building improves your skirmishing capabilities; and your skirmishing earns you resources with which to build up your base).</p>
<p>At its core, the skirmishing is turn-based tactics in a square grid-based map, where you control a few soldiers who can take cover behind walls (cover is either ‘full’ or ‘half’); each turn involves moving all your units, a unit may move a limited distance, or use its turn to shoot its gun. – Whether your unit successfully hits the target it’s trying to shoot is probabilistic: you’re shown that a unit has a X% chance to hit. (ranging from e.g. 95% for if the target really close, to 10% if the it is really far away).<br />
One significant mechanic is the ‘overwatch’ ability: instead of shooting their gun, a unit might be put into ‘overwatch’, where they will then shoot at the first target that moves within their range.<br />
Units have different classes, and different abilities they might use their action points on. (e.g. sniper, medic, wizard).</p>
<p>XCOM 2 of course added some stuff.</p>
<p>I think the base-building strategic part is somewhat more dynamic in XCOM 2 than it was in the first game. Your base is like a flying castle/carrier, and it needs to be re-located in order to complete tasks. – In the first game, you started with all the countries in the council and had to minimize losses; whereas in this game, you start with no territories and have to build up your domination. I prefer this constructive approach.</p>
<p>In terms of the missions:</p>
<p>One mechanic they added was a ‘stealth’ mechanic at the start of the level.<br />
On most missions, the level starts out where your units are ‘concealed’ (enemies aren’t in an alert state). This leads to a nice dynamic where you can essentially set up an ambush against an enemy squad, by sneaking your units up close to the enemy, and then shooting the enemy all at once.</p>
<p>Many of the missions now have a turn limit.<br />
This was added to discourage turtling. But, it’s a bit obnoxious, and sometimes doesn’t make sense.<br />
One type of mission where it makes sense is strike missions against a landed UFO: it makes sense that the crew of a landed UFO may not be alerted to an enemy’s presence (and indeed, in this half of the mission, there isn’t a turn limit); and it makes sense that, once alerted, the UFO might try to take off within X turns (or send an alert out within X turns).<br />
But, for other missions, the turn limit doesn’t seem to make as much sense in tandem with the stealth mechanic. (“Enemies start unalerted; but there’s a time limit” is itself a neat strategical consideration, though; since the more time you take to leverage an advantage from stealth means more effort is required to beat the goal in the turn limit).</p>
<p>I don’t recall it being possible in the previous XCOM game, but in XCOM 2 many of the enemy units are robots, and these can be ‘hacked’ so you can control the robot for a few turns.</p>
<h2 id="xcom-is-not-entirely-to-my-taste">XCOM is Not Entirely to My Taste</h2>
<p>To be honest, I think the intended XCOM playing experience is not to my taste.</p>
<p>I don’t like the RNG fuckery.</p>
<p>Largely the probabilistic combat mechanics.. this means that, even if you make reasonable decisions in order to stop the enemy, your actions may still be ineffective. (It doesn’t matter what decisions you make if all of your shots miss). To a lesser extent, it’s also possible that enemies can show up at an inconvenient time (e.g. spotting one enemy in a squad then aggros the whole enemy squad), and so you learn to ‘game’ the mechanics to avoid this (with XCOM rules, you never want to have your final unit move further than your other units).<br />
– Whenever I felt XCOM was being ‘unfair’, as a casual player I just reloaded an earlier save &amp; avoided making the same mistake. This isn’t a “fun” way to play, but it’s less not-fun than playing an ‘unfair’ game.</p>
<p>XCOM seems to be about “eh, make what you can with what you’re given”.<br />
The first tutorial mission does a good job of setting this up, where it gives you only a handful of soldiers, kills one of them and badly wounds the other.</p>
<p>I know there are some players who can play the game on the hardest difficulty without reloading a save, sure. – But I reckon such people know the rules of the game much more intimately than someone who’s just doing a blind playthrough and doesn’t know the boundaries.</p>
<h2 id="whats-fun">What’s Fun</h2>
<p>I did complete one playthrough. Partly for the sake of completing it.</p>
<p>As much as I generally dislike the game, there were some parts which were quite fun:</p>
<p>I did like the new stealth mechanic.<br />
It’s a lot of fun to set up an ambush and completely wipe out an enemy.<br />
It is possible to screw up, so the stealth mechanic is not a freebie.<br />
– I felt it was a lot of fun to get all of my units into overwatch mode, and to then break stealth by using a grenade (or some other attack which damaged multiple units). The whole squad firing their weapons at once reminds me of the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iG0i0g7Csc8">overkill scene in Generation Kill</a><br />
– Maybe it would be overpowered, but I wonder if having a “synchronised shot” system would also work nicely with this mechanic.</p>
<p>I liked using the sharpshooter (sniper), especially once I was able to upgrade all the unit’s abilities.<br />
Initially, the sharpshooter’s rifle’s magazine has only 3 rounds. Shooting consumes the sharpshooter’s whole turn, so at least 1 turn out of 4 has to be used to reload.<br />
It’s possible to upgrade the sharpshooter’s rifle with an upgrade that gives the magazine an extra 3 rounds (to a total of 6).<br />
This synergises with:<br />
For one, there’s an ability “kill zone”, which has the unit shoot at anything which moves within an area.<br />
For another, there’s an ability where the sharpshooter can keep making shots, so long as each shot they take kills an enemy.<br />
Both of these really encourage effective tactical use of the sharpshooter. The “kill zone” is very powerful to use when setting up the ambush at the start of the level (since enemies will move to cover once the stealth breaks, and thus would trigger the kill zone’s reaction shot).<br />
The “keep shooting so long as you kill units” is also a very powerful way of dealing with situations where you face a large number of enemies at once; you can get your other squadmates to destroy the cover the enemies are hiding behind (to ensure a better hit), to shred some of the enemy’s armour (so that the marksman is more likely to kill the enemy), or to bring a powerful enemy’s health down just enough.</p>
<p>There are times when enemy reinforcements will be fast-roped in from an enemy dropship; the location they show up is marked 1 turn before they insert. – This gives you the opportunity to ambush these units; I found that pretty fun too.</p>
<h2 id="its-enthralling-but-undermined-by-not-being-fun">It’s Enthralling, but Undermined by not being Fun</h2>
<p>I remember from Zero Punctuation’s review of the previous XCOM game, ZP asks rhetorically “Is it fun? Let me play one more level to check… hours later, I noticed it was 2am. Let’s pencil that in as a ‘yes’”.</p>
<p>And I agree that the game is enthralling.</p>
<p>But, I think it’s enthralling in not such a nice way.</p>
<p>The main driving motivation is “if I just get X, then later Y will not be so bad”.
(“once I get the laser guns, then combat will be easier”, “once I get more resources, then my base will be more powerful”, etc.).</p>
<p>Factorio (which I <em>really</em> enjoy playing) also has prominently has “your actions make things easier later” as a driving motivation.<br />
(Whereas, say, shooter games, or RPGs don’t necessarily).<br />
For Factorio, building more stuff means that later I’ll be able to build even more stuff. – e.g. In Factorio’s early game, you might notice that you’re not mining enough copper; so you’ll build more copper miners to speed things up. In the late game, you’ll build bots which then allow you to focus on building your base at a higher level.</p>
<p>But for XCOM?<br />
For XCOM, the draw of continuing to play feels like “just one more thing, and them I’m safe”.</p>
<p>It would be an exaggeration to say that XCOM’s gameplay is all about rolling a dice.<br />
But, I don’t think it’s the same level of exaggeration to say that XCOM wants you to consider what happens when it rolls the dice low, and your shots miss, or you fail to hack the robot, etc.<br />
– Once you have powerful guns, it’s less of a worry if one soldier misses, since another soldier is likely to hit. Once you have the powerful armour, you don’t have to worry about being OHKO’d by random enemies.</p>
<p>So, while obviously a game is ‘not fun’ if it’s trivially easy,<br />
a game is also not fun if it’s unfair.<br />
– I’d say ‘fun’ is about whether I can make decisions where I can feel responsible for things not going well. And XCOM’s RNG fuckery undermines that, even if the worst stuff is a long tail.</p>
<p>With XCOM, in order for me to feel that something is my fault, I have to have fucked up pretty badly.</p>
<p>I don’t feel like I’ve accomplished much by winning, I feel <em>relieved</em> I didn’t roll low RNG.</p>
<h2 id="and-xcom2-has-too-many-not-fun-moments">And XCOM2 Has Too Many Not-Fun Moments</h2>
<p>Okay, so I keep banging on about how XCOM has RNG fuckery.</p>
<p>I’m sure I haven’t experienced the worst, but here were some moments in my playthrough which were pretty annoying:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Some enemy unit was able to charge past 3 of my units in overwatch (i.e. all 3 missed), as well as completely dodging two of the “melee attack if enemy moves to adjancent square” reactions, as well as <em>then</em> missing some the shots I made on my turn.</p>
<ul>
<li>It doesn’t matter how tactically well you play if the enemy can just ignore all of your attacks.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>Due to ‘bad timing’, as soon as I completed an objective at the end of my turn (i.e. my units all had to reload, and had no AP left), completing the objective aggro’d the enemies who were defending the objective (okay, fine), but also aggro’d the squad hiding just behind them, and reinforcements showed up on that same turn. – This meant that my squad went from “no enemies in sight” to “outnumbered 2 to 1”.</p></li>
<li><p>I have the expectation that one randomly generated level should be approximately as difficult as another (at the same point of progression). Once I did attempt a mission which I found to be too difficult; when I reloaded (and the mission re-generated), the regenerated mission was much easier to tackle.</p></li>
<li><p>XCOM 2 has some DLC bosses. These are powerful enough that they take actions (moving &amp; attacking) between each one of your unit’s actions. (e.g. if your unit reloads their weapon, the DLC boss will move &amp; attack something).</p>
<ul>
<li>On the one hand, the bosses being this bullshit-powerful kinda balances against how bullshit-powerful your squad can be in the late game.</li>
<li>On the other hand, the bosses show up randomly; it’s also not signposted. I would be expect most people playing casually would just reload an earlier save to prepare for the boss encounter.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>RNG bullshit in the player’s favour: there’s a powerup which gives your weapon a 5%/10%/15% chance of instantly killing an enemy (depending on whether the powerup is level 1/2/3). I was able to beat a powerful enemy robot with this once. I was surprised.</p>
<ul>
<li>On the one hand, I’ll take it.</li>
<li>On the other hand, I think when this activates, it undermines the tactical demands of the situation.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<p>I saw XCOM described as “hope your units avoid critical hits at the start, and by the end your units are glass cannons”.<br />
This seems quite accurate.</p>
<p>I somewhat didn’t like the turn-limit.<br />
Well, since I was fine with save-scumming, it’s not such an issue.<br />
But, I feel the design goals of “you’d better go fast” really conflict with the design goals of “you have to be able to mitigate for when RNG doesn’t go your way”.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Netflix's 1899 is Fascinating</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/2023-05-09-netflixs-1899-is-fascinating.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/2023-05-09-netflixs-1899-is-fascinating.html</id>
    <published>2023-05-09T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-05-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Netflix’s “1899” comes from the same creators as “Dark”.</p>
<p>I’d watched “Dark” a few years ago; watching the first two seasons in 2019, and then its final third season some time later.</p>
<p>It’s very much a case of “if you like one, you’ll like the other”.<br />
With “1899”, I definitely enjoyed it enough to binge my way through it.</p>
<h2 id="summary-of-the-show">Summary of the Show</h2>
<p>I think an apt enough comparison to make is that watching “Dark” in many ways engages the same parts of my brain as programming does.<br />
– I think more precisely, “Dark” and “1899” are probably most entertaining for people who love modelling for modelling’s sake. The shows each provide interesting and dense relations between each of the characters. – e.g. I recall that “Dark”, a show about time travelling, plays with at least two grandfather paradoxes: a classic ‘her daughter is her mother’, and a more fun ‘his girlfriend is his father’s sister’.</p>
<p>I’m not sure if these shows are quite for everyone.<br />
One reason why these shows might not be broadly appealing to everyone is that the aesthetic and the characters generally are ostensibly quite miserable.<br />
Another is that these shows dawdle their way around their mysteries elements, and aren’t in a particular hurry to explain things.</p>
<p>I knew going in to “1899” that it wouldn’t end with everything explained.<br />
Rather, “Dark” takes 3 seasons to tell its story. And each season essentially added a whole other dimension to the world. Or it crawled, then walked, then ran.<br />
So, that, and, I’d heard “1899” wasn’t going to get its second and third seasons.<br />
– Netflix not renewing seasons reminds me of the YouTube channel “Achievement Hunter”, which would not follow through on series they would start because of a lack of views; and so each episode they put out would be immature (since the ensemble were getting familiar with the game they made a video about). The end result (amongst many other controversies) was that people stopped watching the series, and viewership slowly spiraled down.</p>
<h2 id="what-i-found-engaging-its-themes-and-setting">What I Found Engaging: Its Themes and Setting</h2>
<p>I’d say what makes “1899” so fascinating is its setting, and the themes it plays with as part of its story.<br />
I think the plot (and the mystery aspect of that), and the characters are somewhat weaker.</p>
<p>“1899” is set on an ocean liner at sea in … 1899.<br />
Woven throughout the narrative are themes like ‘the mind and what influences it’, ‘perception and perspective and presentation’, ‘dreams of the future, their realization in the present, and thoughts of the past’, ‘exploration and avoidance and curiousity and fear’.</p>
<p>I mean, to give a couple of examples:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>The ship is filled with crew &amp; passengers who speak different languages such as English, German, Polish, Spanish (not necessarily all overlapping). Sometimes characters who have no hope of understanding one another will still communicate openly and honestly; whereas characters who speak the same language may speak in a guarded manner, not revealing the things they know.</p></li>
<li><p>Early on one character from first class visits the third class below decks. She’s told by the captain “it’s against the rules for you to go there”, and the lady responds “who sets those rules, and for what benefit?”. – Later on, the captain gives an order to his crew; the first mate appeals with “but captain, the rules say…”. – From a certain perspective, these interactions deal with: the boundaries of what’s possible, conformance to or defiance of those rules and perceived expectations.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>I don’t think this is a case of searching for symbolism where there’s none.<br />
Say, “the colour of the carpet” probably has no symbolic value.<br />
But, I think the show densely relates a bunch of things, and doesn’t got out of your way to make sure you notice.</p>
<p>Some of the symbolism I don’t quite get.<br />
We learn the ship is named “Kerberos”. “Kerberos” the three-headed dog that guards Hades in Greek mythology.. but, its symbolism as it applies to “1899” isn’t clear to me.<br />
Triangles and tetrahedrons (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simplex">simplexes</a>???) are also shown prominently. But, any thematic meaning around this also isn’t clear to me.</p>
<p>Anyway.</p>
<p>The characters, if nothing else, do feel like they’re well suited or situated to play around with these kinds of themes. The story weaves in all sorts of details about the characters’ dreams, regrets, and masks.</p>
<p>The show is fun enough to watch in and of itself.<br />
But, there was a moment where I felt the intention really is “hey, this is fun, huh!”:<br />
Each episode ends with a 60’s rock song. (Or some are the 70’s).<br />
– There’s a ‘risk’ of using pop music in media. The viewer might already associate the song with some feeling or emotion. And it seems clear to me that the writers know that, since the story often makes points about being reminded of the past, or of seeing what you want to see.<br />
One episode ended with “(Don’t Fear) the Reaper”.<br />
Or as I know it as: the “More Cowbell” song.</p>
<h2 id="where-the-show-felt-weak-plot-and-characters">Where the Show Felt Weak: Plot and Characters</h2>
<p>The plot?</p>
<p>Well. Each episode will end with a teasing reveal of something mysterious, the effect of which is you’ll want to watch the next episode right away.<br />
This works even if you know it’s going for a cliffhanger; and works even if you’re pretty sure it won’t get explained. (’cause, hey, there’s only so many episodes; some of them will have to explain some stuff).<br />
– I don’t think this is so sophisticated; but it is effective.</p>
<p>Again, not everything gets explained.<br />
But even considering that it’s only one season out of three, there’re still some surreal mystery elements which drive the plot that don’t get explained.<br />
I can’t help but be reminded of that quote from “The Simpsons”: ‘well, anytime you notice something like that, a wizard did it’.<br />
(“The Matrix” was able to do ‘trilogy of stories about weird mystery stuff’ while also having the first part of the story be a coherent whole; I think it’s reasonable that a first part be able to work as a coherent whole).</p>
<p>The show avoids overstaying its welcome… it doesn’t linger on its cleverness or go out of its way to show off how clever it is.<br />
e.g. I did spot the show’s main symbol appearing behind the ear on one character. It’s probably not too hard to spot. But, it’s not emphasised.</p>
<p>I found the characters a bit ‘ehhhhh’.</p>
<p>I’m reminded of what I felt reading R. A. Salvatore’s fantasy stories. Salvatore’s action is excellent: it’s gripping; at the start of the book, the villains seem powerful, and by the end, the heroes manage to make a daring strike to beat the villains, and it’s all very fun. – But Salvatore’s characters <em>sucked</em>, and were a little too self-indulgent. His main character never makes mistakes, everything he does is perfect, everyone who challenges him is a mean pig and a bad person. – It’s … not all that interesting.</p>
<p>With “1899”, my senses are tickled in the same way.<br />
The main character is a women who studied science. And so of course we get such insightful dialogue like “Woman disagrees with me? That’s because she’s letting her emotions affect her” or some such flat thing like that.<br />
The characters feel constructed as if by the morals that would have the Christians all be either naive, crazy, or faking their belief; where the same morality would also emphasise and lament that Muslims aren’t treated with respect in society.<br />
Mostly the show’s characters avoid filling such a sanctimonious role as this.</p>
<h2 id="woulda-been-nice-to-see-the-rest-of-the-story">Woulda Been Nice to See the Rest of the Story</h2>
<p>In any case, I did enjoy watching the show.</p>
<p>I think it’s a shame that the series didn’t continue. (I wonder if it’s the kind of story where by the end of season of season 3, the characters come to realise they’re characters in a TV show).</p>
<p>If a storyteller’s able to come up with something as intruiging as this with this set of toys, it’s a shame to not let them go on present the rest of their toychest.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>

</feed>
