<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Richard Goulter's Blog</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//atom.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog/" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//atom.xml</id>
    <author>
        <name>Richard Goulter</name>
        <email>richard.goulter+blog@gmail.com</email>
    </author>
    <updated>2017-01-15T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <entry>
    <title>Toothless Dangerous Rhetoric in NZPol</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/politics/2017-01-15-toothless-dangerous-rhetoric-in-nzpol.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/politics/2017-01-15-toothless-dangerous-rhetoric-in-nzpol.html</id>
    <published>2017-01-15T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-01-15T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on January 15, 2017
    
        by Richard Goulter
    <br/>
    
    Tags: <a href="/tags/new%20zealand.html">new zealand</a>, <a href="/tags/politics.html">politics</a>
    
</div>

<p>I don’t follow the NZ Blogosphere too closely.<br />
Glimpsing at it, it’s not difficult to come across nutcase-y views. (My favourite, as made popular by the NZ Flag Referendum, was the kind which used CAPITALS to highlight IMPORTANT WORDS in a meaningless rant).<br />
– Given that NZ has a largely apathetic attitude towards politics, religion et al., I guess it’s no surprise that those who <em>do</em> care are disproportionately <em>weird</em>.</p>
<p>There is the risk in pointing to content and saying “hey, this deviates from what society ought to be” that this lends power to such deviants. c.f. <a href="https://status451.com/2016/11/28/its-protein-world-we-just-live-in-it/">Meredith Patterson’s remarks here</a>.</p>
<hr />
<p><a href="http://thewireless.co.nz/articles/there-is-no-such-thing-as-casual-racism">This post</a> came up on my newsfeed.<br />
(For context of popularity: the post itself has 0 comments).</p>
<p>The title “No such thing as casual racism” is pretty edgy.<br />
Moreso since the intended audience is presumably one which would tell you “casual racism is a big problem”. – Less so since the preview-snippet says “it’s just straight-up racism” (which kindof ratchets up an extreme view even further).</p>
<p>Reading over it, the piece isn’t as explicitly dangerous as I was expecting.<br />
The piece takes Sir Peter “Mad Butcher” Leitch as its excuse for saying “current events demonstrate my political view is correct”.<br />
The author’s point, perhaps more elegantly phrased, is that “1) all kinds of racism are racism 2) racism is bad 3) therefore, to categorise kinds of racism means defending racism as ‘not that bad’”. – Thus, referring to any remark as “casually racist” is saying “racism isn’t <em>that</em> bad”. (In the author’s words: <em>“How can you categorise racism in any form and excuse racism in any form?”</em>).</p>
<p>Or, to look at it from another perspective:</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: upper-alpha">
<li><p>Racism is a problem in NZ. e.g. Maoris are over-represented in NZ’s Criminal-Justice System, and Maoris are victims of unconscious bias against them.</p></li>
<li><p>A prominent New Zealander said a racially-tinged remark which the conversant took offence at; the conversant received an immediate apology.</p></li>
<li><p>To defend (B) as ‘not as bad as’ (A) is to defend racism.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>– Logically this leads to “i) (B) is as bad as (A). ii) (B) is not that bad. iii) Therefore, (A) is not that bad”, which is fucking absurd.</p>
<p>I don’t think the author seriously believes that.<br />
But saying “casual racism is racism; racism is bad; so, the term ‘casual racism’ enables racism” is a <em>morally righteous</em> thing to say. It sounds good.<br />
– In the article, the author lambasts Newshub for having a ‘quiz’ “Are a casual racist?”; the author misinterprets this as ‘normalizing’ racism, rather than an attempt to raise consciousness about racism in society. – Again, this looks like an attempt to be the most anti-racist person possible (rather than say something of substance).<br />
– The author continues: <em>Māori Party co-leader Te Ururoa Flavell said … that Sir Peter is not racist, but the incident has highlighted the casual racism in society.</em>: with the above lens in mind, criticising Maori Party’s co-leader of enabling racism is super anti-racist, or something.</p>
<p>If we instead read the post as if it’s discussing problems in NZ society, then that the author is able to steadfastly posture over something so trivial indicates that there can’t be any more serious problems worth worrying about.<br />
– I can only makes sense if the author supports something like “the racism behind misinterpreted remarks is how we end up with inequalities in society”. Horseshoe nails and broken windows and all. – That sounds fascinating, and possibly nuanced. Maybe the author should have written about that instead?</p>
<hr />
<p>It’d be remiss of me, in analysing the post, to not include the most interesting paragraph:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Racism is an ideology, just like being a liberal, conservative, anarchist, or religious. In many cases they are intertwined by design or just pure coincidence. And here we are, masquerading racism as if its “casual” component was comparable to having brunch, or casual sex, actions free of beliefs. What’s next, a Tinder-like app for casual racism?</p>
</blockquote>
<p><code>&quot;Racism is an ideology&quot;</code> sounds like parroting a taught mantra without explaining it. Perhaps using the word ‘racism’ differently to how most people would use the word.<br />
<code>&quot;In many cases they are intertwined by design or just pure coincidence.&quot;</code> is a preaching-to-the-choir sophisticated way of saying “some ideologies are racist, amirite?”.<br />
<code>&quot;What's next, a Tinder-like app for casual racism?&quot;</code>. Like. Surely even the author had to think this was a dumb thing to write. – An absurd exaggeration which doesn’t particularly work for supporting “racism is a problem in NZ”, but does flow for supporting the author saying “look how concerned about this problem I am”.<br />
– That the author doesn’t acknowledge their own convictions are ideologically driven also detracts from the post’s maturity.</p>
<hr />
<p>Coming across the title, I figured the post would be dangerous in terms of inciting tension. (cf. <a href="http://thefederalist.com/2016/11/14/election-marks-end-americas-racial-detente/">“an End to Racial Detente”</a>).<br />
But overall it’s pretty toothless. Much of what is righteously compelling about the post is regurgitation of politicised views of the world. (Viewpoints which aren’t necessarily common/shared with the NZ population).</p>
<p>I still using accusations of ‘racism’ disproportionately is dangerous.<br />
cf. US Media’s drift from over-using “racist”, to “outright racist” to “white nationalist”, as each phrase becomes ineffective; <a href="http://slatestarcodex.com/2016/11/16/you-are-still-crying-wolf/">You’re Still Crying Wolf</a>.<br />
Let alone, if people are condemned regardless of what they do, there’s nothing to stop people from doing wrong.<br />
People like this, righteous &amp; not with majority viewpoint, need to see value in “playing politics” (or “being persuasive”) if they hope to make any changes to the problems they see in the world. Signalling what <em>good people</em> they are only feels good.<br />
– To that extent, it’s still valuable to rebut “casual racism is racism”. (Albeit, with the tradeoffs/risks noted at the start of this post).<br />
One dumb, preaching-to-the-choir internet blogpost to another.</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Internet Myopia</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/argument/2016-12-26-internet-myopia.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/argument/2016-12-26-internet-myopia.html</id>
    <published>2016-12-26T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-12-26T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on December 26, 2016
    
        by Richard Goulter
    <br/>
    
    Tags: <a href="/tags/politics.html">politics</a>
    
</div>

<p>Twitter is a great website for righteous anger. Recently, I’ve observed that people on Twitter tend to be myopic. – You can be fairly sure that the things people tweet about (or retweet) will all have a single focus. It’s more specific than “my tribe is awesome/good”.</p>
<p>I tend to be hesitant about giving object-level opinions.<br />
There’s a well-known fable about four blind folk describing what they sense; four unique/different parts of an elephant. It’s often recounted in a kumbaya, “people may each see a different part of truth” kindof way. (Similarly, there’s the cartoon about the cylinder projected as a circle and a rectangle, and two folk arguing..; I think that’s pretty dumb/bullshit, because it does a poor job of modelling how people disagree over things).<br />
– What I’d emphasise here is the <em>limited</em> nature the opinions (rather than the “everyone sees some truth”). – The blind folk still only know the parts of the elephant they encounter. – You can kinda-sorta dismiss <em>any</em> opinion off-hand as limited and probably-wrong. (This is why ‘qualifying’ the opinion is useful). But it’s still probably useful to have some marketplace of ideas where different opinions get thrown about.</p>
<p>Something which is pretty fascinating is, in their myopic anger.. it’s interesting to see the way one group describes their out-group. – People remain pettily angry about some incident/issue for a long time.<br />
I guess fear is a better motivator than hope; and each side of some conflict will see their side as losing. e.g.:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>in the culture-wars of the tech industry, the progressives see the industry as full of white dudebros even as every major tech company does their best to make efforts toward diverse ethnic/gender identities. Whether the public efforts are lightweight lip-service (without impact) or wasteful tithing to ideology depends on your tribe. (Or: Is <em>saying</em> you’re going to make things better sufficient to show things will get better?).</p></li>
<li><p>Many are exclaiming that 2016 has been a bad year for liberal politics in Western Democracies; those who dissent claim the extreme difficulty with which the non-elite masses have to get their voice heard in democracy.</p></li>
<li><p>Nutcases will use the phrase “Age of Trump” to describe an epidemic of sexism and racism (this dramatic interpretation all because Trump won by ~1% of the vote!), whereas the other side points to those who are fired (or harassed) for not toeing the progressive politics.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>On Facebook, my friends share posts with phrases like “..your Facebook feed full of Trump supporters..”, and such an experience is completely alien to me.</p>
<p>– Of course, none of that is much of a <em>surprise</em>: people don’t question claims which support their beliefs; and will be doubtful about claims which go against their beliefs.<br />
“<em>Can</em> I believe it?” (for things you want to believe),<br />
“<em>Must</em> I believe it?” (for things you don’t want to believe).<br />
– And in a sense all the above is just an example of “talking past each other”. But it’s fascinating to see.</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>What even is the point of politics</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/argument/2016-12-18-what-even-is-the-point-of-politics.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/argument/2016-12-18-what-even-is-the-point-of-politics.html</id>
    <published>2016-12-18T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-12-18T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on December 18, 2016
    
        by Richard Goulter
    <br/>
    
    Tags: <a href="/tags/politics.html">politics</a>
    
</div>

<p>What even is the point of politics?<br />
The arguing-with-acquaintances-about-the-news kind of politics.</p>
<p>It seems to be just for expressing anger.. – but moreover, to express tribal affiliation. (Meaningness’s <a href="https://meaningness.wordpress.com/2015/10/05/buddhist-ethics-is-advertising/">“Ethics is Advertising”</a> post does a good job of arguing this point: that so much of what we do is to signal that <em>we</em> are <em>good</em> people).</p>
<p>But it seems to me all the kinds of articles which get shared about say the same thing: “Here’s something which happened; here’s why it shows my political viewpoint is correct”.<br />
– I’m trying <em>really</em> hard to internalize that people don’t discuss politics in search of truth; that “reason is slave to the passions”. – Surely it’s at least a little pathetic that all the anger expressed has no more purpose, no more impact than a disguised way of saying “hey I’m correct?”.</p>
<p>Perhaps it’s the INTJ in me, but I guess there’s more hope in trying to understand politics in terms of ‘incentives’, then it’s easier to find a model to describe the world; easier to discuss policies in terms of which better suits whatever set of ideals/priorities.<br />
– That, if politics is about satisfying incentives, then we can discuss the politics of history. (“in this case, this happened; in that case, that happened, so what does that mean this time”).</p>
<p>– That righteous-expression-of-anger has dominated the political discussion I see … I guess in order to think that this is a <em>bad</em> thing (compared to, say, a fantastic disinterested discussion of policies), you’d still be clinging to the idea that people intend to seek truth.<br />
– Seeking out the drama of all the hypocrisies inherent in arguing over moral values, &amp; shitposting about this; that’s fun.<br />
– But in terms of modelling &amp; making sense of politics, “righteousness” is a way better model.</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Best Programming Style Always Depends</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2016-12-17-best-programming-style-always-depends.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2016-12-17-best-programming-style-always-depends.html</id>
    <published>2016-12-17T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-12-17T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on December 17, 2016
    
        by Richard Goulter
    <br/>
    
    Tags: <a href="/tags/programming.html">programming</a>
    
</div>

<p>In Steve Yegge’s hauntingly interesting <a href="http://steve-yegge.blogspot.sg/2008/02/portrait-of-n00b.html">“Portrait of a n00b”</a> article, he argues that:</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>all meta-data is unnecessary for programs to run.</li>
<li>n00b programmers can’t handle the complexity of code, and so prefer as much whitespacing as possible (so that there’s less code on the screen). – Expert programmers on the other hand prefer as much code on the screen as possible.</li>
<li>So it’s unsurprising that n00b programmers will write bad code which is over-commented, with a strong preference for meta-data. (While Expert programmers will write bad code which is uncommented, and will avoid use of meta-data).</li>
</ol>
<p>– The article also portrays the kind of person who loves modelling how situations; who just loves meta-data. Either programmers who pickup Database Administration, or who come across an ML-language like OCaml or Haskell. – Yegge points out “you can’t force people to provide meta-data for everything, they’ll hate you”.</p>
<hr />
<p>The generally-accepted rule-of-thumb for function length is “fits on a screen” or “less than 50/30/20 lines”, etc. (I’ve heard the “Pragmatic Object-Oriented Design in Ruby” argues for even stricter guidelines).</p>
<hr />
<p>Not long ago, a post about <a href="http://number-none.com/blow/john_carmack_on_inlined_code.html">an email from John Carmack about inlining code</a> got quite popular.<br />
Briefly: while small functions are fine for ‘pure’ functions, it’s impractical to have all functions be ‘pure’. For impure functions, there are often implicit assumptions made about state: e.g. it’s expected certain methods are called in a particular order. It’s more straightforward to ‘inline’ the ‘methods’ all in one larger method. This guarantees these ‘methods’ can’t be called elsewhere.</p>
<hr />
<p>I also recently came across this interesting post from <a href="http://martinfowler.com/bliki/FunctionLength.html">Martin Fowler, about ‘function length’</a>.<br />
The first observation he makes is that “how long should a function be” is asked in lieu of “what should be contained in its own function?”.<br />
The second observation is the astute distinction between a program’s intention and it’s implementation. – He gives the example from an old system where ‘highlighting’ text was the same as ‘reverse-image of display’; but because the intention (‘highlight’) was significantly different from the implementation (‘reverse’), there was value in a method which just deferred the work to another method.</p>
<hr />
<p><a href="http://degoes.net/articles/insufficiently-polymorphic">“Descriptive Names are a Code Smell”</a> is an interesting post in this regard.<br />
To paraphrase, “long/descriptive names violate the notion of ‘keep your type-declarations as vague as they need to be’”.<br />
– I think this only applies to ‘implementation’ of a computation. (“I want to get a result in this form, from an input in this form”). Because “descriptive names are bad” flies in the face of “keep intention clear”. – I don’t see this advice as contradictory to e.g. Fowler’s. (Implementation code occurs at a lower level of abstraction than the intention’s code).</p>
<p>But. On the other hand.<br />
“Keep things generic”, ‘polymorphic’ rather than ‘monomorphic’.. it’s easier to see how to do this with generic data structures like lists/arrays/dictionaries. For, say, Java, I suppose you get this polymorphims by Interfaces. (Though I guess with e.g. Python/Ruby, you could be ‘generic’ without needing to provide the meta-data).<br />
– But I imagine this is where (mainstream) languages aren’t so expressive. It’s not so easy to provide abstractions over functions, classes, or at least modules/packages. – It’s not so hard to write a common-enough computation for any array; but not so easy to supply functionality over a module. – Though I can’t think of an example off the top of my head why that’d be necessary.</p>
<hr />
<p>There’s something else to be cautious of with “be as generic as possible”.<br />
People love to over-engineer; to solve problems they used to have (or think they’ll have) rather than problems they currently have.<br />
There may be different ways to make a program ‘more generic’.</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Catching up on Action Games</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/games/2016-11-26-catching-up-on-action-games.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/games/2016-11-26-catching-up-on-action-games.html</id>
    <published>2016-11-26T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-11-26T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on November 26, 2016
    
        by Richard Goulter
    <br/>
    
    Tags: <a href="/tags/game.just%20cause.html">game.just cause</a>, <a href="/tags/game.call%20of%20duty.html">game.call of duty</a>
    
</div>

<p>So I recently got a new gaming PC. It’s good to not have to say “can’t play that game, my computer is so old”.</p>
<p>I was able to re-play through Just Cause 3. – I’d played through on a friend’s PS4; but since then the DLC for the game has been released.<br />
JC3 was already very much an action-playground. The DLC added to this: a jetpack (where you get to shoot machine-guns / missiles while flying around), mechs, and a super-action-jetboat (with machine-guns and missiles).<br />
– My thoughs on JC3 remain more/less the same as at the start of the year; I still wish you could customise things (like in Saints Row), etc. – But in terms of “crazy action-man gameplay”, I can’t imagine how Just Cause 4 could possible top Just Cause 3.</p>
<p>I’ve also spent some time catching up on the Call of Duty games. (I was able to get away with playing CoD:Black Ops 2 on my laptop, barely).<br />
– I almost feel the need for a disavowal: CoD is barely more of a game than The Sims is. No serious, enthusiastic gamer would be proud to say they enjoyed playing CoD. (As opposed to, say, The Witcher 3 or Dark Souls or etc.). – That’s fine, but also for the most part refers to CoD <em>multiplayer</em>. Which I don’t touch. (Nor the zombies, for that matter).<br />
– I just play the dumb action campaign, influences of which has somehow come to dominate the FPS genre. – Which is kindof weird; ’cause the CoD games tend to throw in ACTION like the player will get bored if they go for 3 seconds without seeing an explosion or something cool happen. – And games like Homefront which follow the formula pretty closely (albeit with a more budget feel) cop a lot of shit.</p>
<p><em>That</em> stuff I don’t mind so much.<br />
With CoD you pretty much know what you’re getting.</p>
<p>CoD Ghosts, I recall, caught many bad reviews.<br />
It’s “the one with the dog”.</p>
<p>– I think Zero Punctuation’s review remarked that so much of CoD gameplay involved “hey, here’s a new toy, which you get to use once, and never again”. – I think that’s accurate, and it really limits how good a ‘game’ CoD could be.<br />
Rather than incrementally expanding a player’s tools (&amp; the enemies they face).. fancy gimmicks which get used once leads to the game feeling like Dora-the-Explorer: receiving instructions for when to push which button at which time.</p>
<p>So, yeah, CoD Ghosts does that.<br />
And continues the CoD tradition of having a super-bad-guy who wants-to-get-caught. And who you fight at the end only through a series of quick-time-events.<br />
– So, yeah. You know what you’re getting.</p>
<p>CoD: Advanced Warfare. “the one with Kevin Spacey”.<br />
– Holy shit, I found it hard to tell whether the (pre-rendered) cutscenes were computer-rendered or live-action. I’m fairly sure the scenes must be computer-generated.</p>
<p>CoD:AW at least adds a game-mechanic you get to keep using throughout: you have a new exo-suit. (Kindof like a lamer version of Crysis’ exo-suit, although it’ll be different in different levels).<br />
– There was also one interesting level: your left-arm gets injured, so you’re unable to reload and must continuously pick up weapons (with ammo) from fallen enemies. – It’s a nice example of requiring the player to <em>adapt</em> from the game’s typical gameplay.</p>
<p>CoD:AW was less annoying than CoD:Ghosts. But they’re both the same blob-ish cinematic blur of action, which is fun enough.</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>My Impression of Ruby So Far</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2016-10-15-my-impression-of-ruby-so-far.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2016-10-15-my-impression-of-ruby-so-far.html</id>
    <published>2016-10-15T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-10-15T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on October 15, 2016
    
        by Richard Goulter
    <br/>
    
    Tags: <a href="/tags/programming.ruby.html">programming.ruby</a>, <a href="/tags/programming.scala.html">programming.scala</a>, <a href="/tags/programming.haskell.html">programming.haskell</a>
    
</div>

<h3 id="background">Background</h3>
<p>I’ve recently started programming in Ruby. I’ve inherited a codebase for writing automated-UI tests against a website. The tests make use of Capybara, which provides a high-level “DSL” for interacting with a webpage/browser in the sameway a user would; Capybara itself does this by abstracting over Selenium (or some other driver, like Poltergeist/PhantomJS); Selenium itself allows interaction with different web-browsers, by providing abstractions for different drivers of browsers (e.g. ChromeDriver).</p>
<p>As is also common for tests like these (called “UI tests”, “acceptance tests”, “functional tests”, “specifications”, “end to end tests” depending on who you ask) is use of Cucumber. – But that’s not too important for this post.</p>
<h3 id="very-first-impression">Very First Impression</h3>
<p>Anyway,<br />
I’d first read a few books before getting my hands dirty. (“Ruby Best Practices” and some of “The Ruby Way”). What I read was exciting enough: Ruby seems to be a language with decent pedigree, inheriting aspects from Lisp and the emphasis on message-passing from SmallTalk (as well as e.g. the power of Regular Expressions from Perl).<br />
Also cool was e.g. Ruby’s dynamic features. Everything is an object, objects pass messages between each other. And so by overriding a few magic methods, some pretty cool things can be done. – e.g. the <code>method_missing</code> method is called if the object was called with a method that wasn’t defined on that object; so an object overriding this can have different behaviour.</p>
<p>That Ruby isn’t a low-pedigree language surprised me. ‘cause I kindof thought of Ruby as a “slightly prettier Python”. (It really isn’t, the philosophies of the two languages are quite different).<br />
And while I’d heard Ruby documentation was ’good’, it was ‘good’ by-way-of “here’s an example of probably what you’ll want to do”.<br />
And, well, if all someone knew was “Ruby on Rails”, then it’s kindof a good indicator that that person (prob’ly) doesn’t know how to program.</p>
<p>Steve Yegge also gave the language well-nuanced praise: that he didn’t <em>like</em> the language, but he found himself using it for everything when he had the choice; that he didn’t <em>know</em> the language, but he found he didn’t need to read the documentation while writing it (unlike other languages he was more familiar with).</p>
<h3 id="actually-using-it">Actually Using It</h3>
<p>I’d say, Ruby isn’t as nice a blub language as Python is. To me it feels like a blub language, but with a message-passing system.</p>
<p>I guess I don’t like it as much coming from a Scala background:<br />
“Ruby’s nice ’cause you can map/reduce over lists” … just like Scala. But without pattern matching.<br />
And Ruby has nice “no brackets” syntax … like Scala. (Except in Ruby, it’s like <code>o.m(x,y,z)</code> can be <code>o.m x, y, z</code>; in Scala it’s more like <code>x.op(y)</code> can be written as <code>x op y</code>; in Haskell it’s <code>f(x,y,z)</code> must be written as <code>f x y z</code>). – Also, in Scala, operator overloading works for any symbol which is a valid method name, whereas Ruby takes C++’s approach.</p>
<p>That Ruby has symbols (like Lisp) is one thing I certainly do like about it, though.</p>
<p>And I guess I don’t like it as much coming from a Haskell background:<br />
Say what you like about how shit Haskell documentation can be; (and I suppose outside “being too academic”, large-scale shit like Lenses can be god-damn atrocious to read). But at least it’s clear what <em>types</em> things have.<br />
Ruby documentation makes clear what <em>messages</em> the objects receive. – The expectation is that the documentation give examples of different ways to use the method. Fucking good luck to you if the documentation lacks that. – This is slightly exasperated by Ruby’s “there’s more than one way to skin a monkey” philosophy, wherein a call to the same method-definition with different kinds of arguments ought to do the-right-thing.</p>
<p>And I guess it kind-of, sort-of makes sense for those familiar with Ruby, but I was surprised to learn that methods like <code>map</code>, etc. accept <em>only</em> procs; even if an objects method receives the same type of argument as an equivalent proc, the higher-order methods only take procs.<br />
– The lack of tuples (in the same sense as Haskell or Scala or Python) also seems strange to me.</p>
<p>But the biggest woe I have with Ruby at the moment is “wtf errors”, presumably from the magic. – It’s not completely uncommon in statements calling Capybara (and therefore, Selenium, and ChromeDriver) to throw an <code>&quot;undefined method 'map' for 0:Fixnum</code> (or <code>nil:NilClass</code>), when the statement contains no calls to map, nor any numbers/nil values. (I guess as a hint, the same statement may sometimes throw other errors about connection problems for some pipe).<br />
– i.e. the call-stack from the exception doesn’t show the actual call-stack.<br />
It’s possible, but very difficult, to debug this sort of thing. I still haven’t figured it out.</p>
<p>– All that said; this was on an non-idiomatic codebase I’d inherited. And I’m by no means yet comfortable with writing Ruby.</p>
<h3 id="conclusion-hopes">Conclusion / Hopes</h3>
<p>So I find the syntax and semantics of Ruby conflict with what I’d expect, coming from a Scala/Haskell/Python background.<br />
I’m not saying Ruby is a <em>bad</em> language. It looks like it’s pretty nice at writing message-passing paradigm programs. – But I don’t yet have love for the Ruby environment.</p>
<hr />
<h4 id="btw-about-cucumber">Btw, About Cucumber</h4>
<p>Cucumber is a tool to help write “executable specifications”. The specification is written in e.g. Gherkin; the main aspect of a Gherkin specification is its sequence of Given/When/Then steps, written in a natural-language like English. – Cucumber tests will then bind these steps to code by matching the steps against a regex, and executing some code for that.<br />
(In terms of “does the program pass tests”, this is kindof a costly abstraction to make, and for programmers-only, it’s easier to just write the executed code directly. – The purported benefit of writing executable specifications is more about communication: first that those involved in writing/reviewing the specification come up with an agreement of what the program ‘is’, &amp; what terminology/phrases to use when discussing it; second that you get a (readable!) “living document” which describes what features the program has).</p>
<p>The automated testing suite is still quite young (currently working on getting it stable). I’m interested in seeing what difficulties come up in maintaining it (both from a technical and ‘social’ standpoint).</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>My Hope for Political Discussion</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/argument/2016-10-15-my-hope-for-political-discussion.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/argument/2016-10-15-my-hope-for-political-discussion.html</id>
    <published>2016-10-15T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-10-15T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on October 15, 2016
    
        by Richard Goulter
    <br/>
    
    Tags: <a href="/tags/politics.html">politics</a>
    
</div>

<p>The other day something wonderful happened in a chat group I’m in.<br />
Upon reading David Wong’s excellent <a href="http://www.cracked.com/blog/6-reasons-trumps-rise-that-no-one-talks-about/">discussion of rural voter mindset</a>, a friend made the remark like “we need more ‘empathic explainers’, rather than ‘explainer’ articles”.</p>
<p>I agree with the sentiment.. but my mind thinks in ways like “what are the obstacles”.<br />
So I can agree that the stated “people aren’t sharing articles which empathetically discuss the other”, and prob’ly “it’s difficult to find resources to help emphathise with the other”.. essentially I’d say the people apparently don’t want to sympathise with the other; and maybe the infrastructure in place is such that they’re unlikely to.</p>
<hr />
<p>Taking an example. My understanding is Fox News was made as a ‘safe space’ for right-wing ideology. But it’s not hard to believe the right has <a href="https://praxis.ink/2016/08/the-conservative-media-echo-chamber-has-made-the-right-deaf-to-reality/">“constructed an intellectual ghetto that no one else wants to visit”</a>.</p>
<p>The title of the previous link refers to an echo chamber; I’d say the problem of echo chambers isn’t unique to one side. On the other hand, though, while it’s convenient to discuss the problems as symmetric at the meta-level, I don’t believe the climate is symmetric (unless maybe considered on a long-enough timeline).</p>
<p>But, y’see… who exactly has a neutral view of things? Something it seems my news feed doesn’t seem to understand is,<br />
if you ask a non-fanatic Clinton supporter “who’s going to win 2016 election?”, they’re likely to say “oh, probably Trump” prob’ly followed by “so many voters are idiots”;<br />
and similarly a non-fanatic Trump supporter, “oh, probably Clinton” prob’ly followed by “the elites &amp; MSM have pretty much rigged the system”.<br />
– Or, rather, “who’s going to win? probably not my candidate”.<br />
And the next iteration of thought then ought to be .. “gee, people seem to always think their side is losing; but, really, <em>those</em> people are the ones with power”.<br />
– I don’t mean “people are biased”. My lament is that people are <em>unaware</em> that their opponents often think in the same <em>form</em> as they do.</p>
<p>And if people don’t recognise <em>forms</em> of thought like this.. how can we expect people to themselves become more empathetic to opinions they don’t know about?</p>
<hr />
<p>I like Miller’s Law. I think Wikipedia’s phrasing is like “Suspend judgement until you’ve listened to find out what statement you’re hearing is true about”.<br />
My understanding is more like this. No one genuinely says something while thinking “hey this is dumb of me to say”; but many genuinely expressed opinions are gross or otherwise dumb.<br />
Like “how could this guy be so stupid” dumb. (ProTip, “because he’s racist/sexist/gross” isn’t sufficient effort to count as “listening”).<br />
– Ergo, if a statement sounds really awfully dumb in such a way you couldn’t pass Intellectual-Turing-Test for it, you’ve not understood the truth the statement brings.</p>
<p>Sturgeon’s Law is probably another nice law here: “90 percent of everything is crap”.</p>
<p>– With the above two in mind, what fucking point is there in the common anger in how politics usually gets discussed: “look, someone from the other tribe said something dumb!”. (Watch <em>any</em> John Oliver or Daily Show video to see this form of statement). – It’s <em>so</em> satisfying to see how stupid those from the other tribe are. (Well, beneath the anger, anyway).</p>
<p>The other tribe is disgusting <em>by definition</em>.<br />
The other tribe isn’t bad at the things you think the other tribe is bad at; the other tribe is bad at things your tribe is good at.</p>
<p>And your tribe is bad at things the other tribe is good at.<br />
– In reaction to “people are biased; I’m a person and so I don’t know what things I’m wrong about”, I suppose a rational response would be to have people who can disagree with you on-hand so you can find out what you’re wrong about. Who does that? I mean, I think it’s fine that people aren’t truth-seekers like this. But still.</p>
<p>Short of that, for myself, I’d say it’s possible to reason about the things you’re wrong about by their form.<br />
Tools and rules ought to work impartially.<br />
If someone from the other tribe would be a complete-fucking-idiot for saying the same kindof thing, then prob’ly you should hold off.</p>
<p>(Other heuristics are like, e.g. “the world is a complicated place; unqualified or unnuanced statements are probably wrong overall, though may contain some truths”, or forms like “if the other side were consistent about X, then they would say/do Y”, etc.).</p>
<hr />
<p>“The purpose of the internet is to say all sorts of random shit, and then defend what you say as if it were God’s own truth” is something like a tweet I saw once. I quite liked it.</p>
<p>I’d love to see an adaptation of a particular xkcd comic.<br />
Not the “someone on the internet was <em>wrong</em>” one. (The artist is still a smug piece of shit there; holding that the artist’s opinion is probably the right one).<br />
The one which goes “there are too many competing standards, we need a new standard to bring them together” and suddenly there are N+1 competing standards.<br />
– There are too many dumb opinions on the internet. Someone ought to give a right opinion with nuance showing people the errors in their thinking. And suddenly there are N+1 dumb opinions on the internet.</p>
<p>I vaguely recall an old Bertrand Russell quote(?) … <a href="http://quoteinvestigator.com/2015/03/04/self-doubt/">this one</a>. “The fundamental cause of the trouble in the modern world today is that the stupid are cocksure while the intelligent are full of doubt”.<br />
(Russell apparently had some good quotes; e.g. <a href="https://www.brainyquote.com/quotes/quotes/b/bertrandru403503.html">“Why is propaganda so much more successful when it stirs up hatred than when it tries to stir up friendly feeling?</a>, <a href="https://en.wikiquote.org/wiki/Bertrand_Russell">“Nine-tenths of the activities of a modern Government are harmful; therefore the worse they are performed, the better.”</a>).<br />
– I’d adapt this idea a bit: those sensible enough to know that expressing political opinions is fucking annoying know to not share their opinion.</p>
<p>If you had a dumb opinion, how would you know?<br />
Surely you’d still feel your opinion superior, that “the people need to know!”?</p>
<hr />
<p>The way Facebook and Twitter structure their interaction also shapes how people think.</p>
<p>Tumblr is prob’ly the worst, wherein you don’t get to see responses to posts; so propaganda can proliferate uninterrupted.</p>
<p>Facebook is ‘notorious’ in this respect for its filter-bubble, wherein its newsfeed only shows you parts of things.. – But on the whole, filtered-information-shapes-thought has been around for ages; it’s why English translations of the Bible were so controversial at first. (It’d bypass the in-place power structure, right).<br />
– But, really, wouldn’t it be great if your tribe could have such influence over mainstream media and education, etc. such that the views of the other tribe were pretty much unheard of?</p>
<p>I’d say the limitation with Facebook is it’s “among friends”. And if your friends aren’t INTJs, arguing doesn’t seem to be so welcomed.</p>
<p>I don’t think Twitter is necessarily limited by its 140-character posts. People seem to chain them well enough, mostly. – I even prefer it for that; the cost of a tweet is much lower, so it’s easier to share interesting tweets.<br />
But the inevitable problem is, you’re defining your own stream of information.</p>
<hr />
<p><a href="https://popehat.com/2014/10/10/strange-seeds-on-distant-shores/">“fish don’t know that they’re in water”</a>. (The quote continues “We’re so surrounded by people who think like us, that it’s impossible to see that what we think are universal truths are just our local culture. / We can’t see it until we get outside of it.”).<br />
– The quote is well enough in theme with the above; the article is a nice discussion of the culture-wars, going all the way back to English Civil War.</p>
<p><a href="http://status451.com/2016/01/06/splain-it-to-me/">Alice Maz’s utterly fantastic post here</a> discusses, ostensibly, how different people view interactions on Twitter differently; and goes on to discuss ‘status-games and signalling’; how the social games people play forms culture. (And how the same actions get seen as normal or as rude depending on which cultural group you’re from).</p>
<p>Similarly good is anything from Jonathan Haidt discussing morality.<br />
His book “The Righteous Mind” discusses humanity’s righteousness as “a feature, not a bug”.<br />
The most fascinating model from the book is the <a href="http://moralfoundations.org/">Moral Foundation Theory</a>. (The link includes a paragraph discussing MFT for modelling the culture wars of recent decades in the US).</p>
<hr />
<p>I use the terms “tribal” and “the other” a lot in the above; for a good overview of tribalism, I’d recommend <a href="http://slatestarcodex.com/2014/09/30/i-can-tolerate-anything-except-the-outgroup/">“I can tolerate anything except the outgroup”</a> (although it is rather long, yes).</p>
<p>While of course all models are wrong, some models are useful; and I’d think tribalism well-covers the culture wars, and you’d be hard-pressed to find a different model you can substitute in its place.</p>
<hr />
<p>If there’s any sense to the above, it’s a “takes one to know one” kinda thing.<br />
In that respect, I don’t suppose I’d hope for “people to get along better”, or “people to be all super-rational”, etc. – But surely at some point after enough anger and outrage, people have to be aware of the rules of the game?</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Future Cop LAPD</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/games/2016-10-07-future-cop-lapd.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/games/2016-10-07-future-cop-lapd.html</id>
    <published>2016-10-07T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-10-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on October  7, 2016
    
        by Richard Goulter
    <br/>
    
    Tags: <a href="/tags/games.future%20cop.html">games.future cop</a>
    
</div>

<p>Future Cop LAPD is an old game, released for PlayStation One, as well as PC.</p>
<p>It looks like there are <a href="https://gaming.youtube.com/game/UCqgd3IH34aVYaV-P8FUt6aQ#tab=2">dozens</a> of videos about it on YouTube, getting ~1k-10k views each. The comments are usually filled with “man, this was such a cool game”.</p>
<p>Sadly, as happens with ‘legacy’ games, it doesn’t look possible to purchase on modern systems. Even on Sony’s ‘PSOne Classics’, it looks <a href="https://store.playstation.com/#!/en-us/games/future-cop-lapd-(ps3-psp)/cid=UP9000-NPUJ00739_00-0000000000000001">only available for PS3, PSP</a>. (Presumably it’s not further avaible on PS4 or PSVita due to licensing/rights issues).</p>
<p>– For myself, I have vague recollections of the game, on a family-friend’s PlayStation.</p>
<p>The gist of the game is you play as a transforming mech/hovertank, with an arsenal of machinegun/rockets/mortar (or various upgrades). The gameplay is either a single-player campaign with the usual bells &amp; whistles, or a ‘MOBA-style’ match against another player (or an AI): ‘MOBA’ in that you control a powerful unit, but victory depends on getting a weaker AI-controlled unit to reach the enemy’s base.<br />
– I don’t know which game would’ve been first with MOBA gameplay. I’ve heard <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Herzog_Zwei">Herzog Zwei</a> on the Sega Genesis as one of the first RTS/MOBA games. – These days, the game AirMech gets a mention in terms of “games with transforming mechs and underling units”.</p>
<p>Watching a couple of the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=v760C4AmJfQ">hard</a> <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_uqECVDAngI">levels</a> of this MOBA-style gameplay, I do get the impression that there’s a much greater demand for polish in games these days. It looks like “wow this game was cool” is tained with nostalgia and forgotten memories:</p>
<p>– For one, the gameplay design looks somewhat stunted; in both of these videos, the winning strategy is apparently quite similar. Since the victory objective is “get one of your tanks inside their base”, it’s better to pick the tank which can take punishment. (A potential alternative, I guess, is ‘pick a weaker tank, but from closer to the enemy base’; this doesn’t seem viable?). This also seems to require a certain amount of points have been built up first.<br />
– But, like. It strikes me that in the video, the enemy AI has captured towers on the player’s side, and the player doesn’t seem to see benefit in destroying the tower.<br />
– That enemy missiles travel the same speed as the player’s hovertank strikes me as a cute feature; that the player’s mortar (which can apparently destroy a tower in one hit) is so slow that the dynamic of “destroy a tower” is apparently “fire a mortar, then kindof wait around for the mortar to land” feels.. lame.<br />
– Ammunition is kept as one large amount, rather than smaller amounts which could be replenished at a base. (The effect is, the possible-gameplay-time is the limit; when you run out of ammo you lose. Smaller-but-replenishable instead demands moderation: the short-term cost of firing is much higher).</p>
<p>– In terms of ‘polish’… not so much ‘bad graphics’ (which I’d call ‘charming graphics’), so much as the poor interface: the camera feels wonky, which is perhaps balanced by the simple-ish maps, and short range on enemy towers. The enemy spawning a super-tank is apparently quite a big event, but the UI doesn’t make a big deal of it. There’s no healthbar on towers/tanks (YMMV); no timer or other indication of when a destroyed tower will respawn.<br />
Outposts can be captured once. Idk, it just feels strange that there’s apparently not any (expensive) way for an outpost to be re-captured.</p>
<p>I guess ’cause of the ostensible simplicity of the gameplay, there’s some ambition for I-could-do-that-remake. (e.g. <a href="https://theunemployedartist.wordpress.com/2016/03/22/the-project-future-cop-lapd-remake/">this</a> artists amazing recreation of the mech from the cutscenes. Wow). – “We don’t do it because it’s easy; we do it because we thought it would be.”.<br />
– I’ll totally admit that in an undergrad module, I made an abysmal-failure of an attempt to make something inspired by Future Cop LAPD. – All the same, you’d think that e.g. the maps of the MOBA gameplay would be something more available on the internet.</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>On Programming and Testability</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2016-09-21-on-programming-and-testability.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2016-09-21-on-programming-and-testability.html</id>
    <published>2016-09-21T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-09-21T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on September 21, 2016
    
        by Richard Goulter
    <br/>
    
    Tags: 
    
</div>

<p>I’ve been reading some interesting blogposts recently:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>This summary of <a href="https://blog.acolyer.org/2016/09/14/why-functional-programming-matters/">“Why Functional Programming Matters”</a>, (I’ve not read the piece it summarizes, would probably be interesting) argues roughly that the usual pitch of FP is its purity (“no side effects, no having to reason about side effects”), &amp; that this is a bad pitch. Rather, the benefits FP brings are that it offers a better way to write programs modularly (just as control structures allow for modularity where GOTO doesn’t).</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dawFyaWvFg4">“Beyond Design Patterns”</a> talk at PHP Conference Barcelona is a fascinating view on the GoF Design Patterns (which I’ve not read up on – this talk provides a context which might make them more bearable to look at).<br />
<a href="https://pinboard.in/u:rgoulter/b:f41d9c055c12">My notes here</a>, but the key point he makes is that the GoF Design Patterns come down to patterns of information flow. This relates to Alan Kay’s emphasis that ‘OOP’ really ought to be more about the <em>messages</em> between objects.</p></li>
<li><p>The <a href="http://fabiopereira.me/blog/2010/05/27/ttdd-tautological-test-driven-development-anti-pattern/">Tautological Unit Test</a> <em><em>anti-pattern</em></em>. (Because SDLC dipshits can’t communicate whether a concept is good or bad without using the word “pattern”). The post emphasises that tests ought to make assertions about a code’s behaviour, rather than the code’s implementation. It somewhat defeats the point of a “ensure nothing broke” test if you have to update it as you update the program under test. – Tests are more likely to become tautological, the post suggests, through over-use of mocking. (A small example is provided, to try to illustrate the point).</p></li>
<li><p>cf. <a href="http://c2.com/cgi/wiki?PortsAndAdaptersArchitecture">“Ports and Adapters”</a>, which sometimes is mentioned in terms of making a system testable. (In “Working Effectively with Legacy Systems”, the idea of a ‘contact point’ is brought up; i.e. a point wherein you can change/inject a dependency without having to modify the code using it). – “Ports and Adapters” somewhat suggests for ‘large’ components, but these ideas all seem the same to me.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>My fresh, recent understanding of this last point is that in order to be able to inject things, constructing/initialising objects (using “new”) within methods is bad.</p>
<pre><code>class SomeInterestingClass {
  // ...
  public function computeSomething($x) {
    $service = new ServiceFromOtherModule(); // Can&#39;t be changed in here
    return $service-&gt;compute($this-&gt;val, $x);
  }
}</code></pre>
<p>The way to replace this, then, would be to store <code>$service</code> as a property, initialised in constructor instead of “where it’s used”, which can be <code>set</code>. And maybe some more complicated variation for if this class we depend on needs to be initialised with variables the constructor.<br />
– The same more/less applies if the ‘dependency’ is a function call, etc.</p>
<p>My understanding is, then, that for non-trivial computations, “testing behaviour” comes down to assertions on how mocked-up classes/functions are used. Some white-box understanding of how behaviour is implemented is needed to know what can be stubbed. – This somewhat makes unit tests a ‘declarative’ companion to the code: “In this circumstance, this should happen”.</p>
<p>Rephrasing the above in roughly terms of ‘information-flow’: I’m guessing that at least some white-box knowledge of what kinds of messages are received (from what kind of sender), what kinds of messages are sent (to what kind of recipient) is an inevitability; perhaps it’s that it becomes a tautology when the mocking explicitly (albeit limitedly) declares the same messages/relations which the SUT code does.</p>
<p>– But I don’t know. It’s something I’d like to think about some more.</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>On QA Automation Blogposts</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2016-09-18-on-qa-automation-blogposts.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2016-09-18-on-qa-automation-blogposts.html</id>
    <published>2016-09-18T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-09-18T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on September 18, 2016
    
        by Richard Goulter
    <br/>
    
    Tags: <a href="/tags/test-automation.html">test-automation</a>, <a href="/tags/writing.html">writing</a>
    
</div>

<p>I’ve been reading up on the topic of test-automation.</p>
<p>One kindof useful resource has been <a href="https://www.thoughtworks.com/insights/software-testing">ThoughtWorks’ insights blog</a>, but my feelings towards this are mixed.<br />
Some of the posts have great insights, others are more mundane; and there’s a fetishization of nouns which makes wading through the bullshit to find the useful tips all that much harder.</p>
<p>As an example of the latter; in response to DHH saying “TDD is dead”, everyone apparently blew-their-fucking-minds. – That makes no sense to me, unless you’ve fetishized ‘TDD’ to mean ‘some specific thing which is the best, &amp; which we all should do’.<br />
Which is bullshit.<br />
Either your current practices in making software work well, in which case it doesn’t matter one way or the other whether ‘TDD’ is proclaimed ‘dead’; or there are ways you can improve your software development (in which case, it doesn’t matter whether ‘TDD’ is proclaimed better than Jesus).</p>
<p>(After reading Steve Yegge’s <a href="http://steve-yegge.blogspot.sg/2008/02/portrait-of-n00b.html">“Portrait of a n00b”</a>, I suspect closer to the truth is “all software is bad, all the time”; but that some approaches are less-bad in some circumstances).</p>
<p>If programmers had better propensity for moderation, this wouldn’t be so bad.</p>
<p>But fetishizing nouns is more annoying noise than anything else. (Although I suspect it also indicates immaturity).<br />
The other flavours of blogposts tend to come in 1) “here’s this fundamentally useful concept you might not’ve heard of”. (e.g. describing the Test Pyramid, or that tests should assert about behaviours, executable specifications should be written declaratively, etc.), 2) “here are good ideas for ways to do things”.</p>
<p>The trouble with “here are good ideas” is … it comes across as “obvious” while everyone’s still unable to readily apply it. e.g. one blogpost discussed “what to automate”: it mentioned ‘repeated, tedious/painful processes’, which makes sense, but the more salient point written was that “when you’re busy, you might not notice that these things can/should be automated”.<br />
– Simply saying “automate tedious/repetitive processes” is tautological. Saying “be aware that there may be things you’d benefit from automating” comes from experience.</p>
<p>It’s largely natural for programmers to ‘program’ without considering testability of their code. Some computations are hard to test. – I wish the blogposts were focussed more on “here’s why we ended up in a state where testing became difficult” (or, “here’s how we’ve improved; here’s why we were doing things we’ve improved-from”).</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>

</feed>
