<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Richard Goulter's Blog</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//atom.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog/" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//atom.xml</id>
    <author>
        <name>Richard Goulter</name>
        <email>richard.goulter+blog@gmail.com</email>
    </author>
    <updated>2015-08-18T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <entry>
    <title>Reflection on My Reflection</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/meta/2015-08-18-reflection-on-my-reflection.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/meta/2015-08-18-reflection-on-my-reflection.html</id>
    <published>2015-08-18T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-08-18T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on August 18, 2015
    
        by Richard Goulter
    <br/>
    
    Tags: <a href="/tags/rumination.html">rumination</a>, <a href="/tags/cs3216.html">cs3216</a>, <a href="/tags/elitism.html">elitism</a>
    
</div>

<p>It’s been a year since I took CS3216 at NUS.<br />
It’s quite a fun course, working on web app technologies. (For context of those who aren’t aware, almost all the coursework involves teamwork, and entry to the course is by-way-of application.).</p>
<p>– I want to reflect on <a href="http://blog.nus.edu.sg/cs3216rgoulter/2014/09/06/reflection-on-assignment-1/">one of the blogposts I wrote</a>; but to say “hey, what I wrote was great” is awful. The blogpost was warts-and-all, though, so let me reflect on it a bit..</p>
<p>(NOTE 2015/08/22: enough people I showed <em>the</em> post to liked it; I was told by a labmate I was famous for my blog [which I sincerely doubt], which I figure to mean the blogpost I’m hand-wringing over here..)</p>
<h2 id="cs3216-the-elite">CS3216 the Elite</h2>
<p>– Complaints over the exclusive nature of entry into CS3216 made their way onto NUSWhispers; these complaints were met with contempt or ridicule.<br />
(The worst of the complaints being a notion of “CS3216 is for smart/great kids; if I get in I’ll be able to be smart/great.”. – I mean, if you tell students “this class is for smart students, but you’re not invited”, what the fuck d’you expect students to feel?).<br />
The justification given by <a href="https://www.facebook.com/notes/ben-leong/on-cs3216cs3217-and-elitism/10153053255577549">Prof Ben Leong</a> seems to be along the lines of “CS3216/7 lets top-tier students come together and make cool stuff”. This would make sense if every student in 3216/7 were top-tier, and 3216/7 evinced a nature of incubating quality projects (i.e. projects which live on after semester’s end.). – The latter doesn’t happen; and I’ve reason to doubt that everyone who gets into 3216/7 is “top tier”..<br />
Anyway, <a href="http://nuswhispers.com/tag/5641">Beng’s post</a> is much better. (Beng is, somewhat famously, the creator of NUSMods, which is used by pretty much every NUS student to plan their timetables.). Beng’s post points out he wasn’t born amazing, and worked hard to get to where he wanted. But what I like most about it, – and where Prof Leong’s post also agrees with this – is the idea of doing work outside of school to improve one’s skill.</p>
<p>What I would add/emphasise, though, is that.., like. While “getting work done”, and being industrious are fine virtues, I reckon when it comes to programming, this should be a matter of interest: play around with C++11, because building things “natively” is fun, and so then you can be the guy who knows C++ on the team. Play around with some non-Java JVM language, like Scala or Clojure, because these things are more fun to program than Java. Learn one of Haskell or Erlang, because their not-C/Java/Python nature makes them fascinating to a student who otherwise won’t encounter them in coursework. Learn your way around a terminal, because working in a full-screen terminal looks cool-as-shit and like leet-hacker-skills. etc. etc. – I mean, obviously not <em>all</em> of these things; obviously not <em>all</em> at once.</p>
<h2 id="git">Git</h2>
<p><a href="../../posts/programming/2014-04-26-online-resources-for-git.html">I wish everyone knew git better</a>.</p>
<p>During 3216, I had a teammate who “didn’t know git”, and in a reflection blogpost <a href="http://blog.nus.edu.sg/cs3216rgoulter/2014/09/06/reflection-on-assignment-1/">I complained about that</a>.<br />
The truth of the matter is more complicated than the guy “didn’t know git”; his incompetencies were far broader than that. And there were worse things than that post complains about. But, anyway. (Said guy was <em>in his final year of a CS degree</em> at this time. Managed to graduate with “honours”, also. And is now working at a bank prob’ly earning much more money than me. I’m not sure what the moral of the story is there.).</p>
<p>I hadn’t read that blogpost since writing it.<br />
I was quite surprised to see it wasn’t as whiney as I recalled. (There’s still a lot of whining; just not as much as I recalled.).<br />
It’s not all bad. Roughly, it goes over:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>The “renaissance” programmer: not just good at coding, but also at living “the good life”; improving himself, e.g. also in areas of communicating with others, and health/wellbeing.</p></li>
<li><p>Code examples of a top-tier 3216/7 student; including merge conflicts pushed to master. (This is what the blogpost was written for.).</p></li>
<li><p>‘How am I supposed to feel about that?’.</p></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="tone">Tone</h2>
<p>I’m split about the tone.</p>
<p>There’s some self-chastisement; but it’s all in terms of “I’m being a jerk” and “I wish I were a better man”, and not in terms of “if my team sucked, it’s because I didn’t take more responsibility”. – The whole “sorry to be a dick” and then being a dick is the lamest part. (On further thought, the bitterness here takes the sarcasm to another level.).</p>
<p>But I also admire some of the anger; there’s at least anger at the “3216 is for talented kids” pitch. (It’s awful for someone to kiss their own ass, right; but, hey, if I’m criticising myself, only fair for me to like some things, too.).</p>
<p>– Where I’m most ambivalent is about the anger shown at incompetency.<br />
At worst, being angry at someone’s incompetence potentially has the childishness of incredulity at someone not knowing something obscure. It’s unhelpful to be angry at people for something they needn’t have known, and unwelcoming. People inherently deserve to be treated with respect, even if they’re incompetent.<br />
On the other hand, it’s outright surprising that a final year Computer Science student wouldn’t know (or wouldn’t even learn basic) Git/VCS, let alone someone taking an ‘elite’ course. (NUS’ degree required taking software engineering courses, which teach that, so this isn’t the case of “well, computer science doesn’t necessarily involve programming.”.). – Moreover, in a course which by its nature demands quickly learning new skills/concepts (web app dev for people who haven’t done web app dev before), it’s disappointing, perhaps disrespectful, to not learn basics of what you’re working on.<br />
<em>Frustration</em> is at least understandable, in any case.</p>
<p>(EDIT 2015/08/22: I think it’s rare, really rare, to find people who can mediate situations really well. And confronting people is hard. What I wish in general is that it’d be much easier to applaud and admire mediation than to admire posts where someone gets angry at someone who does stupid shit.).</p>
<h2 id="excellence">Excellence</h2>
<p>What I didn’t remember from the blogpost was the notion of “pursuing excellence”.<br />
Not sure the term “renaissance programmer” is widely used, but then as now I like the idea of someone who pursues excellence in understanding the tools of their craft; pursues excellence in how to otherwise be efficient at their craft (e.g. good health, good communication skills).<br />
I think this is where I link to that <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pGFf3SRP1bE">Bruce Lee video, ‘Be Water My Friend’</a>.</p>
<p>I’m inclined to say anyone who spends a blogpost complaining about the incompetencies of their teammates has further to go to reach such excellence..</p>
<p>Probably also one man’s “excellence” is another person’s “competent”, I’d guess. – With Vim, say, it’s a <a href="../../posts/programming/2014-04-26-tools.html">process of continually learning</a> about commands you’ve not heard of before, and noting how to improve on that.<br />
Surely a healthy, helpful attitude to have. :-)</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Curious About GoodReads Reviews and Bullying</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/argument/2015-08-13-curious-about-goodreads-reviews-and-bullying.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/argument/2015-08-13-curious-about-goodreads-reviews-and-bullying.html</id>
    <published>2015-08-13T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-08-13T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on August 13, 2015
    
        by Richard Goulter
    <br/>
    
    Tags: <a href="/tags/goodreads.html">goodreads</a>, <a href="/tags/internet%20abuse.html">internet abuse</a>, <a href="/tags/bullying.html">bullying</a>, <a href="/tags/for%20such%20a%20time.html">for such a time</a>
    
</div>

<h2 id="preamble-bullying-is-bad-try-telling-the-bullies-that">Preamble (Bullying is Bad, Try Telling the Bullies That)</h2>
<p>Amazon and GoodReads are both prominent places to review books. – My Humble Opinion is to prefer GoodReads, since I don’t use Kindle.</p>
<p>I’ve written before about GoodReads: <a href="../../posts/romance/2014-03-08-paradox-of-fandom.html">Wondering</a> if people who read books more were less impressed by good books than people who weren’t as well read; and looking at <a href="../../posts/romance/2014-07-16-readers-and-lists-on-goodreads.html">GoodReads’ lists</a>, remarking hwo snobbish some of the lists were. (Guess which books came under “didn’t finish”, “most hated”?).</p>
<p>So. Recently there’s been <a href="../../posts/romance/2015-08-09-open-letter-regarding-kate-breslins-for-such-a-time-and-diversity-in-romance.html">some controversy</a> in romancelandia.<br />
A quick glance at the <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/18008080-for-such-a-time?from_search=true&amp;search_version=service_impr">GoodReads page</a> for the book shows the reviews filled with at least a dozen 1-star reviews written since August (i.e. after Wendell’s letter.). <em>Many of which even openly admit to not having read the book</em>. – I don’t care how righteous your cause: if you review books as 1-star, <em>without having read the book</em>, you’re a bully.<br />
– Fortunately, at the time of writing the book still has an average of 3.9/5, which is at least par for “really good book”, and about as high as many authors (in the romance genre, at least) are able to achieve. (And somewhat higher than the more mainstream unpopular books.).<br />
– Counterpoint: What about if you borrow a book from a friend, read 1 page, then 1-star it; would that still be bullying? I do think “hate reading” is a thing: reading something knowing you’re going to hate it. Surely you’ve got to be pretty bitter to do <em>that</em>. – But even more simply, if you’re going into a book with that much prejudice.. I think you misunderstand the point of “books let you understand different viewpoints.”.</p>
<p>More importantly: does your giving a 1-star review benefit the community? Is it constructive to the community?<br />
Of course I think there’s room for people to give 1-star reviews. The usual expectation is that they’ve read the book.</p>
<p>– Maybe worth noting is I couldn’t find this book by searching for its title. It’s unclear whether the name was too obscure, there’s a bug in the algorithm/index, the book was unlisted automatically for receiving 1-star reviews(?), the book was unlisted on request (for being too hateful, or for being a target of hate). Or it could just be me.</p>
<h2 id="questions-can-reviews-tell-us-anything">Questions; Can Reviews Tell Us Anything?</h2>
<p>In any case. It would be fascinating to visualise some of this stuff.<br />
Numbers don’t lie. (Interpretation of numbers does, but that’s a different issue.).</p>
<p>But, I mean, I’m not just curious about this controversy. Things I’d love to see:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>What has the average rating of this book been over time? Per number of reviews? What has the number of 5-star, 1-star reviews been over time?</p></li>
<li><p>What has the average rating been for other RITA nominations, from publication to nomination, from nomination to awards, and after the awards?<br />
 <em>Compared to previous years, this would offer a control of what a typical RITA nomination looks like. Oh, comparing to a non-RITA book may be interesting too.</em><br />
 <em>“For Such a Time” is somewhat controversial. Is the data for “For Such a Time” different in an interesting way to show this? (Could you know, given reviews of a book, whether it’s similarly “controversial”?).</em></p></li>
<li><p>Does a reviewer’s “average rating” (the average of the ratings they’ve given) follow a trend over time / over the number of books read?<br />
 <em>I would think it tends toward 3 or 4 over time.</em><br />
 <em>How similar would this be between readers?</em><br />
 <em>If some books do gain controversial attention, do the people giving 1-star, 5-star reviews share similar traits? (e.g. number of books read, average rating.).</em><br />
 <em>If some books do get extreme reviews (1-star, 5-star) from controversial attention, how anomalous does this look per the reviewer?</em></p></li>
<li><p>What percentage of a books reviews are read by “fans”?<br />
 <em>Are books reviews at all by ‘fans’? (e.g. people who liked other books from the same author.).</em> <em>How consistent are authors? (If readers liked some authors book, is there a likelihood that a large proportion of readers will rate the books consistently?).</em></p></li>
<li><p>Does the distribution of 1-5 star ratings for a book follow a trend over time?</p></li>
</ul>
<p>…Do these things vary by genre? (Clearly I care only about Romance Novels here; and even then only some sub-genres.).<br />
I’m not saying these questions are well-formed or anything. (And I clearly have suspicions about some things). But it’d be interesting to see some data related to this. (Though, if you have better questions, I would be interested to hear them.).</p>
<p>Trying my best, I think those who I disagree with might be curious about things like:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Is there any association between words used in the blurb (hinting at content) and average rating, 1-star, 5-star ratings? <em>Rationale would be, books with unpleasant content get more 1-star reviews.</em></p></li>
<li><p>Do 1-star, 5-star reviewers tend to make use of the same words as each other?</p></li>
</ul>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Tabs vs Spaces and Elastic Tabs</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2015-08-12-tabs-vs-spaces-and-elastic-tabs.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2015-08-12-tabs-vs-spaces-and-elastic-tabs.html</id>
    <published>2015-08-12T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-08-12T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on August 12, 2015
    
        by Richard Goulter
    <br/>
    
    Tags: <a href="/tags/tabs%20vs%20spaces.html">tabs vs spaces</a>, <a href="/tags/elastic%20tabs.html">elastic tabs</a>
    
</div>

<p>I was surprised to discover I’ve not written about “tabs vs spaces” before, despite all my love for writing about editors.</p>
<h2 id="whats-tabs-vs-spaces-all-about">What’s “Tabs vs Spaces” All About?</h2>
<p>The less something matters, the more programmers will argue over it. (No, not “bikeshedding”, which is similar, but doesn’t quite account for things like programmers arguing over different programming languages.).<br />
Grammarians are similar, I suppose.</p>
<p>The biggest part of this ‘holy war’ consists of people arguing over whether it’s better to indent with tabs or spaces. Roughly (and without any bias): if you indent with spaces, then you know that it anything aligned will still be aligned on another computer; <em>but</em>, people will have different preferences as to whether to indent with 2-spaces, 4-spaces, or some other size.<br />
Tabs let you change the size of indentation, so when using tabs to indent, people can set the tabwidth to how they prefer it. The chief downside to this is you can’t use tabs to <em>align</em> things, because aligning means you want certain characters to be in the same column, which fixes the tabwidth.</p>
<p>– The middle ground to this is often called “mixed”: use tabs for indentation, and spaces for alignment.</p>
<h3 id="practicality">Practicality</h3>
<p>There are some practical problems about this, too:<br />
Setting up “mixed” tabs/spaces in an editor isn’t as easy as only-spaces or only-tabs.<br />
Even using tabs-only can be messy, since it’s not always clear whether pressing the Tab key on a keyboard will insert spaces or a proper tab; so a poorly configured editor may insert spaces into what was previously a tabs-only file.<br />
Modern editors are pretty capable at treating ‘4-spaces’ as if they were a single indentation character: pressing a Tab key will insert 4 spaces, and pressing backspace will delete 4 spaces.</p>
<p>Working on teams, it’s important for everyone to follow the same code style.<br />
– I’ve heard stories of my friends where there was a sequence of commits which were purely for tabifying or untabifying the codebase.<br />
And, obviously, the diffs shown between these changes simply show “THE WHOLE FILE WAS DELETED, THE WHOLE FILE WAS CREATED.”.</p>
<h2 id="why-this-is-whole-thing-is-dumb">Why This is Whole Thing is Dumb</h2>
<p>One of these programming ‘holy wars’ is dumb? You don’t say!</p>
<p>But, still.<br />
HTML/CSS manages to separate <em>content</em> from <em>form</em>. - <a href="http://www.csszengarden.com/">CSS Zen Garden</a> is a notable example of the <em>exact same content</em> being displayed very differently with different themes.<br />
– While <em>some</em> languages currently make use of whitespace/alignment as part of syntax (famously Python, jokingly whitespace, but also even things like Haskell [in places]), most don’t. – So, it’s kindof dumb that something which doesn’t affect content is treated as content by tools. (Well, tools like Git will offer to ignore whitespace changes in diffs; but, again, tools can be difficult to use.).<br />
For that to work, you’d have to have some program to decode from a neutral source file so that it’s displayed how a programmer likes in an editor (2-space indent or 4-space indent; braces aligned in the same column; spaces between declarations; etc. etc.), as well as some program to encode to the source file in a neutral layout. – This is just pie-in-the-sky, of course, and it’s not hard to come up with cases where this wouldn’t work. (e.g. comments, which the programmer may prefer not aligned relative to the syntax.).</p>
<h2 id="tabs-and-tabstops">Tabs and Tabstops</h2>
<p>But, *gasp*, I have been a little biased in my description:<br />
The simplest way to use tabs is strictly at the start of a line for indentation. If used in the middle of a line, different people/programs have different opinions as to whether the <em>correct</em> thing to do is to skip <em>tabwidth</em> spaces, or to align to the nearest 8th column.<br />
– To me this sounds stupid; when I was using org-mode, I noticed it used tabs after some text as a placeholder for spaces: Emacs insisted on tabwidth being 8, while a Vim plugin insisted on tabwidth being 6.</p>
<p>Yet, both of these are bastardisations of the <a href="http://web.archive.org/web/20090615091848/http://www.nabble.com/-long--Re:-Elastic-tabstops-p20025677.html">“tabstop” as used by typewriters.</a>:<br />
The “tabstop” was a position set so than when pressing the ‘tab’ key, the paper would align to that point. This helped to write Tables. (TABle, TAB).</p>
<pre>
  Tab stop bar:   |------V-----------------V------|

  Typing:         Dear Sir,
                  We are pleased to offer:
                         French Vanilla    $12.00
                         English Custard   $ 8.50
                         Irish Whiskey     $22.40

                  Sincerely,
                  Bramble & Botts Dairy
</pre>
<h2 id="elastic-tabstops">Elastic Tabstops</h2>
<p>I first saw mention of elastic tabstops on Neovim’s issues page.<br />
<a href="http://nickgravgaard.com/elastic-tabstops/">Elastic tabstops</a> are much closer in spirit to aforementioned typewriter tabstops.<br />
The GIF perhaps explains the concept best:</p>
<div class="figure">
<img src="http://i.imgur.com/7MsEnA9.gif" alt="" />

</div>
<p>Although, as far as “implementation”, it seems to just render current tab(s) differently:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>While editors which haven’t yet implemented the elastic tabstops mechanism may not align some text properly in files where tabs were used with elastic tabstops, the problem isn’t that bad. All leading tabs (indentation) will be okay, and the chances of text not aligning correctly diminishes as the width between tabstops increases. So if you plan on switching to elastic tabstops in the future, and wish to choose a code style with that in mind (to use now), I suggest using tabs with fixed tabstops every 8 characters (or more) across. Alternatively co-workers can use tabs with fixed tabstops of whatever size they like as long as no one tries to line up text for anything other than indentation.</p>
</blockquote>
<h3 id="drawbacks">Drawbacks</h3>
<p>It seems the idea was conceived in 2006. It’s 2015. That said, Neovim is in theory going to be easier to contribute to than Vim. And it has already been implemented in some array of text-editors.. so the discipline isn’t impossible.</p>
<p>But this <a href="http://programmers.stackexchange.com/questions/137290/what-are-the-drawbacks-of-elastic-tabstops">StackExchange thread</a> makes some excellent points:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Personal preference</p></li>
<li><p>Technical implementation: It’s different to what most text editors have done, and isn’t widely available. This limits adoption.</p></li>
<li><p>Who cares?: Developers have done well enough as-is for the last however many years; people can set aside subjective disagreements if they <em>really</em> need to, anyway.</p></li>
<li><p>Impact: Compare the quote above; using leading tabs for indentation is pretty much the same behaviour as elastic tabstops; and the other adjustments aren’t all worth the novelty.</p></li>
<li><p>Corner cases: Considering the Python snippet:</p>
<pre><code>def foo( bar,
         xyzzy ):
    wibble()</code></pre>
<p>it’s probably something elastic tabstops will mess up, without code intelligence.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>– For what it’s worth, I still don’t see this as inherently more natural than the “mixed” solution.</p>
<p>Even so, it appears that elastic tabstops are the kind of thing which could be adopted into codebases iteratively. (I imagine this would look ugly for tools which don’t support elastic tabstops; but the same is true if a programmer assumes tabwidth to be a certain value anyway, so it’s not like the issue would be new.).</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Open Letter Regarding Kate Breslin's "For Such a Time", and Diversity in Romance</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/romance/2015-08-09-open-letter-regarding-kate-breslins-for-such-a-time-and-diversity-in-romance.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/romance/2015-08-09-open-letter-regarding-kate-breslins-for-such-a-time-and-diversity-in-romance.html</id>
    <published>2015-08-09T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-08-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on August  9, 2015
    
        by Richard Goulter
    <br/>
    
    Tags: <a href="/tags/rwa.html">rwa</a>, <a href="/tags/for%20such%20a%20time.html">for such a time</a>, <a href="/tags/diversity.html">diversity</a>
    
</div>

<p>So, <a href="http://roselerner.tumblr.com/post/125859575893/letter-to-the-rwa-board-regarding-for-such-a-time">Sarah Wendell’s Letter to the RWA regarding “For Such a Time”</a> came to my attention; shortly after <a href="http://www.suleikhasnyder.com/2015/07/rwa15-in-nyc-tale-of-two-conferences.html">Suleikha Snyder’s rundown of RWA</a> did.</p>
<h2 id="snyders-post">Snyder’s Post</h2>
<p>Snyder’s post is easier to summarise: She first says how great it was to meet with friends at RWA, then goes on to lament her other experience she describes as “a convergence of microaggressions.”. Credit where credit is due, Snyder’s smug condescension and angry tone are on point:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>And they had to share a nomination slate with a Christian romance set in a concentration camp with a Nazi hero and a Jewish heroine who converts at the end. It finaled in two categories. TWO. And I have no freaking clue how. Was no one Jewish involved in the awards process? Do we really need, in this day and age, to have a Jewish person tell us that concentration camp romance is deeply fucked up? Shouldn’t that be, like, COMMON KNOWLEDGE?</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="wendells-post">Wendell’s Post</h2>
<p>Wendell’s begins with an ostensibly much more neutral tone, although manages to share many of the same attitudes.<br />
Key points:</p>
<ul>
<li>The nomination upset some people. Let’s try to discuss why.</li>
<li>Book was set in a concentration camp. The Holocaust was an awful part of human history.</li>
<li>The romance is set between a Nazi and a Jew; this is a pretty unhealthy imbalance of power.</li>
<li>The book is a retelling of Esther set in the Holocaust. The Nazi hero is redeemed in the end. The heroine converts to Christianity.</li>
<li>Redeeming a character who participated in a genocide is insensitive.</li>
<li>It’s demeaning to have a Jewish character convert to Christianity, as this belittles/demeans her identity.</li>
<li>That this book was nominated creates an environment where writers of other faiths feel unwelcome.</li>
<li>Wendell expresses disappointment that this book was considered for RWA’s highest honour; “doesn’t understand” how judges would like such an “offensive and insensitive” book.</li>
<li>Wendell questions the judgement of those involved in the process of writing, publishing, nominating the book.</li>
<li>Nomination of the book tarnishes a community of a genre which has changed for the better.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="common-thesis">Common Thesis</h2>
<p>Before replying to these points, I’ll note that both share the same thoughts: <em>“The romance community is becoming more diverse, and this book is offensive, shouldn’t have been nominated, or even written.”</em>.</p>
<p>I find this attitude to not only be toxic, but also exclusionary, and not what reading is all about.</p>
<h2 id="on-diversity-in-media-and-romance-novels">On Diversity in Media and Romance Novels</h2>
<p>Diversity in content isn’t controversial at all. If there are a wide variety of books to read, it benefits the readers, so then not every book involves a handsome billionaire/duke ending up hitched to the hitherto unnoticed wallflower. Lack of monotony is nice. Perhaps more importantly, it’s good if everyone can find a book they like.<br />
– Reading a book is quite special, though, since it let’s you into the mind of the character. The cliche is the reader has experienced many lives by reading through books. And there’s nothing particularly special about putting your feet in the shoes of someone very similar to you.</p>
<p>– I don’t, however, think that just because a book is written and is different necessitates that the book should sell well, or even win awards.</p>
<p>The word “diversity”, as used by Snyder and Wendell, and the social justice crowd, tends to refer to people of different identities; namely: sex/gender, race, and sexuality. They’re also referring to different aspects: diversity in authors, diversity in characters, and diversity in readers.<br />
(I’ll say, personally, as a man who reads romance novels, it’s kinda funny that the lack of men reading, or writing, in the romance community isn’t brought up as a problematic aspect of the romance community; “for women, by women” is a statement of pride rather than an exclusive statement.).</p>
<p>A key concern for Wendell is that the ‘insensitivities’ of this book may make others feel uncomfortable; that people should be uncomfortable with this book, and it should go away.<br />
A key concern for Snyder is that discussion of ‘diversity’ makes the many feel uncomfortable; that people shouldn’t feel uncomfortable with diversity, and those who are should adapt or go away.</p>
<p>– What troubles me is the thought “Romance ought to be a welcoming community / but not for people like this.”; “Diversity is wonderful / so long as people think how I think.”. Because a community homogeneous in its thought, which excludes attitudes it doesn’t like, sounds nothing like diversity to me.</p>
<h2 id="problematic-romance-novels">Problematic Romance Novels</h2>
<p>Diverse or not, a story featuring a Nazi and Jew romancing, set in the Holocaust is obviously offensive, right?<br />
– Well, be honest: even if the characters were on equal footing, wouldn’t you then complain about <a href="http://anonymousdeveloper.tumblr.com/">Jew-sploitation</a>; that the author was appropriating experiences which weren’t her own, and making money off of an awful period in human history? I’m sure someone would have said it.</p>
<p>But, please, let’s not wash over Romance Novels as if each is a paragon of virtue.</p>
<p>I don’t mean “sex before marriage omg” or “man-slut ends up with the girl”:<br />
If “imbalance of power” is a problem for relationships, it’s unfortunate that “romancing the (fake) governess” is such a common trope. Similarly, the “forced-into marriage” trope is problematic in terms of consent.<br />
In terms of more specific examples:<br />
Judith McNaught’s “Whitney, My Love” is a love-it-or-hate-it novel featuring (apparently) a hero who physically beats the heroine.<br />
Lisa Kleypas’ “It Happened One Autumn”, features the hero forcing himself on a resisting heroine; Kleypas then somewhat corrects this in “Scandal in Spring” emphasising this behaviour as <em>bad</em>, which is followed by a scene where the heroine locks the hero in a room, putting the key down her pants (keeping a non-consenting hero in the room).<br />
Loretta Chase’s “Lord of Scoundrels” features the heroine shooting the hero, a somewhat extreme (and uncriticised) example of intimate partner violence.<br />
Sherry Thomas’ “Tempting the Bride” features the hero giving the heroine a novella wherein he describes having sex with the heroine while she’s restrained (against her will) to a bedpost.<br />
etc. etc. – These examples just from the top of my head. And I’ve not read as many books as some others have.</p>
<p>This shouldn’t become a game of Problematic Olympics.<br />
Or, rather, I think that to scream &amp; shout “hey, that’s offensive, don’t write that!” stifles creativity. – The above books are all outstandingly good books, it’d be a shame if they weren’t read for having problems.</p>
<p>I’ll admit I have no faith that cries of “that’s offensive” will be used with discernment.</p>
<h2 id="different-attitudes-amongst-diversity">Different Attitudes Amongst Diversity</h2>
<p>I imagine neither Snyder nor Wendell would be a fan of George Carlin’s (somewhat pro-feminist) <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fwMukKqx-Os">“don’t let people control what you can or can’t say”</a>.</p>
<p>In any case, it seems an underlying assumption is that “offending others is bad; and making people uncomfortable is at odds with creating an inclusive environment.”. Holding this at the same time as thinking “making the establishment feel uncomfortable is progress” seems a bit inconsistent to me.<br />
What’s certainly not clear is how writers from different (and even conflicting) viewpoints are to express themselves without offending others. “Communal Harmony” vs “Individual Expression” is a conflict any diverse community deals with.</p>
<p>Snyder’s attitude is certainly a not-here-to-make-friends righteousness; and when what’s under discussion is of politics, religion or ethics/morality - subjects people often disagree with each other on - an attitude like that doesn’t foster welcoming for those who differ from the norm.<br />
– Rather than “everyone can think what they want to, so long as it’s behind closed doors, not offending anybody”, it would be nice if people with conflicting viewpoints could come together and discuss things with civility.</p>
<p>– In that regard, it’s deeply, deeply disappointing that both Snyder and Wendell think it would be better if the book weren’t written.<br />
It would probably be worth buying a copy of this RITA-nominated book, if you haven’t already: <a href="https://store.kobobooks.com/en-US/ebook/for-such-a-time-1">Kobo</a>, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/For-Such-Time-Kate-Breslin-ebook/dp/B00DWA695U">Amazon Kindle</a>.</p>
<h2 id="where-to-go-from-here">Where to Go From Here</h2>
<p>Just a reminder that Romance Novels are happy books.<br />
Getting angry with each other and yelling is probably not a constructive effort.</p>
<p>Read a book you hated? (I know I have.). Good! This means your reading includes a diverse range of authors.<br />
Discuss, complain, write angry blogposts if you like. – But don’t aim to silence or other voices; especially not under the guise of “diversity”.</p>
<p>“Don’t be a dick” is always great advice, especially when interacting with others online. I’d love to see more examples of people transcending disagreements, understanding one another and discussing different viewpoints without righteous hobnobbery.<br />
Clearly I need to work on this, just as Wendell might. (Jonathon Haidt is one of the few I know of who can do this well. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vs41JrnGaxc">A relevant, humourous TED talk</a>. Prob’ly the most important link on this page, and it’s left all the way at the bottom..).</p>
<p><strong>Update</strong>: Corrected a few egregious spelling mistakes.</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Impressions of Emacs and Org Mode</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2015-08-07-impressions-of-emacs-and-org-mode.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2015-08-07-impressions-of-emacs-and-org-mode.html</id>
    <published>2015-08-07T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-08-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on August  7, 2015
    
        by Richard Goulter
    <br/>
    
    Tags: <a href="/tags/emacs.html">emacs</a>, <a href="/tags/org-mode.html">org-mode</a>, <a href="/tags/vim.html">vim</a>
    
</div>

<p>I’m a moderately capable Vim user.<br />
I’ve not quite gained the habit of trying to <em>constantly</em> improve using Vim; but at the same time, I’m not exactly using it as something only slightly better than Notepad++.</p>
<p>Lately I’ve been taking quick glances at Emacs.<br />
I was impressed by <a href="http://bling.github.io/blog/2013/10/27/emacs-as-my-leader-vim-survival-guide/">this post from GitHub user bling</a>, who suggests that Vim is the better <strong>editor</strong>, with a much larger/better plugin-writing community; but suggests that Emacs makes for a better Development Environment.<br />
– Org mode makes sense as a ‘gateway drug’ to Emacs..</p>
<h2 id="org-mode">Org Mode</h2>
<p>The testemonials you see of Org Mode compell interest. In terms of a comprehensive note-taking/task-managing format, I’m not aware of any other formats/doctrines which are anywhere near as popular.</p>
<p>There are a couple of ‘implementations’ of a subset of Org mode’s features, for vim: <a href="https://github.com/jceb/vim-orgmode">jceb/vim-orgmode</a>, and <a href="https://github.com/hsitz/VimOrganizer">hsitz/VimOrganizer</a>.<br />
The latter is somewhat less popular, and doesn’t include even a token README, and hasn’t had updates in a year. – It may still be alright, but I’ve not tried it.<br />
The former has had commits within the last couple of months, does have a README, and is more popular.</p>
<p><code>vim-orgmode</code> is mostly alright.<br />
From when I’ve tried to make use of it, there’re a few annoyances I’ve had:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Plain Lists: It was a battle with the auto-indentation to write unordered-lists.</p></li>
<li><p>Header Tags Alignment: While I encountered issues with this in Emacs also; the problem with <code>vim-orgmode</code> is that it uses <em>TABS</em> to pad out the tags after a header. Tabstop <a href="https://github.com/jceb/vim-orgmode/blob/master/ftplugin/orgmode/liborgmode/headings.py#L92">is assumed</a> (and set to be!) 6. – This isn’t exactly a problem if you’re only editing org files with <code>vim-orgmode</code>, as such; but I’m not, and it’s just annoying knowing it’s there.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>It wasn’t a problem for me, with this <code>vim-orgmode</code> plugin, that not every (applicable) part of Org mode was implemented. Org mode seems to have an extensive feature set, and I can’t (at this stage) see myself using most of the features.<br />
What was kindof interesting is that many of the Org mode things were implemented in Python as a library.</p>
<p>– While perhaps using Org mode as a poor-man’s-OneNote may not be making the most out of Org mode, I’ve also found it unclear as to the distinguishment in purpose between headers and unordered lists: I often find myself with an unordered list of things, and then will want to ‘TODO’ these.</p>
<h2 id="emacs">Emacs</h2>
<p>So, as it is, Emacs is the tool to use to manipulate Org mode.<br />
Evil mode certainly mitigates the pain of this.</p>
<p>Emacs feels like it’s an editor in between worlds:<br />
Emacs, in some sense, rightly has that “programmer’s editor of choice” feel to it: it can be customised with macros, it can be run in a terminal, a prominent irc channel, etc.; in these ways, it’s <strong>very</strong> similar to Vim.<br />
But, it also feels like it’s a ‘modern’ editor. It’s start-up time is slow. The text isn’t regular-width, regular-height; you can embed images in the editor. Installing plugins, customising features of the editor can be done through a (somewhat shabby) UI within the editor, which includes rendered buttons, textfields and other widgets.<br />
– Particularly jarring, for example, when writing in Org mode, the formatting of the text is shown as you edit. If text should be bold, then in Emacs the text is bold. Like how MS Word does it; but different than I’m used to when writing markup.<br />
Yet, Emacs just doesn’t feel as ‘polished’ as these.</p>
<p>– I ran into a problem: my Org mode looked bad. The tags were being aligned making use of tags. Org mode assumed a tab width of 8 (which somewhat defeats the point of one of the key advantages to tabs, but okay). The tab width was set to 8, but being rendered as 4-wide.<br />
– The culprit? The <a href="https://github.com/bbatsov/solarized-emacs">solarized mode</a> I was using. I looked at the code; <strong>there’s no mention of tab anywhere!</strong><br />
But also interesting (or horrifying) to note in the <code>solarized.el</code> file (about 2k LoC) features many lines of code dedicated to setting the colour for each face, for a multitude of different modes. It seems to me if you want to write a mode which looks good with this theme, then the theme would have to know about your mode, and be customized to that. – I’m thinking this is an example of a downside of Emacs’ flexibility. Or perhaps colour schemes are just hard to do properly, and this kind of upstream coupling is the best way.</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Notes, OneNote and Org Mode</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2015-07-29-notes-onenote-and-org-mode.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2015-07-29-notes-onenote-and-org-mode.html</id>
    <published>2015-07-29T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-07-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on July 29, 2015
    
        by Richard Goulter
    <br/>
    
    Tags: <a href="/tags/notes.html">notes</a>, <a href="/tags/onenote.html">onenote</a>, <a href="/tags/emacs.html">emacs</a>, <a href="/tags/org-mode.html">org-mode</a>
    
</div>

<p>Many programmers who maintain a blog, I believe, use it as a kind of note-keeping place. Programmer-y stuff can be hard; it’s easy to forget what steps to take when building some program on some distribution – especially what difficulties come up, how to overcome them.<br />
– I’ve used my blog for that.</p>
<p>I’ve also kept a programming journal.<br />
I’m not sure how common this is; I’ve never met anyone who’s done the same. One of the techniques I used was, perhaps in a similar vein to de Bono’s Thinking Hats, making use of colour: red was for things which went wrong (e.g. compiler errors which I didn’t know how to fix), green was for questions (e.g. how does X work? why is it doing that?), blue for facts, black for thoughts, purple for new ideas. – That is, when making notes, it’s useful to distinguish different kinds of thoughts.</p>
<p>When working on my Bachelor of Computing Dissertation, my Final Year Project (FYP), I also made use of Microsoft’s OneNote, in tandem with this journal-writing.<br />
– During my FYP, there were several aspects to the project which would be fun to explore at the start (e.g. how to write Eclipse plugins, inter-process communication between different programs using e.g. Apache Thrift, BNFs of the C grammar, diagrams of ASTs of various C declarations, etc.). - For this, I did prefer to write with pen &amp; paper: I’ve got a decently sized 5-partition folder filled with my notes for these (&amp; relevant print-outs).<br />
OneNote was damn useful for maintaining a series of project-related links. Early on in my FYP I was trying to compile CERN’s Cling (a C++ interpreter) on Windows. I never had any success; but OneNote was invaluable in keeping notes like the output of commands, comments from similar efforts, etc.</p>
<p>From my use and experience, being “searchable” wasn’t such a big deal. (<em>I</em> knew roughly where what I was looking for would be.). This is mitigated by OneNote’s hierarchy UX:<br />
– What I like about OneNote, in lieu of my technique with ‘colours’ to shape thought, is that OneNote naturally shapes thought into hierarchies: a notebook has sections; sections have pages; a page is where you write, either with paragraphs, or with bullet points: it’s really, really easy to make (and remove) bullet points. (typing “*” is enough for OneNote to say “hey, this is a bullet point”.).<br />
Of course, being able to paste links in is useful. And there’re icons you can (quite easily) embellish bulletpoints with (like “Important!” icon, etc.).</p>
<p>Emacs’s Org mode is … not software I’ve used.<br />
It’s “life changing” for those who do make use of it. (Apparently it’s also a nice gateway drug to Emacs. Though key aspects of Org mode exist in Vim plugins, so there’s that.).<br />
– A key philosophy behind Org mode is the idea that ‘notes’ &amp; ‘tasks’ are inter-dependent: when you note things, you’re likely to then come up with tasks; and when you manage tasks, you’re likely to note things down.<br />
At-a-glance, it looks like Emacs’ Org mode has a bunch of fancy .. interfaces, views of data: this data, written in a plain textfile, appears it’s somewhat similar to OneNote: an Org file has headings (and sub-headings, and sub-sub-..), within a heading can have the paragraphs, bullet points, etc.; each heading can have meta-data associated with it (which is where “tasks” come into it), in terms of “TODO/DONE”, custom tags, deadlines, priority, or custom properties.<br />
– There’s supposedly other fancy tosh like export-to-PDF. That I can’t say I care for.</p>
<p>A key advantage to Org mode (in native Emacs, or whether in one of the Vim ports) would be ‘lightweight’-ness compared to OneNote. (You <em>can</em> make use of OneNote on Linux, but that’d have to be by opening a web browser. Thus, internet connection required..).<br />
But I am wondering how well Org mode’s ease-of-use, in terms of inputting bullet points/etc., compares to OneNote.<br />
I’m also wondering whether, in lay usage, the fancy different-perspectives/searching really make that much of a difference.</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Case Study in Vim Plugin Development</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2015-07-22-case-study-in-vim-plugin-development.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/programming/2015-07-22-case-study-in-vim-plugin-development.html</id>
    <published>2015-07-22T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-07-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on July 22, 2015
    
        by Richard Goulter
    <br/>
    
    Tags: <a href="/tags/editors.html">editors</a>, <a href="/tags/vim.html">vim</a>
    
</div>

<p>I don’t know a lot about writing plugins.<br />
My own experience goes as far as trying to write a plugin for Eclipse (which gets <em>very</em> complicated as soon as a plugin isn’t a “monolithic” bundle); as well as writing a quite small plugin for my <a href="https://github.com/rgoulter/c-worksheet.vim">C worksheet</a>. (The fanciest thing it does is to download a JAR archive dependency if not present in the system.).</p>
<p>So I’m not particularly qualified to say what is or isn’t a good plugin architecture, etc.</p>
<p>I recently came across the problem: “In Vim, use <code>*</code> to find next occurence of current selection in visual mode”.<br />
Vim doesn’t offer this behaviour out of the box.<br />
The fella on IRC was using <a href="https://github.com/nelstrom/vim-visual-star-search">nelstrom/vim-visual-star-search</a>. The readme for this somewhat helpfully links to <a href="https://github.com/thinca/vim-visualstar">thinca/vim-visualstar</a>. – Neither of these repos is outstandingly popular.</p>
<p>Nelstrom remarks “Looks like it uses a lot more code to do pretty much the same thing. Is it better?”.</p>
<p>Nelstrom’s plugin is simple enough to show here:</p>
<pre><code>&quot; From http://got-ravings.blogspot.com/2008/07/vim-pr0n-visual-search-mappings.html

&quot; makes * and # work on visual mode too.
function! s:VSetSearch(cmdtype)
  let temp = @s
  norm! gv&quot;sy
  let @/ = &#39;\V&#39; . substitute(escape(@s, a:cmdtype.&#39;\&#39;), &#39;\n&#39;, &#39;\\n&#39;, &#39;g&#39;)
  let @s = temp
endfunction

xnoremap * :&lt;C-u&gt;call &lt;SID&gt;VSetSearch(&#39;/&#39;)&lt;CR&gt;/&lt;C-R&gt;=@/&lt;CR&gt;&lt;CR&gt;
xnoremap # :&lt;C-u&gt;call &lt;SID&gt;VSetSearch(&#39;?&#39;)&lt;CR&gt;?&lt;C-R&gt;=@/&lt;CR&gt;&lt;CR&gt;

&quot; recursively vimgrep for word under cursor or selection if you hit leader-star
nmap &lt;leader&gt;* :execute &#39;noautocmd vimgrep /\V&#39; . substitute(escape(expand(&quot;&lt;cword&gt;&quot;), &#39;\&#39;), &#39;\n&#39;, &#39;\\n&#39;, &#39;g&#39;) . &#39;/ **&#39;&lt;CR&gt;
vmap &lt;leader&gt;* :&lt;C-u&gt;call &lt;SID&gt;VSetSearch()&lt;CR&gt;:execute &#39;noautocmd vimgrep /&#39; . @/ . &#39;/ **&#39;&lt;CR&gt;</code></pre>
<p>Thinca’s is <a href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/thinca/vim-visualstar/master/plugin/visualstar.vim">certainly longer</a>:</p>
<pre><code>function! s:search(type, g)
  let s:count = v:count1 . a:type
  let reg = &#39;&quot;&#39;
  let [save_reg, save_type] = [getreg(reg), getregtype(reg)]
  normal! gv&quot;&quot;y
  let text = @&quot;
  call setreg(reg, save_reg, save_type)

  let [pre, post] = [&#39;&#39;, &#39;&#39;]
  if !a:g
    ....
  endif

  let text = substitute(escape(text, &#39;\&#39; . a:type), &quot;\n&quot;, &#39;\\n&#39;, &#39;g&#39;)

  let @/ = &#39;\V&#39; . pre . text . post
  call histadd(&#39;/&#39;, @/)
endfunction</code></pre>
<p>(Code truncated at <code>....</code> for brevity).</p>
<p>With my current proficiency, I’m sure Nelstrom writes closer to how I’d write:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Cites any sources / close inspiration.</p></li>
<li><p>Leaves comments explaining anything non-trivial. (Which Thinca doesn’t do AT ALL. Not even for functions!).</p></li>
</ul>
<p>Even from this snippet it’s clear that Thinca’s is of higher quality. I’d base that one the use of functions to do caretaking of the editor environment. – It’s not clear what the argument <code>g</code> is for (like the <code>g</code> in substitute?), but the ommitted lines seem to take care of some edge case.<br />
– Something to note, I guess, it seems that in both cases the VimL is ‘impure’ in providing read-only info. (Again, I’m not sure if it’s possible to get this without the caretaking.).</p>
<p>Not hatin’ on Nelstrom: while the Vim community has some excellent plugins, I think most Vim users don’t bother touching VimL enough to learn how to do this kindof thing.</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Comical Conservative</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/argument/2015-07-12-comical-conservative.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/argument/2015-07-12-comical-conservative.html</id>
    <published>2015-07-12T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-07-12T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on July 12, 2015
    
        by Richard Goulter
    <br/>
    
    Tags: <a href="/tags/politics.html">politics</a>, <a href="/tags/righteous%20mind.html">righteous mind</a>, <a href="/tags/liberals.html">liberals</a>, <a href="/tags/conservatives.html">conservatives</a>
    
</div>

<p>Came across <a href="https://www.facebook.com/TheComicalConservative/photos/a.133361476797039.26402.133352176797969/626100744189774/?type=1">this</a> on Facebook:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Liberal: I am pro-choice<br />
Me: Can I choose my own health care?<br />
Liberal: No.<br />
Me: Can I choose what I do with money I earn?<br />
Liberal: No.<br />
Me: Can I choose how I defend my family and possessions?<br />
Liberal: No.<br />
Me: What can I choose?<br />
Liberal: An abortion, and a same sex marriage.<br />
Me: I don’t agree with your opinions.<br />
Liberal: OH MY GOD STOP OPPRESSING ME YOU RACIST SEXIST BIGOT!</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It’s not particularly hard to figure out that this comes from a socially-conservative poster.<br />
I wouldn’t criticise this post for the quality of its opinion; but what’s perhaps disappointing is the “the guy I disagree with is so stupid” nature to it. It’d be unfair, though, to say that this attitude is unique to this post (or to social conservatives).</p>
<p>Lately I’ve been listening to some of Jonathon Haidt’s talks/lectures.<br />
In particular</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=b86dzTFJbkc">‘Why conservatives don’t like social justice and science’</a>, in which Haidt discusses is “Righteous Mind” thesis, how humans develop morality in regards to care/loyalty/etc., and discussing socially liberal and conservative attitudes in regards to this. Haidt finishes the talk with a resounding criticism of the social sciences discrimination against conservatives. (– Ha, Karen Straughan chips in in the comments section).</li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=v3o-F94S4FI">‘How Common Threats Make for Common Ground’</a> (TED talk), in which Haidt points out this hyper-partisanship makes each side deny the looming threats we face, since each threat has become a political issue.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iOu_8yoqZoQ">‘Three Stories About Capitalism’</a> (TED talk), in which Haidt discusses that some problems are “wicked problems” since they invoke our moral beliefs to resolve them, and the political disagreement over capitalism,</li>
<li>and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1OnTTWkAv_E">this talk to some law students</a> (somewhat pessimistic).</li>
</ul>
<p>Haidt is a social psychologist; one of his main theses is that, lately, American politics has become extremely polarised. Roughly, in “The Righteous Mind” he points out our morality brings people together, but also divides us, as we sacrilise things which are “good”, and so anything opposing it is “bad”.<br />
e.g. social liberals ‘sacrilise’ women’s rights, so the women’s right to choose abortion is far more important than a fetus’ “right to live” or so.<br />
– The utterly refreshing thing about these lectures from Haidt is the utterly neutral way he discusses the social left/right.</p>
<p>With that in mind, (great if you’ve seen any of the videos, but in any case):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Liberal: I am pro-choice</p>
</blockquote>
<p>“Pro-choice” is a heavily charged term used to refer to a pro-abortion attitude (as opposed to “pro life” [or “anti-choice”]).<br />
It seems a slightly mis-placed phrasing. Though, as with many arguments, what’s under attack is the Liberal’s <strong>sincerity</strong> about “people should be free to do what they want”.</p>
<p>Haidt discussed that, while everyone values “liberty”.<br />
The social left means “liberty” as in enabling everyone to have the freedom to choose what to do. (e.g. everyone should be able to go to college.).<br />
The social right means “liberty” as in not interfering with individual choices. (e.g. don’t tax successful people more for being successful.).</p>
<p>Next, the post somewhat attacks the liberal attitudes on some points:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Me: Can I choose my own health care?<br />
Me: Can I choose what I do with money I earn?<br />
Me: Can I choose how I defend my family and possessions?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Briefly,<br />
‘Can I choose my own health care?’ ObamaCare seems to’ve been quite nasty for the middle class.<br />
‘Can I choose what I do with money I earn?’ is slightly poorly phrased. Social conservatives prefer small government / lower taxes; but any taxation would still be the govt imposing what an individual does with the money. I mean, I think with better phrasing, (perhaps “Will I be rewarded for working harder than others, and taxed at the same rate as everyone else?”) it’d be easier to push a conservative viewpoint.<br />
‘Can I choose how I defend my family and possessions?’ is an unfortunate one; the second amendment issue seems politically charged, and I understand only in the US is anyone so in favour of ‘civilians having assault rifles’. (Though, e.g. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RSk1UkqBx58">Dana Loesch</a> seems to be able to argue quite well in favour).</p>
<p>Again, this is all “look how un-liberal the social left’s attitudes are”.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Me: What can I choose? Liberal: An abortion, and a same sex marriage.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Somewhat interesting to note that these two things are abhorrent to the religious right.</p>
<p>You’d think a socially conservative attitude, in favour of a limited government, would be argue something more like “it’s not the government’s duty to interfere with individual liberty in these matters, [even if they are abhorrent]”.<br />
It’s certainly a more interesting argument than “it’s morally right for this to be able to happen, why is it not legal?”.</p>
<p>Still, this certainly makes the post look tacky.<br />
For the social left, it’s great that a woman can have an abortion, and that two people who love each other can marry!<br />
– I guess what’s intended is a mocking along the lines of “this is the only ‘liberty’ the social left cares about[; they don’t <strong>really</strong> care about liberty, like we do]”. And America is all about liberty/freedom.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Me: I don’t agree with your opinions. Liberal: OH MY GOD STOP OPPRESSING ME YOU RACIST SEXIST BIGOT!</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This part doesn’t flow at all from the rest.<br />
Again, with regards to Haidt, the social left ‘sacrilises’ the oppressed; so, anyone who disagrees with the left is a ‘racist’, is a ‘sexist’.<br />
Also fun is that these words short-circuit argument. To be ‘racist’ is to be a heathen to the social left. Anything ‘racist’ is bad, and so it’s not worth considering the argument, because of course anything ‘racist’ cannot be true.</p>
<p>Adding to the depiction of the Liberal as someone who doesn’t care about liberty, this paints the Liberal as someone who isn’t into civilised discourse, as well as someone who is incapable of defending their opinion.</p>
<p>I guess what’s disappointing is that, rather than simply saying “social conservative attitudes aren’t dumb”, the post reaches further and says “social left attitudes are dumb”. It’d be just as easy to make a similar “social right attitudes are dumb” post, which would almost certainly be similarly tacky.</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Beware Radicalisation</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/argument/2015-07-01-beware-radicalisation.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/argument/2015-07-01-beware-radicalisation.html</id>
    <published>2015-07-01T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-07-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on July  1, 2015
    
        by Richard Goulter
    <br/>
    
    Tags: <a href="/tags/feminists.html">feminists</a>, <a href="/tags/feminism.html">feminism</a>, <a href="/tags/hacker%20culture.html">hacker culture</a>, <a href="/tags/sjw.html">sjw</a>, <a href="/tags/community.html">community</a>
    
</div>

<p>Shot(s): <a href="https://medium.com/@maradydd/when-nerds-collide-31895b01e68c">When Nerds Collide</a> by <span class="citation">@maradydd</span> / Meredith Patterson, 2014 Mar (Bonus: <a href="https://medium.com/@maradydd/okay-feminism-its-time-we-had-a-talk-about-empathy-bd6321c66b37">Okay, Feminism, It’s Time We Had a Talk About Empathy</a>, 2013 Oct).<br />
Chaser: <a href="http://esr.ibiblio.org/?p=6642">Meredith Patterson’s valient effort is probably doomed</a> by <span class="citation">@esrtweet</span> / Eric S. Raymond, 2015 Jan.</p>
<p>Well, at least ERS hedges by saying ‘probably’.</p>
<p>I read the above two pieces from Patterson some time ago.<br />
‘When Nerds Collide’ is a particularly brilliant piece of writing you should go read. In short, it’s a response to the tensions which come up in terms of tech and ‘inclusivity’. THe piece is filled with a plethora of amazing points, but at its core discusses the idea of a “weird nerd”, who was previously rejected by mainstream culture but now happens to wield power.<br />
The ‘peace offering’ here is more of a “you want inclusivity? here’s how you can have that.”; it’s a call for respect/construction rather than aggression/destruction.</p>
<p>(The second essay isn’t bad, either, but whereas the aforementioned essay is inclined to use progressive lingo, this one uses techie lingo and suggests that many of the efforts in the “women in tech” issue make for anti-patterns.).</p>
<p>I came across ERS’ above essay when someone linked to it on Twitter as part of a culture-war over some GitHub repo.<br />
The key line used was “total rejection of the SJW doctrine”.</p>
<p>It’s not a bad piece of writing.<br />
But it’s not a piece of writing which is going to make any friends. It’s clearly not written to be the kind of article which makes friends. – <em>except maybe</em>, maybe those who transcend the tribalism and genuinely care about “justice and inclusion”.</p>
<p>Yet, ERS’ does include the key phrase “defense of hacker culture”; maradydd’s writing more/less features this term, also.<br />
– If there is any kind of peace offering in ERS’ piece, “shut up and show us the code”; the same conclusion maradydd’s piece ends with.</p>
<p>I don’t think any “kumbaya, let’s all sit around the campfire and be friends” attitude can outright reject ERS’ piece. At least, “ERS = bad, maradydd = good” seems as unlikely to win friends as “SJWs = bad, hackers = good”.<br />
Hostile tone aside, iterate the points of ERS’ piece without hostility. (e.g.; as with <strong>pretty much every argument</strong>, “the other side aren’t <strong>sincere</strong> in caring about the values they say they care about, otherwise they’d do …”, “some bullying happens guised as ‘being inclusive’. This is concerning.”, etc.). – Perhaps a more neutral way of phrasing a conclusion would be “be inclusive, but have zero tolerance for bullying” or so.</p>
<p>In any case, what I note foremost from this is how ERS’ post manages to be much more hostile than maradydd’s (“they’re the enemy / we can’t let them gain an inch”) while following the same kinds of points.<br />
ERS’ piece is much more radical / radicalising than maradydd’s more grounded piece.<br />
And it’s concerning that such a tribalistic “they’re the enemy / we’re the good guys” (and therefore, any action we do is righteous, and action they do is evil) follows so closely from a more reasonable piece.</p>
<p>– Whether “code is without morality” (similar to “numbers don’t lie, interpretations do”?) holds or not is <em>probably</em> a point of contention to be had, among other points, but that can be considered some other time.<br />
I’d be more interested to transcend the arguing here and consider the tribalism and all this “kumbaya” shit, how people interact &amp; communicate (or don’t) in online places; the evils of (self-)righteousness, why it’s so much easier to spot that the other guy is an asshole (and of course you aren’t).</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Romance Tropes in Anime vs Romance Novels</title>
    <link href="http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/romance/2015-06-29-romance-tropes-in-anime-vs-romance-novels.html" />
    <id>http://www.rgoulter.com/blog//posts/romance/2015-06-29-romance-tropes-in-anime-vs-romance-novels.html</id>
    <published>2015-06-29T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-06-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on June 29, 2015
    
        by Richard Goulter
    <br/>
    
    Tags: <a href="/tags/anime.html">anime</a>, <a href="/tags/romance%20novels.html">romance novels</a>, <a href="/tags/if%20my%20heart%20had%20wings.html">if my heart had wings</a>, <a href="/tags/valkyria%20chronicles.html">valkyria chronicles</a>
    
</div>

<p>Recently I’ve finished playing <strong>Valkyria Chronicles</strong> and <strong>If My Heart Had Wings</strong>.<br />
<strong>Valkyria Chronicles</strong>, recently released for PC (earlier released on PlayStation 3) is a strategy game; featuring a bunch of cute boys &amp; girls in cutesy uniforms with rifles in an almost WWII-esque setting.<br />
<strong>If My Heart Had Wings</strong> is a ‘visual novel’; the story is about friends at a school who build &amp; fly a glider.</p>
<p>Spoilers prob’ly follow. You’ve been warned.</p>
<p>Both of these stories are anime-esque (coming from Japan), and both feature elements of romance; though, IMMHW is more focused on this aspect.<br />
I’d love to compare how the elements of narrative used in these stories compared to the (written-in-the-US) Romance Novels I know &amp; love.<br />
Admittedly, it’s a rather small and not particularly representative “sample”; I doubt many of the comparisons here extend too far.</p>
<p>VC is awfully concise in its narrative; there’re some very sweet romance-y bits in the story, though. The story is a bit camp, but one of the lines which sticks with me from the romance between Alicia and Welkin is Alicia’s declaration: “with you I’m not scared anymore”. (Or something like that).<br />
– Compared to RNs: it wouldn’t be so out of place; though, VC naturally lends itself to a much more action-oriented plot than most RNs tend to have. - My impression, though, is RNs, with so much focus on for-women-by-women, will tend to try and have more ‘girl power’ to them. So, dialogue like “I can’t live without you” isn’t uncommon, but I’m sure I can’t recall any story where anyone said “I rely on you” to the other.<br />
Overall, VC doesn’t spend so much time on its romances. The boy and the girl like each other. They do stuff together. There’s kindof a “look I love you” moment, but not particularly any ‘internal conflict’ between the characters. But it’s not particularly a huge focus of the game/story, so oh well.</p>
<p>I’d’ve thought IMMHW would’ve had more sex scenes in it, from the hoo-hah everyone seems to make about the restoration-patch, and all the “people think I’m a loser, but jokes on them, I’ve got a wheelchair-girlfriend” type comments/reviews on Steam.<br />
See, in some of the sexier RNs, there’s gotta be sex by, like, page 20 otherwise it’s considered boring. – IMMHW isn’t so quick to the chase. (Difference in medium may have something to do with that.).<br />
– Sexuality/identity, and sexual representation are waaay different in IMHHW than in the RNs. I mean, those who’re inclined to be offended by a ‘sexist’ trope would find plenty to complain about in IMMHW.</p>
<p>– Part of this is inevitably due to the difference in media between VNs and RNs: even in RNs plenty of people will get upset at the way a story was told. (Things like: ‘the hero was kindof a douchebag, the heroine deserved better’.). With VNs, choices are made which determine the outcome of which girl the main character ends up with.<br />
Sometimes IMMHW did this nicely; you choose which girl you want to spend time with, and the dialogue builds intimacy between the characters. – One particular choice, though, “whose swimsuit/boobs look the best?” is … certainly not something you’d see in RNs.</p>
<p>– On the otherhand, perhaps there’s also plenty to celebrate? In IMMHW, there’re many female characters: The school council’s president is female: authorative, fair, and compassionate. The senior student who was building the glider is female: she’s slightly eccentric, super smart, though with some faults. The other members of the glider club, who study hard to understand aeronautics, work hard to build and maintain the glider, are female. – None of these girls are treated as less for being female; the narrative shows no surprise or novelty that these characters are female. These characters aren’t treated as one-dimensional sex kittens.<br />
– It’s a cute tease, but IMMHW does pass the Bechdel test. (Not sure how many RNs would pass that; though, Bechdel test seems more of an arbitrary thing for people to be able to cry ‘sexist’ over, so <em>shrug</em>.).<br />
RNs main strength is character; mostly just the main hero/heroine. IMMHW has many characters, perhaps not all with the same depth as the H/H in RNs, but not paricularly flat characters, either.</p>
<p>That there’s a ‘choice’ of which partner to pick is somewhat quaint.<br />
In (modern) RNs, it’s fairly conventional that by the end of the second chapter or so, you’ll know who the main Hero and Heroine are, and that they’ll be end the story Happily-Ever-After. - In IMMHW, it’s not (to me) as apparent, given the breadth/depth of characters featured.<br />
(I’ve only played through one ‘route’ of IMMHW. I’m not sure how inferior/shorter other ‘routes’ of the story may be. – In some sense, VNs compare to Choose Your Own Adventure stories. Choose Your Own Romance?).<br />
– Maybe a bad example, but if Twilight where CYOR, it’d make the whole ‘Team Edward’/‘Team Jacob’ thing more fun. ;P</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>

</feed>
